<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2014-09-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>La Ravallière 1742, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 139; Auguis 1824, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 9; Tarbé 1850, 40; Bartsch 1908, 187; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 199; Wallensköld 1925, 61; Brahney 1989, 76.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(9) K 21b-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 64d-65a (anonima), O 70ac (anon.), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 29v-30v (<hi rend="italic">Monios</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 79rv (anon.), T 8v-9r (anon., but <hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>), V 10c-11a (anon.), X 21d-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), a 5rv (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>). All mss. insert this song into a corpus of texts attributed to Thibaut de Champagne, with the sole exception of R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, whose attribution cannot be considered reliable.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(9) K 21b-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 64d-65a (anonima), O 70ac (anon.), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 29v-30v (<hi rend="italic">Monios</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 79rv (anon.), T 8v-9r (anon., ma <hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>), V 10c-11a (anon.), X 21d-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), a 5rv (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>). Tutti i testimoni inseriscono questa canzone in un corpus di testi attribuiti a Thibaut de Champagne, con l’eccezione del solo R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, la cui attribuzione non può essere considerata affidabile.</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10abbac’c’aa (MW 1410, 2 = Frank 549); the original model is the crusade song <hi rend="italic">S’onques nuns hons por dure departie</hi> of Hugues de Berzé (RS 1126), of which however only the ‘a’ rhyme is feminine; 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) with a 4-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di (c’c’aa); a = <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; b = <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-u</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>; c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; the identical rhyme-word <hi rend="italic">maintenir</hi> in vv. 4 and 9 (but the two occurrences may have different nuances), <hi rend="italic">avenir</hi> in vv. 12 and 15, <hi rend="italic">vertu</hi> in vv. 19 and 27 <hi rend="italic">aidier</hi> in vv. 23 and 31; lyric caesura in v. 26 and perhaps v. 17; melody in M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVXR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, with M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVX attesting the same melodic line and R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> offering a variant of this; the melody of R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> on the other hand is entirely independent (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 204; Tischler 1997, IX n° 835).</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10abbac’c’aa (MW 1410, 2 = Frank 549); il modello originario è costituito dalla canzone di crociata <hi rend="italic">S’onques nuns hons por dure departie</hi> di Hugues de Berzé (RS 1126), dove però la sola rima femminile è la a; 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 4 versi (c’c’aa); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-u</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima identica <hi rend="italic">maintenir</hi> ai vv. 4 e 9 (ma le due occorrenze possono avere sfumature diverse), <hi rend="italic">avenir</hi> ai vv. 12 e 15, <hi rend="italic">vertu</hi> ai vv. 19 e 27 <hi rend="italic">aidier</hi> ai vv. 23 e 31; cesura lirica al v. 26 e forse al v. 17; melodia in M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVXR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, con M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVX che concordano nell’attestare la medesima linea melodica e R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> che ne propone una variante; la melodia di R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> è invece totalmente autonoma (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 204; Tischler 1997, IX n° 835).</p></metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The omission of v. 40 shows the usual grouping of mss. KOVX; the version of ms. R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, which lacks stanza V and the envoi, is fairly independent, but is basically linked to KOVX; mss. M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T as usual constitute the second branch of the tradition of Thibaut’s <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>; R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>a, while sharing some readings with M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T (vv. 12 and 22), seem to draw on a different tradition predating the compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>, and it will be appropriate to accept their readings where the variants are indifferent, especially when they are also supported by T. Graphies have been taken from ms. O. The fact that the majority of the mss. present some irregular rhymes (especially in vv. 1 and 20) and some doubtful readings (vv. 25 and 33) convinced Bédier of the existence of a corrupt archetype, but in reality none of these cases seems conclusive.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>La mancanza del v. 40 permette di raggruppare come di consueto i mss. KOVX; il ms. R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, privo della quinta strofa e del congedo, ha una lezione piuttosto autonoma, pur collocandosi sostanzialmente nel gruppo di KOVX; i mss. M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T costituiscono come di consueto il secondo ramo della tradizione del <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi> di Thibaut; R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>a, pur condividendo qualche lezione di M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T (vv. 12 e 22), sembrano attingere ad una tradizione diversa e anteriore alla compilazione del <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>, per cui converrà accettarne le lezioni in caso di alternative adiafore, soprattutto quando sono appoggiate anche da T. Come base grafica si è scelto il ms. O. Il fatto che la maggioranza della tradizione presenti qualche infrazione alla rima (soprattutto ai vv. 1 e 20) e qualche lezione dubbia (vv. 25 e 33) ha convinto Bédier dell’esistenza di una copia archetipica corrotta, ma in realtà nessuno di questi casi sembra determinante.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2014-09-27T19:29:47Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Thibaut de Champagne</titlePart><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="text" xml:id="rs.1469.fro" xml:lang="fro"><lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1">Li douz pensers et li douz sovenir</l><l n="2">m’i font mon cuer esprendre de chanter</l><l n="3">et fine amor, qui ne m’i lait durer,</l><l n="4"> qui fait les suens de joie maintenir</l><l n="5">et met es cuers la douce remenbrance;</l><l n="6">por c’est amors de trop haute poissance,</l><l n="7">qui en esmai fait home resjoir</l><l n="8"> ne pour doloir ne lait de li partir.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="9">Sens et honor ne puet nuns maintenir</l><l n="10">s’il n’a en soi sentu les maux d’amer,</l><l n="11">n’en grant valor ne puet por riens monter,</l><l n="12">n’onques encor nel vit nuns avenir;</l><l n="13">por ce vos pri, d’amors douce senblance,</l><l n="14">c’on ne s’en doit partir por esmaiance,</l><l n="15">ne ja de moi nel verrez avenir,</l><l n="16">que tout parfaiz vuil en amors morir.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="17">Dame, se je vos osasse proier</l><l n="18">mout me seroit ce cuit bien avenu,</l><l n="19">mais il n’a pas en moi tant de vertu</l><l n="20">que devant vos vos os bien avisier;</l><l n="21">ice me font et m’ocit et m’esmaie:</l><l n="22">vostre beauté fet a mon cuer tel plaie</l><l n="23">que de mes eulz seul ne me puis aidier</l><l n="24">dou resgarder, dont je ai desirrier.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="25">Quant me covient, dame, de vos loignier</l><l n="26">onques certes plus dolanz hons ne fu,</l><l n="27">et Dex feroit, ce croi, por moi vertu</l><l n="28">se je jamés vos pooie aprochier,</l><l n="29">que touz les biens et toz les max que j’aie</l><l n="30">ai je par vos, douce dame veraie,</l><l n="31">ne ja sanz vos nuns ne me puet aidier:</l><l n="32">non fera il, qu’il n’i avroit mestier.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="33">Ses granz beautez, dont nuns hons n’a pooir</l><l n="34">qu’il en deïst la cinquantisme part,</l><l n="35">li dit plaisant, li amoreus regart</l><l n="36">me font sovent resjoïr et doloir:</l><l n="37">joie en atent, que mes cuers a ce bee,</l><l n="38">et la paors rest dedanz moi entree;</l><l n="39">ensi m’estuet morir par estovoir</l><l n="40">en grant esmai, en joie et en voloir.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="41">Dame, de cui est ma granz desirree,</l><l n="42">saluz vos mant d’outre la mer salee</l><l n="43">com a celi ou je pans main et soir,</l><l n="44">n’autres pansers ne me fait joie avoir.</l></lg></div></body><back><div type="historical" xml:lang="en"><head> Historical context and
        dating </head><p>From the envoi it appears that the author is overseas; if this allusion is considered realistic and if it covers the whole text, essentially a song of separation, it must have been composed at the time of the ‘Barons’ crusade’ in which Thibaut de Champagne took part, between September 1239 and the same month of 1240.</p></div><div type="historical" xml:lang="it"><head> Contesto storico e
        datazione </head><p>Dall’accenno contenuto nel congedo si desume che l’autore si trova oltremare; se si considera realistica questa allusione e la si estende all’intero testo, che si configura tendenzialmente come una canzone di lontananza, esso dovrà essere stato composto al tempo della «crociata dei Baroni» alla quale Thibaut de Champagne partecipò, tra il settembre 1239 e lo stesso mese del 1240.</p></div><div type="notes" xml:lang="en"><head> Notes </head><p>The song exploits themes favoured by Thibaut de Champagne and in many cases developed on the basis of texts by his illustrious predecessor Gace Brulé (on his relations with Gace see for example Grossel 1987): the necessity for amorous suffering, the power of Love which brings at the same time joy and suffering, the lover’s timidity, and the value of memory and recollection which ennoble the heart. The allusions to parting and separation, however, give a new and more ‘historical’ tone to these themes. The author deliberately moves between <hi rend="italic">topoi</hi> typical of the courtly love song, in particular those focussing on the lover’s timidity, and themes characteristic of songs of separation, more grounded in reality, thus creating a hymn to true love, the memory of which overcomes distance and allows the experience of joy as well aseven in sorrow (je ne sais pas si “as well as” est la bonne traduction; je veux dire que la “mémoire” de la dame permet au poète de faire l’expérience de la joie même dans la douleur de la séparation. The (chivalric?) virtues are also obtained thanks to amorous suffering. The timid lover lacks the courage to declare himself, but nonetheless the full pain of love remains and cannot even be alleviated by the contemplation of the beloved (who is far away). So the <hi rend="italic">covient</hi> of v. 25 may refer to the imminence of farewell or, more probably, take on the sense of a past tense (as it already did in RS 273, 37) and the allusion to the eyes which do not in themselves enable the lover to see can refer back to the power of thought and recollection evoked at the end of the first stanza. The final stanza also seems to play on the interrelation between reality and memory, but the envoi brings the song back to the sphere of distance. </p><p>The first stanza in particular is dedicated to the lexical field of memory, typical of Thibaut de Champagne (see for example Dolly-Cormier 1978, Zaganelli 1982; the introduction of Brahney 1989, especially pp. xviii-xix; Grossel 1994).</p><p>[nn=9-10]<hi rend="italic">sens et honor</hi>. Virtues acquired through self-mastery «dans une résolution de toutes les antithèses existentielles, afin d’atteindre ainsi le <hi rend="italic">raffinement</hi>» (Grossel 1994, p. 436). But in the context of this song they might also designate chivalric virtues which, as in Chrétien de Troyes’ romances, are won and increased through loyalty in love’s service and also through the suffering that flows from it.</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=20)">Bédier and Wallensköld accept the reading araignier only found in R3 because of the difficulty of explaining the sense of aviser; but this verb is also attested in the sense of ‘to look, contemplate, turn one’s gaze towards’; moreover the scribe of R tends to intervene to smoothe out linguistic and syntactic difficulties. The graphy avisier of T, the only one to respect the rhyme, has a few late attestations among Guillaume de Machaut, Christine de Pizan and Eustache Deschamps, but is also found in the Prose Tristan (ed. Curtis, I, i, 92 e I, i, 118), apparently with the same sense of ‘to look, observe, scrutinise’ that it appears to have in the present passage.</p><p>[nn=29-32]The conjunction <hi rend="italic">que</hi> must have causal force (Ménard § 232) and <hi rend="italic">il</hi> does not designate God, but repeats generically the preceding <hi rend="italic">nuns</hi> (Wallensköld 1925, p. 64).</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=39)">The expression par estovoir indicates constriction, coercion (‘per forza’), but could also have the more precise sense of deprivation and lack.</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=42)">This line contains the only reference to crusading, as Wallensköld emphasises; he does not even consider this text to be a true crusading song.</p></div><div type="notes" xml:lang="it"><head> Note </head><p>La canzone sfrutta temi cari a Thibaut de Champagne e in molti casi sviluppati a partire dai testi del suo illustre predecessore Gace Brulé (sui rapporti con Gace si veda per esempio Grossel 1987): la necessità della sofferenza amorosa, il potere d’Amore che fa gioire e soffrire allo stesso tempo, la timidezza dell’amante, il valore del ricordo e della memoria che nobilitano il cuore; gli accenni alla partenza e alla separazione danno però una sfumatura nuova e più “storica” a questi temi. L’autore mantiene volutamente una certa ambiguità tra il <hi rend="italic">topos</hi> lirico della timidezza amorosa e i temi più concreti della canzone di lontananza, un inno al vero amore il cui ricordo vince la distanza e permette di provare gioia anche nel dolore. Le virtù (cavalleresche?) si ottengono anche grazie alla sofferenza amorosa. All’amante timido è mancato il coraggio di dichiararsi, ma nonostante tutto la ferita d’amore permane e non può neppure essere alleviata dalla contemplazione dell’amata (che è lontana). Così il <hi rend="italic">covient</hi> del v. 25 può riferirsi all’imminenza dell’addio oppure più probabilmente acquisire un senso di preterito (come già in RS 273, 37) e l’accenno agli occhi che da soli non bastano a vedere può rimandare al potere del pensiero e del ricordo già evocato fin dalla prima strofe. Anche l’ultima strofe sembra giocare tra la realtà e il ricordo, ma il congedo riporta la canzone nell’ambito della lontananza.</p><p>La prima strofe in particolare è dedicata al campo lessicale della memoria, tipico di Thibaut de Champagne (si veda per esempio Dolly-Cormier 1978, Zaganelli 1982; l’introduzione di Brahney 1989, soprattutto le pp. xviii-xix; Grossel 1994).</p><p>[nn=9-10]<hi rend="italic">sens et honor</hi>. Virtù che si ottengono nel superamento di se stesso «dans une résolution de toutes les antithèses existentielles, afin d’atteindre ainsi le <hi rend="italic">raffinement</hi>» (Grossel 1994, p. 436). Ma nel contesto di questa canzone potrebbero designare anche le virtù cavalleresche che, come nei romanzi di Chrétien de Troyes, sono conquistate e incrementate con la lealtà nel servizio amoroso e anche con le sofferenze che ne derivano.</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=20)">Bédier e Wallensköld accolgono a testo la lezione araignier del solo R3 a causa della difficoltà di spiegare il senso di aviser; ma questo verbo è attestato anche col senso di “guardare, contemplare, volgere lo sguardo verso”; inoltre il copista di R tende a intervenire per appianare le difficoltà linguistiche e sintattiche. La grafia avisier di T, l’unica che permette di rispettare la rima, ha qualche attestazione tarda tra Guillaume de Machaut, Christine de Pizan e Eustache Deschamps, ma si trova già nel Tristan en prose (ed. Curtis, I, i, 92 e I, i, 118), apparentemente con lo stesso senso di “guardare, osservare, scrutare” che sembra avere nel nostro passo.</p><p>[nn=29-32]La congiunzione <hi rend="italic">que</hi> avrà valore causale (Ménard § 232) e <hi rend="italic">il</hi> non designa Dio, ma riprende genericamente il <hi rend="italic">nuns</hi> precedente (Wallensköld 1925, p. 64).</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=39)">L’espressione par estovoir esprime costrizione, obbligo (“per forza”), ma potrebbe anche avere un senso più preciso ed esprimere il senso di privazione e di mancanza.</p><p corresp="#rs.1469.fro:(n=42)">Questo verso contiene l’unico accenno alla crociata, come sottolinea anche Wallensköld che pure non considera questo testo come una vera canzone di crociata.</p></div></back></text></TEI>
