<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2015-12-01</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>de la Borde 1780, II, 211; Paris 1833, 103; Leroux de Lincy 1841-1842,<hi rend="smallcaps"> I,</hi> 116; Dinaux 1837-1863, <hi rend="smallcaps">I</hi>, 140;
            Brakelmann 1870, 56; Meyer 1877, II, 367; Bédier 1906, 379; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 62;
            Gennrich 1951, 24; Wentzlaff-Eggebert 1960, 154; Cluzel 1969, 46; Schöber 1976, 162;
            Dufournet 1989, 100; Dijkstra 1995a, 192.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>de la Borde 1780, II, 211; Paris 1833, 103; Leroux de Lincy 1841-1842,<hi rend="smallcaps"> I,</hi> 116; Dinaux 1837-1863, <hi rend="smallcaps">I</hi>, 140;
            Brakelmann 1870, 56; Meyer 1877, II, 367; Bédier 1906, 379; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 62;
            Gennrich 1951, 24; Wentzlaff-Eggebert 1960, 154; Cluzel 1969, 46; Schöber 1976, 162;
            Dufournet 1989, 100; Dijkstra 1995a, 192.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(2).</hi> M 50a (<hi rend="italic">Me sire hues doysj</hi>), T 53r
              (<hi rend="italic">Me sire hues doisy</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(2).</hi> M 50a (<hi rend="italic">Me sire hues doysj</hi>), T 53r
              (<hi rend="italic">Me sire hues doisy</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababbaba (MW 902,1 = Frank
        302); 3 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+1); the first stanza has only 6 lines, with
        the rhyme-scheme 10abbaba: there may have been a gap in a previous exemplar or the stanza
        may form a sort of refrain; rhyme a: <hi rend="italic">-i</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-a</hi>;
        rhyme b: <hi rend="italic">-ans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>. Three of the four rhymes
          (<hi rend="italic">-i</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>) also
        appear in RS 1314 by Conon de Béthune. The versification is very common, but Huon d’Oisy is
        imiting Conon de Béthune’s song RS 1125 in particular, though the latter has a feminine
        a-rhyme. Identical rhyme vv. 15 and 20 (the whole expression <hi rend="italic">quant il s’en
          ala</hi>), equivocal rhyme vv. 6 and 12 (<hi rend="italic">failli</hi>, first a verb and
        then an adjective), paronymous rhyme vv. 9 and 14 (<hi rend="italic">ci-merci</hi>, also for
        the ear in <hi rend="italic">ausi</hi> v. 1), etymological figure vv. 3 and 16 (<hi rend="italic">preechemans-preechier</hi>); lyric caesura vv. 2, 10 and 15 (but the latter
        is probably a case of a median caesura 5+5); feminine caesura with elision v. 11; melody in
        both mss., with melodic structure ABAB CDC’D’ (T 601).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababbaba (MW 902,1 = Frank
        302); 3 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+1); la prima strofa è di soli 6 versi con
        schema 10abbaba: potrebbe trattarsi di una lacuna materiale della tradizione o di una specie
        di <hi rend="italic">refrain</hi>; rima a: <hi rend="italic">-i</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-a</hi>; rima b: <hi rend="italic">-ans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>; tre rime su
        quattro (<hi rend="italic">-i</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>) si trovano anche nella canzone RS 1314 di Conon de Béthune; lo schema è molto
        diffuso, ma Huon d’Oisy imita in particolare la canzone RS 1125 di Conon de Béthune, che
        però ha la rima a femminile; si ha rima identica ai vv. 15 e 20 (tutta l’espressione <hi rend="italic">quant il s’en ala</hi>), rima equivoca ai vv. 6 e 12 (<hi rend="italic">failli</hi>, prima verbo e poi aggettivo), rima paronima ai vv. 9 e 14 (<hi rend="italic">ci-merci</hi>, all’orecchio anche con <hi rend="italic">ausi</hi> del v. 1), figura
        etimologica ai vv. 3 e 16 (<hi rend="italic">preechemans-preechier</hi>); vi è cesura lirica
        ai vv. 2, 10 e 15 (ma in quest’ultimo caso si tratta più probabilmente di una cesura mediana
        5+5); cesura femminile con elisione al v. 11; melodia in entrambi i canzonieri, con schema
        melodico ABAB CDC’D’ (T 601).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The two manuscript versions are virtually
        identical, with minimal variants. In both there are two lines rhyming ab apparently missing
        in the first stanza. The various editors indicate the lacuna as corresponding to two initial
        lines or vv. 3-4. However there are no noticeable skips or breaks in the stanza’s syntactic
        structure and the melody is marked out regularly in both cases; it may be a case of a type
        of refrain rather than a gap in the common source, and given this uncertainty it is better
        not to indicate missing lines in the printed text. T’s graphy is essentially followed, its
        northern features being preserved. For the alternation of the forms <hi rend="italic">Diu/Dieu</hi> in particular see Gossen 1976, § 9, pp. 55-58 (compare also <hi rend="italic">liu</hi> for <hi rend="italic">lieu</hi> in v. 19). M is used only for v. 3
        where there is an error in T (<hi rend="italic">preemans</hi> which generates a hypometric
        line).</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>I due testimoni hanno la stessa lezione, con
        varianti minime. In entrambi i canzonieri mancano due versi con rima ab nella prima strofa.
        I vari editori segnalano la lacuna in corrispondenza dei primi due versi o dei vv. 3-4. Non
        si notano però salti o fratture nella struttura sintattica della strofa e la melodia è
        regolarmente tracciata in entrambi i casi; potrebbe anche trattarsi di una sorta di <hi rend="italic">refrain</hi> piuttosto che di una lacuna materiale e, vista l’incertezza, si
        preferisce non segnalare graficamente i versi mancanti. Si segue sostanzialmente la lezione
        e la grafia di T, conservandone anche i tratti settentrionali. In particolare per
        l’alternanza delle forme <hi rend="italic">Diu/Dieu</hi> si veda Gossen 1976, § 9, pp. 55-58
        (si veda anche <hi rend="italic">liu</hi> per <hi rend="italic">lieu</hi> al v. 19). Si
        ricorre alla lezione di M solo al v. 3 dove si riscontra un errore di T (<hi rend="italic">preemans</hi> che genera ipometria).</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2015-12-10T17:18:08Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Huon d’Oisy</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1030.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Despite all the saints and despite God Himself Conon is returning, and a curse on his
              return! Shame on him and his preaching, and shame on anyone who does not say to him
              ‘fie upon you’! When God sees him in great need He will not help him, just as he has
              not helped Him.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Sing no more, Conon, I pray you, for your songs are no more pleasing. Now you will
              live a shameful life here; you did not choose to die joyfully for God, and now you are
              counted among the cowards, so you will stay here with your failed king. May Our Lord,
              who has power over all people, have no pity, first on the king and [then] on you! </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>When he set off, Conon was very brave in giving sermons and preaching to people, and
              if a single man stayed behind, he covered him in shame and reproach. Now he has
              returned to soil his home [his nest?], and he is filthier than when he left. For sure,
              he can keep his cross and stow away, as it is in the same state as it was when he
              carried it away.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1030.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>A dispetto di tutti i santi e di Dio stesso, Conon ritorna e che sia malvenuto. Sia
              infamato lui e la sua predicazione, e sia infamato (anche) chi non gli dice
              «vergogna»! Quando Dio lo vedrà in grande bisogno non lo soccorrerà, dal momento che
              lui non L’ha soccorso.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Non cantate più, Conon, ve ne prego, perché le vostre canzoni non sono più piacevoli.
              Ora resterete qui a condurre una vita disonorevole; non avete voluto morire in letizia
              per Dio, e adesso fate parte dei codardi, così resterete con il vostro re imbelle.
              Nostro Signore, che ha potere di giudicare tutti, non abbia pietà né del re né di
              voi.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Conon, quando partì, fu molto zelante nel predicare e arringare la gente, e se solo
              uno voleva restare qui, lo copriva di disonore e biasimo. Ora è tornato a insozzare la
              sua dimora [il suo nido?], ed è più sporca di quando è partito. Può davvero riporre e
              custodire la sua croce, perché è ancora tale e quale come quando l’ha presa.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
