<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-10-21</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, 271, Tyssens 2015, 81.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, 271, Tyssens 2015, 81.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: (2) C 165rv (anonymous), U 20v (anonymous).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: (2) C 165rv (anonima), U 20v (anonima).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bba’b (MW 901,39 = Frank
        301); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> + 1 <hi rend="italic">singular</hi>; rhyme a
          -<hi rend="italic">ise</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ie</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">oie</hi>;
        rhyme b -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ent</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">eir</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ir</hi>; very common versification (29 cases), used
        especially by Gace Brulé in three songs in <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (RS 1779, RS
        1502, RS 42); decasyllables <hi rend="italic">a maiore</hi>: vv. 6, 18; median caesura: v.
        3; lyric caesura: vv. 12, 27, 33; elision in vv. 1, 3, 9, 14, 18, 31; hiatus in vv. 3, 18;
        v. 25 is hypometric by one syllable in U.</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bba’b (MW 901,39 = Frank
        301); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> + 1 <hi rend="italic">singular</hi>; rima a =
          -<hi rend="italic">ise</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ie</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">oie</hi>; rima
        b -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ent</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">eir</hi>,
          -<hi rend="italic">ir</hi>; schema metrico-rimico molto frequente (29 casi), impiegato
        specialmente da Gace Brulé in tre canzoni strutturate in <hi rend="italic">coblas
          doblas</hi> (RS 1779, RS 1502, RS 42); decasillabi <hi rend="italic">a maiore</hi>: vv. 6,
        18; cesura mediana: v. 3; cesura lirica: vv. 12, 27, 33; sinalefe ai vv. 1, 3, 9, 14, 18,
        31; dialefe ai vv. 3, 18; il v. 25 è ipometro di una sillaba in U.</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>There is an empty stave in both mss.. In C stanza
        V is missing and f. 165v has been left completely blank after six lines, at the end of the
        transcription of stanza IV. There would therefore have been enough space for the
        transcription of other stanzas. However, because of the <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi>
        structure and the essentially courtly theme of the song, this last stanza in ms. U might be
        considered spurious, a reworking of the text designed to add the two traditional motifs of
        the double service of God and Love and the heart which remains beside the beloved while the
        body leaves for overseas. I follow the graphy of the Lorraine ms. C.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>In entrambi i mss. il pentagramma è lasciato
        senza notazione. In C manca la V strofe e il f. 165v è stato lasciato completamente bianco
        dopo sei righi, alla fine della trascrizione della quarta strofe. Ci sarebbe stato dunque lo
        spazio sufficiente per la trascrizione anche di strofi successive. Tuttavia, e per la
        struttura strofica a <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> e per l’argomentazione
        essenzialmente cortese della canzone, si potrebbe considerare spuria quest’ultima strofa del
        ms. U e vederla come prodotto di un rimaneggiamento teso a inserire i due motivi
        tradizionali del doppio servizio a Dio e ad Amore e del cuore che rimane accanto all‘amata
        mentre il corpo parte per la <hi rend="italic">voie</hi> ultramarina. Si segue la grafia del
        lorenese C.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-10-21T15:22:41Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1636.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>New Love has set itself within my heart and calls upon me to make a new song. But I
              do not know from where to draw my joy, since it is fitting, if Love wishes me to sing,
              for it to give me a heart joyful from my desire, for I can sing in no other way. All
              loyal lovers know this well.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Although I have always sung my best turned towards <hi rend="italic">fin’Amor</hi>,
              which I serve and ardently love – may it give me true passion and desire! –, it has
              behaved most tyrannically towards me, so I congratulate myself inasfar as my lady has
              looked most favourably upon me! I must sing and offer my service: I shall have great
              joy if this pleases her. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>If Love has ever hurt or betrayed me, from now on I must not reproach it, for anyone
              who blames me in connection with Love is a fool: even if I were still overseas I
              should still want to think of my lady, because her beauty and her great courtliness
              would be well able to improve me both here and there.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>If I go off to the land of Syria, this will not make me take my heart away [from
              her], since I am ever a <hi rend="italic">fin aman</hi>, without any deceit, this I
              can swear: I wish to serve and revere her wherever I may be! Sweet lady, your
              sovereignty gives me passion and desire to sing.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>My will does not wholly belong to me, I need to serve Our Lord. I shall put my whole
              soul and body into the passage, but my heart will never be able to part from my lady:
              God let me have joy of her! I shall not leave her for anything in the world, because I
              wish to die a <hi rend="italic">fin aman</hi>.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1636.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Di nuovo Amore si è insediato nel mio cuore e mi spinge a fare un nuovo canto; ma io
              non so da dove trarre la mia gioia, cosicché mi conviene, se Amore vuole che io canti,
              che mi doni il cuore gioioso dal mio desiderio, perché non posso cantare in altro
              modo. Lo sanno bene tutti gli amanti leali.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Sebbene abbia sempre cantato al mio meglio rivolto a <hi rend="italic">fin’Amor</hi>,
              che servo e amo con ardore – che mi doni sempre passione e desiderio! –, molto mi ha
              tiranneggiato, così mi felicito con me stesso che la mia dama mi abbia fatto bel
              sembiante! Devo cantare e offrire il mio servizio: ne avrò gran gioia se riesco a
              piacerle.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Se mai Amore mi ha fatto male o ingannato, d’ora in avanti non mi devo lamentare,
              perché è folle chi mi biasima riguardo ad Amore. Anche se fossi al di là del mare
              penserei di continuo alla mia dama, perché la sua bellezza e la sua gran cortesia e
              qui e là mi potranno rendere migliore. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Se anche me ne andassi in terra di Siria, non allontanerei per questo il mio cuore da
              lei, perché rimango sempre un <hi rend="italic">fin amans</hi>, senza alcun inganno,
              sono pronto a giurarlo: voglio servirla e riverirla ovunque mi trovi! Dolce dama, la
              vostra signoria mi doni passione e desiderio di cantare.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>La mia volontà non appartiene tutta a me, nostro Signore mi toccherà servire. Metterò
              nel passaggio tutta la mia anima e il mio corpo, ma mai il mio cuore si potrà dividere
              dalla mia dama, che Dio mi conceda di gioire di lei! Per niente al mondo me ne
              separerei, perché vorrei morire da <hi rend="italic">fin amans</hi>.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
