<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2014-10-04</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Raynaud 1887; Paris – Mas Latrie 1906; Kohler 1913; Rossebastiano 1979, 418; Melani 1994, 128.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(2) Turin, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 39v-40r (47v-48r); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (modern copy of the Turin ms. made by Carlo Perrin and checked by Gaston Raynaud against the original), f. 47v-48r. The graphy and readings of the Turin ms. are followed, apart from the correction of hypermetric lines (vv. 1, 22, 53) and a few minor scribal slips (vv. 4, 21, 53); the translation is that of Melani 1994 with a few modifications.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(2) Torino, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 39v-40r (47v-48r); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (copia moderna del ms. di Torino eseguita da Carlo Perrin e ricontrollata da Gaston Raynaud sull’originale), f. 47v-48r. Ci si mantiene fedeli alla grafia e alla lezione del manoscritto di Torino, correggendo solo le ipermetrie (vv. 1, 22, 53) e qualche minima svista del copista (vv. 4, 21, 53); la traduzione è quella di Melani 1994 con qualche modifica.</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababccd’d’6x’ (MW 1229,2 = Frank 389); 7 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-o(u)r(s)</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-ent/ens</hi>; rhyme c = <hi rend="italic">-on(s)</hi>; rhyme d = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rhyme x = refrain-rhyme-word <hi rend="italic">aube</hi>; identical rhyme <hi rend="italic">vie</hi> in vv. 16, 35 and 53. A c rhyme is missing in stanzas vi and vii.</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababccd’d’6x’ (MW 1229,2 = Frank 389); 7 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rima a = <hi rend="italic">-o(u)r(s)</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-ent/ens</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-on(s)</hi>; rima d = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima x = parola-rima <hi rend="italic">aube</hi>; rima identica <hi rend="italic">vie</hi> ai vv. 16, 35 e 53. Manca un verso a rima c nelle strofi vi e vii.</p></metDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2014-10-15T11:35:20Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"/><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1990a.en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head>
                  <div><p><hi rend="italic">One night it happened that Philippe de Novare accompanied Sir Ansel on the watch and then overheard the words of some men who were standing in a small ruined tower, which had remained in place in the said castle, but even without this he knew what was their state of mind. At once he composed a song that goes like this:</hi></p></div>
                  <div n="1" type="stanza"><p>The other day I was on the night watch until daybreak very close to the wall, alone, without company. I heard the men in Kantara, who are sad and sorrowful, lamenting high up there in a tower. One companion whispered to the other: ‘Alas, Sir!’ he said, ‘whatever shall we do? Renard has betrayed us, God curse him, along with the false letter sent from Castrie which is arriving here before dawn!».</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Another man then responded: ‘We are suffering great grief and great pain, and great torments: watching at night, toiling during the day, with little food and poor garments; we have to pull on the petrary; we have all the discomforts, and all the sufferings. If we have to lead this life for much longer I pray death will kill us all this very night, before the dawn arrives.’</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>And then one said, ‘Friends and kinwill be weeping and in tears for us: all of us will die here, for their trebuchet makes our ovens collapse so much, our walls and ramparts, crenellations and houses. If we are attacked, how shall we defend ourselves? For our people are unequipped with armour. The walls would not be able to save us now: let us flee before dawn!</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>The mill and the oven are already ruined; it would not make much sense to wait for longer. The bailiffs of Dieudamour have betrayed us, and have broken their oath to us. They have treacherously robbed us of the king, and it was promised that we should have him. Then they made us fight at Nicosia to save them and to rob us of our life. May they never see the dawn!</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>Too late for us the Easter rescue: we are done for, as I believe and think! It was a disaster ever to set eyes on the emperor: soon we shall have to beg for mercy.’ ‘Indeed, said the other, if we were to find it, but I really think we shall not have it; therefore it is better to flee to Turkey. But those outside are keeping careful watch all night until dawn.’</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>When Gauvain saw his men in such confusion, his heart and thinking greatly changed. Sighing he said to them, ‘My lords, I cannot find a messenger in here who dares to go where we would like. [. . . . . . . . . . . . . . ] Is there anyone still in Cyprus or in Syria who will grieve if we lose our life?’ And then the dawn appeared.</p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>When I thus heard their lament and their wailing, I returned to our sergeants’ watch, and reported with joy and happiness that in Kantara there was sorrow and discord. One of my companions in arms begged me</p></div><div n="8" type="stanza"><p> [. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ] And I did so in such a way that the lament was heard. When it was finished and completed dawn broke everywhere.</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1990a.it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head>
                    <div><p><hi rend="italic">Una notte accadde che Filippo da Novara andò con messer Ancello al posto di guardia e allora intese le parole di alcuni che stavano in una torre piccola tutta diroccata, che era rimasta al detto castello, ma anche senza ciò egli sapeva qual era la loro disposizione d’animo. Subito compose una canzone che dice cosi:</hi></p></div>
                    <div n="1" type="stanza"><p>L’altr’ieri fui di guardia di notte fino a giorno<lb/>assai presso alle mura, solo, senza compagni.<lb/>Ho udito lamentarsi, lassù dentro una torre,<lb/> i candariani che sono tristi e dolenti.<lb/>A voce bassa disse uno all’altro compagno:<lb/>«Ohimè, Signore! – disse – Che cosa mai faremo?<lb/>Rainardo ci ha traditi, che Dio lo maledica,<lb/>e la lettera falsa spedita da Castrie<lb/>che qui venne anzi l’alba!».</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Rispose allora a quello un altro: «Gran dolore,<lb/>e gran pena, con grandi tormenti, noi soffriamo:<lb/>la notte vigilare, il giorno faticare,<lb/>con poco da mangiare e con povere vesti;<lb/>inoltre noi dobbiamo tirar con la petriera:<lb/>tutti i fastidi abbiamo, ed anche tutti i mali.<lb/>Se a lungo noi dobbiamo condurre tale vita<lb/>la morte prego in questa notte tutti ci uccida<lb/>prima che venga l’alba».</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>E dopo un altro disse: «In lacrime ed in pianti<lb/>saranno per noi [tutti] gli amici ed i parenti:<lb/>tutti moriamo qui, perché il loro trabocco<lb/>ci fa crollare addosso i nostri forni, ed anche<lb/>muri, e le costruzioni di pietra, e merli e case.<lb/>Se ci danno l’assalto come ci difendiamo?<lb/>Perché la nostra gente è priva delle armi;<lb/>il muro adesso non ci potrebbe salvare!<lb/>Scappiamo avanti l’alba!».</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>«È stato già abbattuto il mulino ed il forno!<lb/>D’attendere altro tempo non è cosa assennata!<lb/>Ci hanno traditi i baili che stanno a Diodamore,<lb/>ci son venuti meno i loro giuramenti.<lb/>Costoro con l’inganno ci hanno sottratto il re,<lb/>mentre il patto era invece che l’avessimo noi.<lb/>Dopo essi ci hanno fatto pugnare a Nicosia<lb/>per esser salvi loro togliendo a noi la vita.<lb/>Che mai non vedan l’alba!».</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>«Troppo tarda per noi il soccorso di Pasqua:<lb/>siamo oramai spacciati, per quel che credo e penso!<lb/>Veder l’imperatore fu la nostra disgrazia:<lb/>presto ci toccherà invocare la grazia»<lb/>«È vero, disse quello, se potremo trovarla,<lb/>ma credo veramente che non ci riusciremo!<lb/>Per questo sarà meglio fuggirsene in Turchia;<lb/>ma quelli fuori fanno la guardia attentamente<lb/>la notte fino all’alba».</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Galvano, avendo visto i suoi tanto sgomenti,<lb/>cambiaron molto in lui lo spirito ed i piani.<lb/>Sospirando egli ha detto loro: «Signori miei,<lb/>non riesco a trovare quaggiù un messaggero<lb/>che osi andare là dove desideriamo<lb/>[. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .]<lb/>Ci sarà ancora chi, a Cipro oppure in Siria,<lb/>avrà dolore se noi perdiamo la vita?».<lb/>Allora apparve l’alba.</p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>Quando ebbi così udito il pianto ed il lamento<lb/>me ne tornai al posto di guardia dei sergenti,<lb/>e là raccontai loro con gioia ed allegrezza<lb/>che dentro a La Candare c’è dolore e discordia.<lb/>Cosi mi prego uno dei miei compagni d’armi<lb/>[. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .]<lb/>Ed io feci in tal modo che il lamento fu udito.<lb/>Quando esso fu finito e tratto a compimento<lb/>dovunque schiarì l’alba.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
