<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2015-12-02</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, p. 283.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, p. 283.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>(1). U 161r-v (anon).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>(1). U 161r-v (anon). </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10 abab c'c'dd (MW 1209:16); 5
        8-line <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi> + 2 4-line <hi rend="italic">envois</hi>.
        Rhyme a = I <hi rend="italic">is,</hi> II <hi rend="italic">our</hi> (<hi rend="italic">or),</hi> III <hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">os (ors),</hi> V <hi rend="italic">ant</hi>; rhyme b = I <hi rend="italic">ant,</hi> II <hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> III <hi rend="italic">er (eir),</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">i (it),</hi> V <hi rend="italic">er (eir)</hi>; rhyme c = I <hi rend="italic">oie (aie),</hi> II, III, IV <hi rend="italic">ance,</hi> V <hi rend="italic">ente,</hi> t1 <hi rend="italic">ante,</hi> t2
          <hi rend="italic">ente</hi>; rhyme d = I <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, IV <hi rend="italic">ont</hi>; identical-equivocal rhyme: 13 <hi rend="italic">puissance</hi> : 29 <hi rend="italic">poussance</hi>; equivocal rhyme 37 <hi rend="italic">entente</hi> : 45 <hi rend="italic">antente</hi>; identical expression at the rhyme: 39 <hi rend="italic">leament ameir</hi> : 48 <hi rend="italic">leamant ameir</hi>. Medial caesura: 7, 8, 14,
        32, 37; lyric caesura: 9, 13, 40. Diaeresis: 9, 16, 29, at the caesura: 7, 35; elision at
        the caesura: 8, 14, 37. Enjambement: 19-20 (v. 20 without caesura). The verse form 1209
        (=Frank 382) only actually corresponds to st. I and st. IV, which have the final couplet
        rhyming <hi rend="italic">dd. </hi>In the middle part of the song the final couplet of
        stanzas II and III repeats the rhyme <hi rend="italic">aa</hi> (= MW 1144 = Frank 360),
        while the final stanza (V) and the two <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> end with <hi rend="italic">bb</hi> (MW 1163 = Frank 362). These metrical forms [OK?] reveal
        particularly interesting points of contact. The versification of stanzas II and III (= MW
        1144:3) is modelled on the love-song <hi rend="italic">Ne me sont pas achoison de
          chanter</hi> (RS 787 = MW 1144:2, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> of 8 vv. + 1
        4-line <hi rend="italic">tornada</hi> di 4 vv., melody ABAB CDEB'), attributed to Gace Brulé
        by mss. CKNPX, whereas ms. a assigns it to Guillaume le Vinier; mss. HLOUVza on the other
        hand transmit it as anonymous and it is also so cited by Gerbert de Montreuil in his <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Violette</hi>. The versification of st. V and the two <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> of our RS 1582 (not registered in MW under 1163) is identical to
        that of Andrieu Contredit d'Arras’s love-song<hi rend="italic">... ir / del gerredon ke
          j'atenc a avoir</hi> (RS 1387b = 1163:3), 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> of 8
        lines (v. 1 is missing) + 4-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>, transmitted without
        attribution (but with <hi rend="italic">autonominatio</hi> in v. 15) and provided with a
        musical stave without notation in the Droz fragment (BnF, nouv.acq. fr. 15797, see Droz
        1928, 540). Stanzas I and III of the song <hi rend="italic">Bele et blonde est cele pour qui
          je chant</hi> (RS 308 = 1163:2) have this same versification, 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas
          unissonans</hi> + 4-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>, transmitted with two different
        melodic versions in PU (ABAB CDEB' e ABCD EFGH). Of the three mss. preserving it, C 28
        attributes it to Thibaut de Champagne (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navaire</hi>) and P 109
        to the Châtelain d'Arras (<hi rend="italic">Li chastelains d'Arraz</hi>), while U 67 gives
        it as anonymous (<hi rend="italic">Li chastelain d'Arras</hi> only being added in the margin
        by a later hand). Wallensköld 1915, p. 127, considers it the work of an anonymous author in
        the first half of the 13th c., excluding it not only from Thibaut’s corpus but also from
        that of the Châtelain d'Arras, and later (Wallensköld 1925, 224-227) inserts it in into his
          <hi rend="italic">Appendice</hi> among Thibaut’s songs of doubtful attribution (see also
        pp. LXVI and LXX-LXXI. For the possibility that RS 308 may be attributable to the Châtelain
        d'Arras, author of the <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> RS 140, see Barbieri 2015,
        Note). To the network of analogies described here we can add the third verse-form found in
        stanzas I and IV of <hi rend="italic">Por joie avoir perfite en Paradis</hi>, with its final
        decasyllabic couplet rhyming <hi rend="italic">dd </hi>(= MW 1209:16). This pattern also is
        found in two songs from Arras datable to between the first and second quarter of the 13th c.
        and which are associated with the same tune having the structure ABAB CDEF: the first is
        attributed to Chardon de Croisilles in T 41 and C 209, <hi rend="italic">Rose ne lis ne me
          done talent</hi> (RS 736 = MW 1209:15, 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> of 8 vv. + 2
        4-line <hi rend="italic">envois</hi>) and the second is <hi rend="italic">Par maintes fois
          ai chanté liement</hi> by Robert de la Pierre (RS 696 = 1209:14, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> of 8 vv. + 1 5-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> of ms. a). To these songs can be added two <hi rend="italic">jeux-partis</hi> by the <hi rend="italic">Prince del Puy </hi>of Arras Jehan Bretel: <hi rend="italic">Adan, mout fu Aristotes sachans</hi> (RS 277 = 1209:12) and <hi rend="italic">Jehan de Vergelai, vostre escient</hi> (RS 669 = MW 1209:13). Finally, the
        versification and tune are also found in the gallicised version of Pistoleta’s <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi> with a courtly tone, RS 641 <hi rend="italic">Quar eusse cent
          mil mars d'argent</hi>, transmitted with two different melodic versions by U 82 and O 125
        (original version: <hi rend="italic">Ar agues eu mil marcs de fin argen</hi>, BdT 372.3 =
        Frank 382:25, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> di 8 vv., melody ABAB CDEF). Also
        linked to the Occitan tradition indicated under Frank 382 (= MW 1209) is another text
        datable to between the first and second quarter of the 13th c.: the <hi rend="italic">tenso</hi> of Raimbaut de Vaqueiras and Conon de Bethune, <hi rend="italic">Seigner
          Coine, jois e pretz et amors</hi> (BdT 392.29 = Frank 382:27, 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas
          unissonans</hi> of 8 vv.), from the period of the Fourth Crusade (see Paterson 2012). In
        summary, <hi rend="italic">Por joie avoir perfite en Paradis</hi> appears as a sort of
        metrico-melodic collage of three verse-forms (MW 1144:3, 1209:16, 1163) whose models are to
        be identified respectively with Gace Brulé’s song (the attribution in ms. a to the Arrageois
        Guillaume le Vinier is significant, and is probably due to his admiration of Gace declared
        in RS 1859), with the <hi rend="italic">tenso</hi> of Conon de Bethune and Raimbaut de
        Vaqueiras, and with the song of Andrieu Contredit. These three configurations match those of
        compositions by a sizeable group of poets gravitating around Arras and its poetic circle in
        the first half of the 13th c. (the Châtelain d'Arras, Chardon de Croisilles, Andrieu
        Contredit, Robert de la Pierre, Jehan Bretel). The presence of two different
        metrical-melodic forms (MW 1144 and 1209) in the same song may conceivably be the result of
        an attempt to update modes of performance, with adjustments being made to the basic
        structure at the end (though the rhyme-words have the same tonic vowel), in a position
        particularly susceptible to melodic variation. Note also that the texts following the
        (triple) metrico-melodic model of RS 1582, apart from Gace Brulé RS 787 (f. 98v), are
        preserved in U together with neumatic notation: Pistoleta’s <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi>
        BdT 372.3 (given as anonymous on f. 82r), Chardon de Croisilles’ song RS 736 (f. 58r) and
        the <hi rend="italic">Chastelain</hi> d'Arras’s song RS 308 (f. 67r).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10 abab c'c'dd (MW 1209:16); 5
          <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi> di 8 vv. + 2 invii di 4 vv. Rima a = I <hi rend="italic">is,</hi> II <hi rend="italic">our</hi> (<hi rend="italic">or),</hi> III <hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">os (ors),</hi> V <hi rend="italic">ant</hi>;
        rima b = I <hi rend="italic">ant,</hi> II <hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> III <hi rend="italic">er (eir),</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">i (it),</hi> V <hi rend="italic">er (eir)</hi>; rima
        c = I <hi rend="italic">oie (aie),</hi> II, III, IV <hi rend="italic">ance,</hi> V <hi rend="italic">ente,</hi> t1 <hi rend="italic">ante,</hi> t2 <hi rend="italic">ente</hi>;
        rima d = I <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, IV <hi rend="italic">ont</hi>; rima identico-equivoca:
        13 <hi rend="italic">puissance</hi> : 29 <hi rend="italic">poussance</hi>; rima equivoca 37
          <hi rend="italic">entente</hi> : 45 <hi rend="italic">antente</hi>; identico sintagma in
        rima: 39 <hi rend="italic">leament ameir</hi> : 48 <hi rend="italic">leamant ameir</hi>.
        Cesura mediana: 7, 8, 14, 32, 37; lirica: 9, 13, 40. Dialefe: 9, 16, 29, in cesura: 7, 35;
        elisione in cesura: 8, 14, 37. Enjambement: 19-20 (v. 20 senza cesura).In realtà lo schema
        1209 (= Frank 382) corrisponde alle sole str. I e IV, che hanno il distico finale con rima
          <hi rend="italic">dd. </hi>Nella parte centrale della canzone infatti, le str. II e III
        presentano gli ultimi due versi con ripresa della rima <hi rend="italic">aa</hi> (MW 1144 =
        Frank 360), mentre la str. V, l'ultima, e i due invii hanno la ripresa della rima <hi rend="italic">bb</hi> finale (MW 1163 = Frank 362). La distribuzione degli schemi metrici
        permette di trovare dei punti di contatto particolarmente interessanti. La struttura delle
        str. II e III (= MW 1144:3) ha il suo modello nella canzone <hi rend="italic">Ne me sont pas
          achoison de chanter</hi> (RS 787 = MW 1144:2, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>
        di 8 vv. + 1 tornada di 4 vv., mel. ABAB CDEB'), attribuita a Gace Brulé dai mss. CKNPX,
        contro a che la assegna a Guillaume le Vinier; i mss. HLOUVza invece la trasmettono anonima
        ed è citata come tale anche da Gerbert de Montreuil nel suo <hi rend="italic">Roman de la
          Violette</hi>. In secondo luogo, lo schema della str. V e dei due invii della nostra RS
        1582 (non registrato in MW sotto l'articolo 1163) è identico a quello della canzone di
        Andrieu Contredit d'Arras <hi rend="italic">... ir / del gerredon ke j'atenc a avoir</hi>
        (RS 1387b = 1163:3), 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> di 8 vv (manca il v. 1) +
        invio di 4 vv, trasmessa senza attribuzione (ma con <hi rend="italic">autonominatio</hi> al
        v. 15) e provvista di rigo musicale senza notazione nel frammento Droz (BnF, nouv.acq. fr.
        15797, cfr. Droz 1928, 540). Sempre con questa struttura, va ricordato il caso delle str. I
        e III della canzone <hi rend="italic">Bele et blonde est cele pour qui je chant</hi> (RS 308
        = 1163:2), 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> + invio di 4 vv., trasmessa con due
        versioni melodiche diverse in PU (ABAB CDEB' e ABCD EFGH). Dei tre mss. che la tramandano, C
        28 la attribuisce a Thibaut de Champagne (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navaire</hi>), P 109
        al Chastelain d'Arras (<hi rend="italic">Li chastelains d'Arraz</hi>), mentre U 67 la
        trasmette anonima (solo una mano posteriore aggiunge a margine <hi rend="italic">Li
          chastelain d'Arras</hi>). Wallensköld 1915, 127, la considera opera di un anonimo della
        prima metà del XIII escludendola non solo dal corpus di Thibaut ma anche da quello del
        Castellano d'Arras, e più tardi (Wallensköld 1925, 224-227), la inserisce in <hi rend="italic">Appendice</hi> tra le canzoni dubbie di Thibaut (cfr. anche pp. LXVI e
        LXX-LXXI. Sulla possibilità che RS 308 sia attribuibile al Castellano d'Arras, autore della
          <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> RS 140, cfr. Barbieri 2015, Note). Nella rete
        di analogie che si va illustrando, va aggiunto il terzo schema coinvolto nelle strofi I e IV
        di <hi rend="italic">Por joie avoir perfite en Paradis</hi>, con distico finale di
        decasillabi con rima <hi rend="italic">dd </hi>(= MW 1209:16). Anch'esso accoglie due
        canzoni di provenienza artesiana databili tra il primo e il secondo quarto del XIII secolo e
        accomunate dalla medesima melodia secondo lo schema ABAB CDEF: la prima è attribuita a
        Chardon de Croisilles in T 41 e C 209, <hi rend="italic">Rose ne lis ne me done talent</hi>
        (RS 736 = MW 1209:15, 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> di 8 vv. + 2 envois di 4 vv.) e
        la seconda è <hi rend="italic">Par maintes fois ai chanté liement</hi> di Robert de la
        Pierre (RS 696 = 1209:14, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> di 8 vv. + 1 envoi di
        5vv., unicum di a). A queste canzoni vanno aggiunti due <hi rend="italic">jeux</hi>-partis
        del <hi rend="italic">Prince del Puy </hi>di Arras Jehan Bretel: <hi rend="italic">Adan,
          mout fu Aristotes sachans</hi> (RS 277 = 1209:12) e <hi rend="italic">Jehan de Vergelai,
          vostre escient</hi> (RS 669 = MW 1209:13). Infine, lo schema e la melodia si ritrovano
        anche nella versione francesizzata del sirventese di tono cortese di Pistoleta, RS 641 <hi rend="italic">Quar eusse cent mil mars d'argent</hi>, trasmesso con due diverse versioni
        melodiche in U 82 e O 125 (versione originale: <hi rend="italic">Ar agues eu mil marcs de
          fin argen</hi>, BdT 372,3 = Frank 382:25, 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> di 8
        vv., melodia ABAB CDEF). Rimanendo collegati alla tradizione occitana, sotto lo stesso
        articolo Frank 382 (= MW 1209), è rintracciabile un altro testo localizzabile
        cronologicamente entro il primo quarto del secolo XIII. Si tratta della tenzone di Raimbaut
        de Vaqueiras e Conon de Bethune, <hi rend="italic">Seigner Coine, jois e pretz et amors</hi>
        (BdT 392,29 = Frank 382:27, 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> di 8 vv.), risalente
        al periodo della IV crociata (cfr. Paterson 2012). Riepilogando, <hi rend="italic">Por joie
          avoir perfite en Paradis</hi> si presenta come una sorta di centone metrico-melodico
        composto da tre schemi (MW 1144:3, 1209:16, 1163) i cui modelli sono identificabili
        rispettivamente nella canzone di Gace Brulé (significativa l'attribuzione in a all'arrageois
        Guillaume le Vinier, dovuta probabilmente alla sua ammirazione verso Gace dichiarata in RS
        1859), nella tenzone di Conon de Bethune con Raimbaut de Vaqueiras, e nella canzone di
        Andrieu Contredit. Queste tre configurazioni trovano riscontri in componimenti di un
        consistente gruppo di poeti che gravitano attorno ad Arras e alla cerchia poetica arrageoise
        nella prima metà del XIII secolo (Chastelain d'Arras, Chardon de Croisilles, Andrieu
        Contredit, Robert de la Pierre, Jehan Bretel). Che la compresenza dei tre schemi nella
        stessa canzone possa trattarsi di un caso di tentativo di aggiornamento dei modi esecutivi
        consistente in un riassestamento della struttura proprio in <hi rend="italic">cauda </hi>(e
        comunque le parole in rima presentano la medesima vocale tonica), cioè in una posizione
        particolarmente sensibile alle variazioni melodiche, o piuttosto un semplice omaggio
        formale, è difficile confermare. Segnalo inoltre che i testi che rappresentano il (triplice)
        modello metrico-melodico di RS 1582, tranne Gace Brulé RS 787 (f. 98v), sono testimoniati in
        U provvisti di notazione neumatica: il sirventese di Pistoleta BdT 372,3 (trasmesso anonimo
        al f. 82r), la canzone di Chardon de Croisilles RS 736 (f. 58r) e la canzone del <hi rend="italic">Chastelain</hi> d'Arras RS 308 (f. 67r).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The first three lines of a blank four-line stave
        are traced in red beneath the first line of the text, with space for musical notation in the
        first stanza. The song was transcribed by the third hand at work in the ms. (ff. 110-168,
        fasc. XXII) datable to the end of the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c. At the bottom of
        f. 161v are two later additions (see Tyssens 1991, 387, and Tyssens 2007, 21-22). Bédier’s
        emendations not accepted into the present edition are as follows: vv. 7 <hi rend="italic">je</hi> for <hi rend="italic">si</hi>; 11 eliminates <hi rend="italic">et</hi> and prints
          <hi rend="italic">tante dousour</hi>; 17 <hi rend="italic">puet</hi> for <hi rend="italic">pui</hi>; 18 <hi rend="italic">ne ne l'en</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ne l’en neu</hi>; 19
          <hi rend="italic">ke</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ki</hi>; 24 <hi rend="italic">l'avrai</hi>
        for <hi rend="italic">l’aurei</hi>; 25 <hi rend="italic">ensi</hi> for <hi rend="italic">asi;</hi> 27 <hi rend="italic">siel</hi> for <hi rend="italic">sielz</hi>; 29 <hi rend="italic">poissance</hi> for <hi rend="italic">poussance</hi>; 41 <hi rend="italic">nest</hi> for <hi rend="italic">nast</hi>; 43 <hi rend="italic">revien</hi> for <hi rend="italic">revaig</hi>; 45 <hi rend="italic">entente</hi> for <hi rend="italic">antente</hi>; 48 <hi rend="italic">leament</hi> for <hi rend="italic">leamant</hi>.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Sono tracciati in rosso i primi tre righi del
        tetragramma sotto il primo verso; lasciato spazio nella prima strofe per l'inserzione della
        notazione. La canzone è stata trascritta dalla terza mano operante nel codice (ff. 110-168,
        fasc. XXII) databile alla fine XIII secolo. In fondo al f. 161v si leggono due addizioni
        posteriori (cfr. Tyssens 1991, 387, e Tyssens 2007, 21-22). Si segnalano di seguito gli
        interventi al testo operati da Bédier e non accolti qui: vv. 7 <hi rend="italic">je</hi> per
          <hi rend="italic">si</hi>; 11 elimina <hi rend="italic">et</hi> e pone a testo <hi rend="italic">tante dousour</hi>; 17 <hi rend="italic">puet</hi> per <hi rend="italic">pui</hi>; 18 <hi rend="italic">ne ne l'en</hi> per <hi rend="italic">ne l’en neu</hi>; 19
          <hi rend="italic">ke</hi> per <hi rend="italic">ki</hi>; 24 <hi rend="italic">l'avrai</hi>
        per <hi rend="italic">l’aurei</hi>; 25 <hi rend="italic">ensi</hi> per <hi rend="italic">asi;</hi> 27 <hi rend="italic">siel</hi> per <hi rend="italic">sielz</hi>; 29 <hi rend="italic">poissance</hi> per <hi rend="italic">poussance</hi>; 41 <hi rend="italic">nest</hi> per <hi rend="italic">nast</hi>; 43 <hi rend="italic">revien</hi> per <hi rend="italic">revaig</hi>; 45 <hi rend="italic">entente</hi> per <hi rend="italic">antente</hi>; 48 <hi rend="italic">leament</hi> per <hi rend="italic">leamant</hi>.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2015-12-10T17:35:41Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1582.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>To have perfect joy in Paradise I must leave the land I love so well, where lives the
              lady from whom I always have mercy, with her elegant, joyful person, and her fresh and
              pleasing face. My true heart gives itself completely to her, but my body has to part
              from her: thus I shall leave for the place where God suffered death to ransom us on
              Good Friday.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Sweet love, I have felt a sharp pain now that I finally have to part from you, in
              whom I have found so much kindness, such sweetness, joy and happiness, all to my
              delight. But Fortune in her power has changed my joy to grief and torment, which I
              shall feel on your account many a night and day. Thus do I go to serve my Creator.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>I can endure hunger no more than can a child, and just as he cannot be stopped from
              crying for it, I do not think that anyone can keep me away from you, whom I love to
              kiss and embrace. I have no such power of abstinence in me! A hundred times a night I
              gaze on your beauty in my imagination: it pleased me so much to hold you in my arms!
              When I have this no more, I shall die of desire.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Fair Lord God, if for your sake I leave the land where lives the one I love so
              dearly, grant in your mercy everlasting joy in the heavens for me and my beloved! And
              give her the strength to continue to love me, so that she does not forget me because
              of the long wait, for I love her more than anything else in the world, and I feel such
              pity for it that my heart is melting!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Fair Isabella, I commend you to Christ’s body. I may no longer remain with you: to
              the unbelievers in pagan lands must I go for the love of God. To save my soul I go
              with good intention. But be well aware, my beautiful, gracious love, if ever anyone
              died for loving loyally, I do not think I shall live until I arrive at a safe sea
              port. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <p>For as the flower is born of the anther, so is born of you the great sorrow which
              torments me. But if I return, I can swear upon the saints that it will be to serve and
              honour you.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="stanza">
            <p>I sing of loyal love whereon I have my thoughts, and I seek not for my heart to
              repent of it. But I wish my lord of Gisors to know that it is an honour to love
              loyally.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1582.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Per aver gioia perfetta in paradiso, mi tocca lasciare il paese che amo tanto, dove
              vive colei da cui ho sempre avuto grazia, dal corpo elegante e florido, dal viso
              fresco e piacente. Il mio cuore leale si dona a lei completamente ma occorre che il
              corpo si separi: così me ne potrò andare là dove Dio il giorno di Venerdì soffrì fino
              alla morte per la nostra redenzione.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Dolce amica, ho sentito pungente un grande dolore perché alla fine dovrò separarmi da
              voi, in cui ho trovato tanto bene, tanta dolcezza, gioia e letizia, del tutto a mio
              piacere. Ma Fortuna nel suo potere ha rovesciato la mia gioia in dolore e tormento,
              che proverò per voi per molte notti e molti giorni. Così andrò a servire il mio
              Creatore.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Come un bambino, non posso sopportare la fame, e così come non si può nemmeno
              impedirgli di piangere, non credo che nessuno possa tenermi lontano da voi, che amo
              baciare e stringere fra le braccia. Non ho in me tanta forza di astinenza! Cento volte
              di notte immagino la vostra bellezza: ero così contento di tenervi stretta a me! Non
              vi avrò più, morirò di desiderio.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Bel Signore Dio, se lascio per voi il paese in cui vive colei che amo, compensateci
              nella vostra bontà con la gioia eterna nei cieli per me e la mia amica! E datele la
              forza di continuare ad amarmi, che non mi dimentichi nella lunga attesa, che io l'amo
              più di qualsiasi altra cosa al mondo, e ne ho un tale languore che il cuore mi si
              strugge!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Bella Isabella, al corpo di Cristo vi raccomando, non posso più restare presso di
              voi: in terra pagana, contro gli infedeli, devo andare dunque per amore di Dio. Per
              salvare la mia anima, ci vado con un buon proposito. Ma sappiatelo bene, amica bella e
              graziosa, se mai qualcuno morì per aver amato lealmente, io non credo di vivere fino
              all'arrivo in un porto sicuro di mare.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <p>Perché come il fiore nasce dall'antera, così da voi nasce il grande rimpianto che mi
              tormenta. Ma, se ritorno, sono pronto a giurarlo sui santi, sarà per servirvi e
              onorarvi.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="stanza">
            <p>Io canto dell'amore leale dove sta il mio pensiero, e mi auguro che il mio cuore non
              se ne penta. Ma voglio far sapere al mio signore di Gisors che è un onore amare
              lealmente.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
