<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-10-21</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Camus 1891, 241; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 247; Bertoni 1917, 363; Petersen Dyggve 1939,
            139; Dijkstra 1995, 214.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Camus 1891, 241; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 247; Bertoni 1917, 363; Petersen Dyggve 1939,
            139; Dijkstra 1995, 214.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: <hi rend="bold">(1). </hi>H 220b (<hi rend="italic">Moniez
              d’Arraz</hi>); for the attribution see the introduction to RS 640.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: <hi rend="bold">(1). </hi>H 220b (<hi rend="italic">Moniez
              d’Arraz</hi>); per l’attribuzione si veda l’introduzione al testo RS 640.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bba’ba’b (MW 909,2 = Frank
        304); 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (of which four are preserved in their entirety
        and one partially) with a 5-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> (babab); rhyme a: <hi rend="italic">-oie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rhyme b:
          <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-uz</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>;
        paronymous and derivative rhymes vv. 25 and 29 (<hi rend="italic">revenu-venu</hi>), 23 and
        31 (?) (<hi rend="italic">esperdu-perdu</hi>); caesura 6+4 vv. 23 and 37 (?); lyric caesura
        v. 24; feminine caesura with elision vv. 31 and 59.</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bba’ba’b (MW 909,2 = Frank
        304); 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (di cui quattro conservate integralmente e una
        parzialmente) con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 5 versi (babab); rima a: <hi rend="italic">-oie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima b:
          <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-uz</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>; vi è
        rima paronima e derivativa ai vv. 25 e 29 (<hi rend="italic">revenu-venu</hi>), 23 e 31 (?)
          (<hi rend="italic">esperdu-perdu</hi>); cesura 6+4 vv. 23 e 37 (?); cesura lirica al v.
        24; cesura femminile con elisione vv. 31 e 59.</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>For analysis of the manuscript see the
        corresponding rubric to the song RS 640. The text is transmitted in an incomplete and
        corrupt state, from the point of view of both structure and readings. As Bédier clearly
        shows, an analysis of the rhymes points to an original structure of <hi rend="italic">coblas
          doblas</hi>, but in the way the text is set out in the manuscript it appears lacunary and
        disorderly. The rhymes of the first stanza are isolated, and Bédier rightly postulates the
        existence of a second, lost, stanza with the same rhymes (there is only one known case of a
        song with five stanzas having the structure 1+2+2: the anonymous pastourelle RS 2002). The
        rhymes of the second stanza in the manuscript (the third in Bédier’s reconstruction, the
        fourth in ours) are picked up in five lines transposed by the scribe to the end of the text,
        but sense and syntax show that they must be the residual stump of an originally complete
        stanza which should be placed in an a position adjoining the fourth stanza of the
        reconstructed text; not only are the rhymes the same, but the reference in v. 41 to the
        king’s recovery presupposes that the lines on his illness come first. The scribe is likely
        to have transposed these lines to the end precisely because of their fragmentary nature. The
        final part of the text has been correctly transcribed by the copyist, with two other stanzas
        having the same rhymes and a five-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> echoing the rhyme-scheme
        and rhyme-sounds of the second part of the preceding stanzas. Unlike Bédier, I place the
        incomplete stanza in third position: the sense is no obstacle to this, and the result is a
        series of three stanzas all beginning with an apostrophe directed respectively at Jerusalem,
        France, and its king. In addition the gap in the text becomes continuous and can more easily
        be explained by imagining an already corrupt model. The text contains some Picard elements,
        especially the use of <hi rend="italic">u</hi> after <hi rend="italic">o</hi> (v. 5 <hi rend="italic">alun</hi>, v. 6 <hi rend="italic">nus</hi>, vv. 7 and 40 <hi rend="italic">sun</hi>, vv. 8 and 36 <hi rend="italic">geredun</hi>, v. 35 <hi rend="italic">unt</hi>,
        v. 47 <hi rend="italic">tun</hi>, v. 49 <hi rend="italic">lungement</hi>, v. 57 <hi rend="italic">porrunt</hi>) and the use of <hi rend="italic">g</hi> alone to express the
        velar in front of a palatal vowel (vv. 8 and 36 <hi rend="italic">geredun</hi>, v. 45 <hi rend="italic">gier</hi>); there is also a case of reduction <hi rend="italic">iee &gt;
          ie</hi> in <hi rend="italic">esillie</hi> (v. 35). There are also a few occitanisms or
        italianisms such as <hi rend="italic">serventés</hi> (v. 1, but <hi rend="italic">serventois</hi> in v. 47), <hi rend="italic">emperaor</hi> (v. 55, a venetianism?) and in
        all likelihood <hi rend="italic">poi</hi> (v. 54). There are very frequent infractions of
        the two-case system, which sometimes affect the rhyme (vv. 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 33, 36). It
        should be noted that the reconstruction of the correct form would restore all regular rhymes
        in <hi rend="italic">-uz</hi>, an element which suggests an original written in central
        France. Bédier proposes a normalised and correct text, whereas I prefer to remain faithful
        to the manuscript readings (see also the edition of Petersen Dyggve 1939), intervening only
        where the text is patently corrupt. The conjectural emendations are purely hypothetical and
        are given in italics. The conjectures in vv. 7, 31, 37, 39 and 48 are Bédier’s; those of vv.
        33-34 and 54 are mine.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Per l’analisi del manoscritto si veda la rubrica
        corrispondente della canzone RS 640. Il testo è tramandato in modo incompleto e corrotto, a
        livello di struttura e di lezione. Come mostra bene Bédier, l’analisi delle rime lascia
        intravvedere una struttura originaria a <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi>, ma nella
        disposizione del manoscritto il testo appare lacunoso e disordinato. Le rime della strofa
        incipitaria restano isolate, e Bédier postula correttamente l’esistenza di una seconda
        strofa perduta con le stesse rime (si conosce un solo caso di canzone a cinque strofe con
        struttura 1+2+2: la pastorella anonima RS 2002). Le rime della seconda strofa del
        manoscritto (la terza nella ricostruzione di Bédier, la quarta nella nostra) sono riprese da
        cinque versi dislocati dal copista in posizione finale, ma il senso e la sintassi mostrano
        che deve trattarsi del moncone residuo di una strofa inizialmente completa che trova la sua
        giusta collocazione in posizione contigua alla quarta strofa del testo ricostruito; non solo
        le rime sono le stesse, ma l’accenno del v. 41 alla guarigione del re presuppone che i versi
        sulla malattia vengano prima. È probabile che il copista abbia spostato questi versi in
        posizione finale proprio per il loro carattere frammentario. La parte finale del testo è
        trascritta correttamente dal copista, con altre due strofe che sfruttano le stesse rime e un
        congedo di cinque versi che riprende lo schema e le rime della seconda parte delle strofe
        precedenti. Diversamente da Bédier, colloco il moncone di strofa in terza posizione: il
        senso non lo impedisce, anzi si ottiene una successione di tre strofe che iniziano con
        un’apostrofe rivolta rispettivamente a Gerusalemme, alla Francia e al suo re. In questo modo
        inoltre la lacuna nel testo risulta continua e si può spiegare più facilmente immaginando un
        modello già corrotto. Il testo presenta diversi piccardismi, soprattutto il ricorso a <hi rend="italic">u</hi> al posto di <hi rend="italic">o</hi> (v. 5 <hi rend="italic">alun</hi>, v. 6 <hi rend="italic">nus</hi>, vv. 7 e 40 <hi rend="italic">sun</hi>, vv. 8
        e 36 <hi rend="italic">geredun</hi>, v. 35 <hi rend="italic">unt</hi>, v. 47 <hi rend="italic">tun</hi>, v. 49 <hi rend="italic">lungement</hi>, v. 57 <hi rend="italic">porrunt</hi>) e l’uso di <hi rend="italic">g</hi> semplice per esprimere la velare
        davanti a vocale palatale (vv. 8 e 36 <hi rend="italic">geredun</hi>, v. 45 <hi rend="italic">gier</hi>); vi è anche un caso di riduzione <hi rend="italic">iee &gt;
          ie</hi> in <hi rend="italic">esillie</hi> (v. 35). Si segnalano anche alcuni occitanismi o
        italianismi come <hi rend="italic">serventés</hi> (v. 1, ma <hi rend="italic">serventois</hi> al v. 47), <hi rend="italic">emperaor</hi> (v. 55, venetismo?) e con
        tutta probabilità <hi rend="italic">poi</hi> (v. 54). Frequentissime le infrazioni alla
        declinazione bicasuale, che a volte intaccano la rima (vv. 23, 25, 27, 29, 31, 33, 36). Va
        segnalato che la ricostruzione della forma corretta restituirebbe tutte rime regolari in <hi rend="italic">-uz</hi>, elemento che fa pensare a un originale scritto nella Francia
        centrale. Bédier propone un testo normalizzato e corretto, mentre qui si preferisce rimanere
        fedeli alla lezione del manoscritto (si veda già l’edizione Petersen Dyggve 1939),
        intervenendo solo dove il testo è palesemente corrotto. Le ricostruzioni congetturali
        restano puramente ipotetiche e sono segnalate in corsivo. Le congetture ai vv. 7, 31, 37, 39
        e 48 sono di Bédier; quelle ai vv. 33-34 e 54 sono mie.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-10-21T15:22:57Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1729.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>At God’s command I shall begin a sirventes, a discourse of happiness and joy, so that
              he may teach us the way and the path to go to Him without impediment. Let us all go,
              and that most quickly, with the One who summons and exhorts us, responding swiftly to
              his convocation: as a reward He offers us paradise for evermore for our salvation.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p> [...]</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p> [...] when the king of Paris was in a desperate state, so that they thought his soul
              had left him; and when he returned to life, he requested the cross and the one who is
              witness to such a beautiful miracle gave it to him.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Jerusalem, you are so forlorn! Misfortune has come upon you! Christendom has
              dreadfully abandoned you, and the sepulchre is lost, the temple which in the past was
              held so dear. Time was, you were much served and honoured, God was nailed and hanged
              in you; now pagans have ruined and destroyed you: they will be justly punished for
              it.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>France, you should rightly have great prestige, you should be honoured above all
              things! God seeks from you aid and assistance to liberate His land from the pagans:
              this is why He raised the king from the dead. He took the cross to purify his life,
              and so, God willing, he will go overseas. All his barons will go with him; the count
              of Artois will lead his hosts.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <p>Go, <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi>, to relay your message to the noble king who
              rules France, so that he does not forget the Holy Land: he cannot delay here any
              longer. Paris wishes to exhort him openly to a send his army to the lands of the East;
              he will easily be able to conquer them and baptise the sultan of Turkey; then he will
              be able to liberate this whole world.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="stanza">
            <p>Let him reconcile the pope and the emperor, then he will cross the sea with a great
              navy; the pagans will not be able to resist him; he will conquer all of Turkey and
              Persia, and will go to be crowned in Cairo.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1729.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Per volontà di Dio comincerò un sirventese, un discorso di letizia e di gioia,
              affinché ci indichi la via e il cammino per andare fino a lui senza impedimenti.
              Andiamo tutti e molto in fretta con Colui che ci chiama e ci esorta, rispondendo con
              prontezza al suo invito a radunarci: come ricompensa, ci offre il paradiso eterno per
              la nostra salvezza.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p> [...]</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p> [...] quando il re di Parigi fu in condizioni disperate, tanto che pensavano che
              l’anima se ne fosse andata; e quando fu tornato in vita, chiese la croce e gliela
              diede colui che è testimone di così belle virtù.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Gerusalemme, sei così sconsolata! su di te è ricaduta la sventura! La cristianità ti
              ha malamente abbandonata, ed è perduto il sepolcro, il tempio che in passato fu tenuto
              in così alta considerazione. Un tempo tu fosti giustamente servita e onorata, Dio fu
              inchiodato e appeso in te, ora i pagani ti hanno devastata e distrutta: ne riceveranno
              la giusta punizione.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Francia, è giusto che tu abbia un grande prestigio, devi essere onorata sopra ogni
              cosa! Dio ti chiede soccorso e aiuto per liberare il suo paese dai pagani: per questo
              ha fatto risorgere il re. Ha preso la croce per purificare la sua vita, e perciò
              andrà, a Dio piacendo, oltremare. Tutti i suoi baroni gli faranno compagnia; il conte
              d’Artois guiderà il suo esercito.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="stanza">
            <p>Vai, sirventese, a riferire il tuo messaggio al nobile re che governa la Francia,
              affinché non dimentichi la Terra Santa: non può indugiare qui a lungo. Parigi lo
              esorta apertamente a mandare il suo esercito nella terra d’Oriente; la potrà
              facilmente conquistare e far battezzare il sultano di Turchia; così potrà liberare
              tutto il mondo.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="stanza">
            <p>Faccia accordare il papa e l’imperatore, poi attraverserà il mare con una grande
              flotta; i pagani non potranno resistergli; conquisterà tutta la Turchia e la Persia, e
              andrà al Cairo a farsi incoronare.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
