<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2015-03-06</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Zarifopol 1904, <hi rend="a-size-large">50;</hi> Bédier-Aubry 1909, 295; Lepage 1981, 119.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Zarifopol 1904, <hi rend="a-size-large">50;</hi> Bédier-Aubry 1909, 295; Lepage 1981, 119.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: a 121v-122r (<hi rend="italic">maistre ricars</hi>).</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl><hi rend="bold">Ms</hi>.: a 121v-122r (<hi rend="italic">maistre ricars</hi>).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p><hi rend="collocazionedato">10a'ba'bba'ba' (</hi>MW 902,12 = Frank 302); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi>; rhyme a = -<hi rend="italic">euses </hi>(but also -<hi rend="italic">euse</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">euse </hi>(but also -<hi rend="italic">ouse</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">ire</hi> (but also -<hi rend="italic">ivre</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">erre</hi> (but also -<hi rend="italic">erme</hi>); rhyme b = -<hi rend="italic">en</hi> (but also -<hi rend="italic">ens</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">our</hi> (but also -<hi rend="italic">ours</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">or</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">es</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is</hi> (but also -<hi rend="italic">ir</hi>); elision at the caesura: v. 14. There are numerous irreparable irregularities at the rhyme (see Lepage 1981, 121: ‘les corriger conduirait à refaire la chanson’ and Crespo 2002, 48: ‘rime insanabilmente imperfette e assonanze’), consisting mainly of tonic assonances, some written with what could be described as a phonetic graphy: -<hi rend="italic">euse</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">ouse</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">en</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">our</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">or</hi>. The only rhyme which can be called imperfect is that in -<hi rend="italic">is</hi> in stanza I, in v. 7, which is where Bédier has intervened, restoring the rhyme in -<hi rend="italic">en</hi> by interverting the hemistiches (with some adjustment and strain). The versification is found in another 10 compositions, the particularly significant ones being two other crusade songs: Conon de Béthune RS 1125 (melody ABAB CDCD in O), most probably the model, and Chardon de Croisilles RS 499, as well as the parodic <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi> by Huon d'Oisi RS 1030 (mel. ABAB CDC'D'), closely linked to RS 1125, though built on all masculine decasyllables. It is interesting to observe how alliteration also contributes to the musicality of the text, along with the assonanced rhythm of the hemistiches, and the frequent repetitions both at the rhyme (1 <hi rend="italic">oiseuses</hi> : 16 <hi rend="italic">oiseuse</hi>; 8 <hi rend="italic">dolereuses</hi> : 11 <hi rend="italic">dolereuse</hi>; 7 : 28 <hi rend="italic">mis</hi>) and elsewhere (4, 18 <hi rend="italic">li fiex Dieu</hi>; 16, 32 <hi rend="italic">paradis</hi>; 17, 24 <hi rend="italic">ire</hi>; 27, 31, 32 <hi rend="italic">aler</hi>). These all produce a mnemonic,  psalm-like effect, probably a sign that the text could have had a paraliturgical purpose. Melody ABAB CDCD (Tischler VII, 647,2).</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p><hi rend="collocazionedato">10a'ba'bba'ba' (</hi>MW 902,12 = Frank 302); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi>; rima a = -<hi rend="italic">euses </hi>(ma anche -<hi rend="italic">euse</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">euse </hi>(ma anche -<hi rend="italic">ouse</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">ire</hi> (ma anche -<hi rend="italic">ivre</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">erre</hi> (ma anche -<hi rend="italic">erme</hi>); rima b = -<hi rend="italic">en</hi> (ma anche -<hi rend="italic">ens</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">our</hi> (ma anche -<hi rend="italic">ours</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">or</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">es</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is</hi> (ma anche -<hi rend="italic">ir</hi>); sinalefe in cesura: v. 14; tra le numerose irreparabili irregolarità rimiche (cfr. Cfr. Lepage 1981, 121: «les corriger conduirait à refaire la chanson» e Crespo 2002, 48: «rime insanabilmente imperfette e assonanze»), si trovano soprattutto assonanze toniche, alcune delle quali scritte con una grafia che potremmo definire fonetica: -<hi rend="italic">euse</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">ouse</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">en</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">our</hi>:-<hi rend="italic">or</hi>; l'unica rima che può dirsi imperfetta è quella in -<hi rend="italic">is</hi> nella prima strofa, al v. 7, che è il luogo in cui Bédier è intervenuto, ristabilendo la rima in -<hi rend="italic">en</hi> con l'inversione degli emistichi (con qualche aggiustamento e forzatura). Lo schema metrico si ritrova in altri 10 componimenti, tra i quali particolarmente significativa è la presenza di altre due canzoni di crociata: Conon de Béthune RS 1125 (melodia ABAB CDCD in O), molto probabilmente il modello, e Chardon de Croisilles RS 499, oltre al sirventese parodico di Huon d'Oisi RS 1030 (mel. ABAB CDC'D'), strettamente legato a RS 1125, sebbene strutturato su <hi rend="italic">décasyllabes</hi> tutti maschili. È interessante notare come anche le allitterazioni contribuiscano a fornire al testo una musicalità che, unita al ritmo assonanzato degli emistichi e alle frequenti ripetizioni sia in rima (1 <hi rend="italic">oiseuses</hi> : 16 <hi rend="italic">oiseuse</hi>; 8 <hi rend="italic">dolereuses</hi> : 11 <hi rend="italic">dolereuse</hi>; 7 : 28 <hi rend="italic">mis</hi>) che all'interno del testo (4, 18 <hi rend="italic">li fiex Dieu</hi>; 16, 32 <hi rend="italic">paradis</hi>; 17, 24 <hi rend="italic">ire</hi>; 27, 31, 32 <hi rend="italic">aler</hi>), produce un sicuro effetto mnemonico, quasi salmodico, probabile indizio che il testo potesse avere un impiego paraliturgico. Melodia ABAB CDCD (Tischler VII, 647,2).</p></metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The text is transcribed into fascicle XX (cc. 120-127) of ms. BAV <hi rend="reference-text">Reg. lat. 1490 (= a) </hi>devoted to songs to the Virgin (<hi rend="italic">Che sont chançons de Nostre Dame</hi>), and is the only crusade song among the <hi rend="italic">chansons pieuses</hi>, following <hi rend="italic">Mere au roi omnipotent</hi> (RS 713), which is also attributed to <hi rend="italic">Maistres Ricars de Fournival</hi>. The two texts were therefore transcribed separately from the corpus of  RcFor’s other lyrics which in ms. a are concentrated in folios 39r-43v. This is one of the reasons for which their attribution to this trouvère, especially that of this crusade song, is still <hi rend="italic">sub iudice</hi>.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Il testo è trascritto nel fascicolo XX (cc. 120-127) del ms. BAV <hi rend="reference-text">Reg. lat. 1490 (= a) </hi>dedicato alle canzoni alla Vergine (<hi rend="italic">Che sont chançons de Nostre Dame</hi>), unica canzone di crociata tra le <hi rend="italic">chansons pieuses</hi>, dopo <hi rend="italic">Mere au roi omnipotent</hi> (RS 713), attribuita anch'essa a <hi rend="italic">Maistres Ricars de Fournival</hi>. I due testi sono stati dunque trascritti fuori dal corpus delle liriche di RcFor che in a si concentra ai ff. 39r-43v. Questa è una delle ragioni per cui la loro attribuzione al troviero, soprattutto questa canzone di crociata, è tuttora <hi rend="italic">sub iudice</hi>.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2015-03-08T12:02:55Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1020a.en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Listen, Lords, idling in indolence, you who procrastinate, lacking all good qualities, remember the painful death which the Son of God first suffered! He was fettered to the stake and lashed with knotted whips; we well know that He was set upon the cross to free us from grievous pains.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Ah, faint-hearts, shameful wicked creatures, do you then feel great fear of death? Call to mind the painful death which will be everlasting and will be ever worse! Le us be reconciled with our Creator who will come and seek us, most joyfully welcoming us and saying: ‘Come here, all you good and best people, there is plenty of free space in Paradise!’.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>On the dread dark day of wrath, when the Son of God will come, terrible and wrathful, and will openly reveal the wounds in his side, in his hands, in his feet, pierced and nailed for us, then there will be no saint who dares to utter a single word. The bravest will wish he had taken the cross, so much will they fear his fury and his ire!</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Overseas, in that holy land where God was born and where he died and lived again, we should go to claim our inheritance, for He was most wrongly expelled from there on our account. Anyone who does not go will not be His friend, for there is no peace, nor truce, nor respite there. God let us so go there and return that we may enter Paradise without war!</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1020a.it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Udite, signori, ignavi per indolenza, voi che indugiate bisognosi di tutto, ricordatevi della morte angosciosa che il figlio di Dio soffrì, lui per primo! Egli fu legato al palo coi lacci e fu percosso con cinghie nodose, noi sappiamo bene che fu messo in croce per liberarci dalle pene dolorose.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Ah, cuori imbelli, carni malvagie e degne di disonore, avete dunque così paura di morire? Ricordatevi della morte dolorosa che sarà eterna e sempre più penosa! Riconciliamoci col nostro Creatore che ci appellerà trionfante dicendo: «Di qua tutti i buoni e i migliori, in Paradiso c'è un grande spazio libero!».</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Il giorno spaventoso, scuro e pieno d'ira, quando il figlio di Dio verrà terribile e adirato, e mostrerà scoperte le sue ferite nel costato, nelle sue mani, nei suoi piedi, trapassati e inchiodati per noi, allora non ci sarà santo che oserà pronunciare parola, e il più coraggioso vorrebbe aver preso la croce, tanto temeranno il suo malanimo e la sua ira!</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Oltremare, in quella santa terra dove Dio nacque e dove morì e risorse, dobbiamo andare a pretendere la nostra eredità, perché con gran torto fu scacciato di là per causa nostra. Chi non ci verrà, non sarà tra i suoi amici, perché non esiste pace, né tregua né sospensione. Dio ci lasci andare e ritornare, perché possiamo andare in Paradiso senza guerra!</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
