<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-02-24</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Jubinal 1838, 37; Michel 1839, 52; Buchon 1840, I, 425; Leroux de Lincy
              1841-1842,<hi rend="smallcaps"> I,</hi> 122; Wackernagel 1846, 34; Paris 1890a, 294;
            Bédier-Aubry 1909, 145; Serper 1983, 82; Guida 1992, 98; Dijkstra 1995a, 202.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Jubinal 1838, 37; Michel 1839, 52; Buchon 1840, I, 425; Leroux de Lincy
              1841-1842,<hi rend="smallcaps"> I,</hi> 122; Wackernagel 1846, 34; Paris 1890a, 294;
            Bédier-Aubry 1909, 145; Serper 1983, 82; Guida 1992, 98; Dijkstra 1995a, 202.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss. (3).</hi> C 96r (anonymous), M 81b (<hi rend="italic">Hues de
              saint quentin</hi>), T 42v (<hi rend="italic">Hues de saint quentin</hi>); M’s text is
            mutilated because of the removal of a vignette; the attribution appears in the initial
            table of the songbook.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss. (3).</hi> C 96r (anonima), M 81b (<hi rend="italic">Hues de
              saint quentin</hi>), T 42v (<hi rend="italic">Hues de saint quentin</hi>); il testo di
            M è mutilato a causa dell’ablazione di una vignetta; l’attribuzione si legge nella
            tavola iniziale del canzoniere.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">
        <p>10ababbbaabba (MW 961,1); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi>; rhyme a:
            <hi rend="italic">-is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; rhyme b: <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>; the metrical shape is a <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> in Old French lyric and there are no examples in troubadour lyric;
          paronymous rhymes in vv. 3-22 (<hi rend="italic">amis-pramis</hi>), 14-18-19 (<hi rend="italic">souspris-pris-repris</hi>, also derivative), 25-41-44 (<hi rend="italic">pardon-guerredon-don</hi>); <hi rend="italic">ment</hi> in v. 20 constitutes a
          paronymous rhyme with numerous forms of the rich rhyme <hi rend="italic">-ment</hi> in the
          first two stanzas (vv. 2, 5, 6, 9, 16, 17); lyric caesura in vv. 17, 28 and 42; feminine
          caesura with elision in v. 10; melody in MT, with the melodic scheme ABAB CDEFGHI (T
          911).</p>
      </metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">
        <p>10ababbbaabba (MW 961,1); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi>; rima a: <hi rend="italic">-is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; rima b: <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>; lo schema metrico è un <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> nella
          lirica francese e non se ne trovano esempi nella lirica trobadorica; si ha rima paronima
          ai vv. 3-22 (<hi rend="italic">amis-pramis</hi>), 14-18-19 (<hi rend="italic">souspris-pris-repris</hi>, anche derivativa), 25-41-44 (<hi rend="italic">pardon-guerredon-don</hi>); <hi rend="italic">ment</hi> al v. 20 costituisce rima
          paronima con numerose forme in rima ricca <hi rend="italic">-ment</hi> delle prime due
          strofe (vv. 2, 5, 6, 9, 16, 17); cesura lirica ai vv. 17, 28 e 42; cesura femminile con
          elisione al v. 10; melodia in MT, con schema melodico ABAB CDEFGHI (T 911).</p>
      </metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en">
        <p>The absence of v. 26 unites the three witnesses and represents an archetype error; the
          absence of v. 19 unites mss. MT in error against C. MT’s text is, as is often the case,
          generally better and is therefore used as base. Because of material gaps in M’s text the
          more northern graphy of ms. T is followed, which probably respects the author’s more
          closely. The main northern features are: <hi rend="italic">u</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ou</hi> (vv. 2, 6, 29), <hi rend="italic">cascun(s)</hi> (vv. 5, 13, 22, 41), <hi rend="italic">liu</hi> v. 6, <hi rend="italic">faura</hi> v. 11, <hi rend="italic">Diu(s)</hi> (vv. 20 and 22), <hi rend="italic">ara</hi> v. 43; on the morphological
          level see <hi rend="italic">le</hi> for <hi rend="italic">la</hi> in vv. 9-10. T’s reading
          is rejected each time it is opposed to the joint reading of C and M (v. 2 <hi rend="italic">doucement</hi>, v. 4 <hi rend="italic">son cors</hi>, v. 31 <hi rend="italic">qui</hi>, v. 35 <hi rend="italic">k’il</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vai
            a</hi>). In the absence of M, C’s reading has been preferred in v. 14, where T presents
          an improbable syntactic alternative (<hi rend="italic">mais que</hi>). Finally I complete
          v. 19 according to C’s reading, the only manuscript to transmit it, and in v. 21 (<hi rend="italic">recolu</hi>) correct the graphy of T, which often confuses <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> in conformity with the northern
          “scripta”.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it">
        <p>L’assenza del v. 26 unisce i tre testimoni e costituisce un errore d’archetipo; l’assenza
          del v. 19 unisce in errore i mss. MT contro C. La lezione di MT è come spesso accade
          generalmente migliore e quindi viene utilizzata come base. In particolare, anche a causa
          delle lacune materiali del testo di M, si segue la grafia più settentrionale del ms. T,
          che probabilmente rispecchia più da vicino quella dell’autore. I principali tratti
          settentrionali sono: <hi rend="italic">u</hi> per <hi rend="italic">ou</hi> (vv. 2, 6,
          29), <hi rend="italic">cascun(s)</hi> (vv. 5, 13, 22, 41), <hi rend="italic">liu</hi> v.
          6, <hi rend="italic">faura</hi> v. 11, <hi rend="italic">Diu(s)</hi> (vv. 20 e 22), <hi rend="italic">ara</hi> v. 43; a livello morfologico si veda <hi rend="italic">le</hi>
          per <hi rend="italic">la</hi> ai vv. 9-10. Si abbandona la lezione di T ogni volta che a
          essa si oppone la lezione congiunta di C e M (v. 2 <hi rend="italic">doucement</hi>, v. 4
            <hi rend="italic">son cors</hi>, v. 31 <hi rend="italic">qui</hi>, v. 35 <hi rend="italic">k’il</hi> e <hi rend="italic">vai a</hi>). In assenza di M, si preferisce
          la lezione di C al v. 14, dove T presenta un’alternativa sintatticamente improbabile (<hi rend="italic">mais que</hi>). Infine si integra il v. 19 secondo la lezione di C, unico
          testimone a riportarlo, e si corregge al v. 21 la grafia di T (<hi rend="italic">recolu</hi>), che conformemente alla “scripta” settentrionale confonde spesso <hi rend="italic">c</hi> e <hi rend="italic">t</hi>.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-03-13T09:37:45Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Huon de Saint-Quentin</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1576.en" xml:lang="en">
        <head> Translation </head>
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
          <p>Jerusalem laments, and the land where the Lord God suffered death most gently, because
            this side of the sea it has few friends who offer it the slightest help. If each one
            remembered the judgment (the Last Judgment) and the holy place where He suffered torture
            when He forgave Longinus for His death, he would not readily renounce his crusading vow;
            for whoever takes the cross with full consent for God’s sake denies Him on the day he
            gives it back, and like Judas will lose paradise.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
          <p>Our shepherds take little care of their sheep when each of them sells them to the wolf
            for money, but sin has so taken hold of them that they have forgotten God for the sake
            of silver. What will become of the rich ornaments they acquire most shamefully with the
            fraudulent payment they have taken from the crusaders? Be well aware that they will be
            blamed for this, if loyalty and God and faith do not lie; they have stolen from Acre and
            Bethlehem what each had promised to God.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
          <p>Who will dare to preach and speak of God any more in square or cloister, and announce
            benefits and indulgences, [<hi rend="italic">when no-one is disposed to perform</hi>]
            anything which can assist Our Lord to conquer and win back the land where He paid our
            ransom with His blood? Lord prelates, it is neither good nor just that you so delay his
            help: you, this can certainly be said, have made Roland of God and Ganelon of
            yourselves.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
          <p>There is no wisdom nor intelligence in anyone who knows this without helping to avenge
            those who are over there in prison for God’s sake, and to remove their souls from
            danger. Since one has to die here, one should not fear pain or torment, shame or harm:
            everything one does in His name is for God, who will give to each such a reward that the
            heart of man could not appreciate its worth; for he will receive paradise as a reward,
            and no-one has ever had such a rich gift for so little.</p>
        </div>
      </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1576.it" xml:lang="it">
        <head> Translation </head>
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
          <p>Gerusalemme si lamenta, e la terra dove Dio sopportò la morte con mansuetudine, perché
            da questa parte del mare ha pochi amici che siano disposti a prestarle soccorso. Se
            ciascuno si ricordasse del giudizio e del santo luogo dove egli patì il supplizio quando
            perdonò Longino per la sua morte, non rinuncerebbero a cuor leggero al voto di crociata;
            perché chi prende con pieno consenso la croce per Dio, lo rinnega il giorno che la
            restituisce, e come Giuda perderà il paradiso.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
          <p>I nostri pastori curano male le loro pecore dato che ognuno le vende al lupo per
            denaro, ma il peccato ha talmente preso possesso di loro che hanno dimenticato Dio per i
            soldi. Che ne sarà dei ricchi ornamenti che acquistano vergognosamente con i vili
            contributi che hanno riscosso dai crociati? Sappiate che saranno per loro motivo di
            biasimo, se la lealtà, Dio e la fede non mentono; hanno sottratto a Acri e a Betlemme
            ciò che ognuno aveva promesso a Dio.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
          <p>Chi oserà più predicare e parlare di Dio in piazza o in convento, e annunciare
            gratificazioni e indulgenze, [<hi rend="italic">quando nessuno è disposto a
              compiere</hi>] atti che possano aiutare Nostro Signore a conquistare e recuperare la
            terra dove pagò il prezzo del nostro riscatto con il suo sangue? Signori prelati, non è
            né buono né giusto che facciate tardare così tanto il suo soccorso: voi avete fatto, lo
            si può ben dire, di Dio Orlando e di voi stessi Gano.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
          <p>Non ha saggezza né intelligenza chi sa tutto questo e non contribuisce a riscattare
            coloro che sono laggiù in prigione per Dio, per allontanare le loro anime dal pericolo.
            Poiché si deve comunque morire, non si devono temere pena e tormento, ingiuria o danno:
            tutto ciò che si fa in suo nome è per Dio, che darà a ciascuno una tale ricompensa che
            nessuno potrebbe stimarne il valore; perché riceverà in premio il paradiso, e nessuno ha
            mai ricevuto un così grande dono per così poco.</p>
        </div>
      </div></body></text></TEI>
