<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-09-15</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Meyer 1877, 369; Bartsch 1920<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 243; Bédier-Aubry 1909,
            19; Rosenberg-Tischler 1981, 105; Guida 1992, 73; Dijkstra 1995a, 94.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Meyer 1877, 369; Bartsch 1920<hi rend="superscript">12</hi>, 243; Bédier-Aubry 1909,
            19; Rosenberg-Tischler 1981, 105; Guida 1992, 73; Dijkstra 1995a, 94.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss</hi>. <hi rend="bold">(2)</hi>. C 245v-246r (<hi rend="italic">Denostre/daime</hi>), U 127r-v (anonymous).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss</hi>. <hi rend="bold">(2)</hi>. C 245v-246r (<hi rend="italic">Denostre/daime</hi>), U 127r-v (anonima).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>8ababbaabab (MW 865,3); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi>; rhymes a = -<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">iez</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is </hi>(-<hi rend="italic">ins</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">ier</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain </hi>(-<hi rend="italic">ains</hi>); b =
          -<hi rend="italic">ais</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ait</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi>,
          -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi> (-<hi rend="italic">ent</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">oir</hi>.
        The song shares its metrical shape with two other songs, the anonymous <hi rend="italic">Grant piece a que ne chantai mais</hi> (RS 194 = MW 865:1) and the song in <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> di Raoul de Ferrières <hi rend="italic">Quant je voi les
          vergiers florir</hi> (RS 1412 = MW 865:2). Spanke 1936, 153, relates this versification to
        the monodic <hi rend="italic">conductus Quid ultra tibi facere</hi> attributed to Philippus
          <hi rend="italic">parisiensis</hi>, chancellor of the chapter of Notre-Dame from 1217. The
        paraliturgical text, composed of six 10-syllable lines on two rhymes which change position
        in the central part of the stanzas (whose complete melody is transmitted only in ms.
        Florence, Biblioteca Laurenziana, Pluteus 29.1), is a lamentation of Christ who contrasts
        His sufferings with the thirst for power and the slothfulness of the Church and the clergy
          (<hi rend="italic">Planctus Christi de malis praesulibus</hi>). Equivocal rhymes: 2 <hi rend="italic">pais</hi> : 5 <hi rend="italic">paix</hi>, 12 : 14 <hi rend="italic">lait</hi>, 26 : 27 <hi rend="italic">pis</hi>, 42 : 45 <hi rend="italic">savoir</hi>;
        identical rhymes: 1 : 7 <hi rend="italic">amor</hi>, 3 : 9 <hi rend="italic">jor</hi>; link
        in <hi rend="italic">cobla capfinida</hi> between stanzas IV and V; both mss. are
        hypermetric by one syllable in v. 2 (<hi rend="italic">ne dormeis uos pais</hi>); the text
        is transmitted without music (blank staves in C, the interlinear space is left blank in the
        first stanza in U).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>8ababbaabab (MW 865,3); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas singulars</hi>; rima a: -<hi rend="italic">or</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">iez</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">is </hi>(-<hi rend="italic">ins</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">ier</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ain </hi>(-<hi rend="italic">ains</hi>); rima
        b: -<hi rend="italic">ais</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ait</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi>,
          -<hi rend="italic">ant</hi> (-<hi rend="italic">ent</hi>), -<hi rend="italic">oir</hi>; lo
        schema sillabico e rimico della canzone è condiviso con altri due testi: l’anonima canzone
        in tre <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans Grant piece a que ne chantai mais</hi> (RS 194 =
        MW 865:1) e la canzone a <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> di Raoul de Ferrières <hi rend="italic">Quant je voi les vergiers florir</hi> (RS 1412 = MW 865:2). Spanke 1936,
        153, mette in relazione questo schema con quello del <hi rend="italic">conductus
        </hi>monodico <hi rend="italic">Quid ultra tibi facere</hi> attribuito a Philippus <hi rend="italic">parisiensis</hi>, cancelliere del capitolo di Notre-Dame dal 1217. Il testo
        paraliturgico, composto da 6 strofe di 10 ottonari su due rime che si invertono in sede
        centrale di strofe (la cui melodia completa è trasmessa unicamente dal ms. Firenze,
        Biblioteca Laurenziana, Pluteus 29.1), è una lamentazione di Cristo che oppone le sue
        sofferenze alla sete di potere e all’accidia della Chiesa e del clero (<hi rend="italic">Planctus Christi de malis praesulibus</hi>). Rime equivoche: 2 <hi rend="italic">pais</hi> : 5 <hi rend="italic">paix</hi>, 12 : 14 <hi rend="italic">lait</hi>, 26 : 27
          <hi rend="italic">pis</hi>, 42 : 45 <hi rend="italic">savoir</hi>; rime identiche: 1 : 7
          <hi rend="italic">amor</hi>, 3 : 9 <hi rend="italic">jor</hi>; legame in <hi rend="italic">cobla capfinida</hi> tra la IV e la V <hi rend="italic">cobla</hi>; ambedue i mss. sono
        ipermetri di una sillaba al v. 2 (<hi rend="italic">ne dormeis uos pais</hi>); il testo è
        stato trasmesso senza melodia (rigatura musicale vuota in C, spazio bianco nell’interlineo
        della prima strofe in U).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>Of the two Lorraine witnesses the version of ms.
        U has been chosen, both for its graphy and for its text, complete in contrast to C which
        lacks v. 25.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Tra i due testimoni lorenesi è stata scelta la
        versione del ms. U sia per la grafia che per il testo, completo rispetto a C, che è mancante
        del v. 25.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-09-15T14:54:22Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1967.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>You who love with true love, wake up, sleep no more! The lark brings us the dawn and
              tells us with its warbling that the day of peace has come which God, in his great
              sweetness, promises to those who for love of Him will take the cross, and for their
              sins will suffer pain both night and day. Then He will see who truly loves Him! </p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Anyone who abandons his lord in his hour of need deserves to be sent into exile. And
              he will be, you can be sure of that! He will suffer pain and disgrace at the Last
              Judgment, when God will show His bleeding and wounded sides, hands and feet: even one
              who has behaved most righteously [in this life] will be so appalled that he will
              tremble, whether he wishes or no.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>The one who was set upon the cross for us did not love us dissemblingly but did so as
              a perfect lover, and for our sakes, with dignity, [He took] the holy cross most
              sweetly in his arms, holding it tightly in anguish across his chest, like a gentle,
              innocent and pious lamb. Then he was nailed fast with three nails through feet and
              hands. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>I have heard say in a proverb: ‘A good price draws money from the purse’ and ‘It is a
              complete fool who sees what’s good and takes what’s bad’. Do you know what God
              guarantees to those wishing to take the cross? God help me, splendid wages: Paradise
              assured! Anyone who can pursue profit [today] is mad to wait until tomorrow.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>We have no [certainty of] tomorrow, we know this well. Someone may think he is in
              perfect health yet within a quarter of a day may no longer put any value on the whole
              sum of his wealth or knowledge, for once death holds him in his bridle and he can no
              longer move his hands and feet in one direction or another, he gives up his soft bed
              and takes a straw mattress. But realisation comes too late!</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1967.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>O voi che amate di vero amore, svegliatevi, non dormite oltre! L’allodoletta ci
              annuncia il giorno e ci dice coi suoi gorgheggi che è giunto il giorno della
              pacificazione che Dio, nella sua grande dolcezza, promette a coloro che, per amor suo,
              prenderanno la croce e per il peso dei loro peccati soffriranno pena notte e giorno.
              Allora Egli vedrà quelli che lo amano davvero!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Chi abbandona il suo Signore nel bisogno merita di essere messo al bando. E lo sarà,
              sappiatelo! Costui patirà pene e oltraggi nel giorno del nostro giudizio finale quando
              Dio mostrerà il costato, le mani e i piedi sanguinanti e feriti: anche chi si sarà
              comportato al meglio sarà così spaventato che, gli piaccia o no, tremerà.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Colui che per noi fu messo in croce non ci ha amato per finta, ma da amico perfetto e
              per noi, con dignità, (egli prese) molto docilmente la Santa Croce tra le sue braccia,
              chino sul suo petto, come agnello mansueto, innocente e pio, e la trascinò
              angosciosamente. Poi fu inchiodato con tre chiodi che trapassarono le mani e i piedi,
              conficcati nel profondo.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Ho sentito dire in un proverbio: «Il buon prezzo fa tirar fuori il denaro dalla
              borsa» e «È un vero sciocco chi vede il bene ma sceglie il male». Sapete quello che
              Dio garantisce a coloro che vorranno prendere la croce? Un bel compenso davvero, che
              Dio mi assista! il Paradiso assicurato! Chi può ricavare un buon guadagno (oggi) è
              folle se aspetta domani.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Noi non abbiamo (certezza del) domani, lo sappiamo bene. Uno può sentirsi pieno di
              salute ma entro il quarto giorno potrebbe non apprezzare più né tutto il suo avere né
              tutto il suo sapere. Allora, quando la morte lo tiene imbrigliato e non può tirare a
              sé né allentare né le mani né i piedi, lascia le morbide coltri e prende il
              pagliericcio. Ma è troppo tardi per il ravvedimento!</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
