<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Tomaz Erjavec</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2014-03-17</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl type="manuscripts">
                    <head>Mss. (5).</head>
                <bibl>Baltimore, Walters Art Museum, W.142 (B), 310d-311a;</bibl>
                <bibl>Paris, BnF, fr. 9083 (P1), 316cd; </bibl>
                <bibl>Paris, BnF, fr. 22495 (P2), 283v;</bibl>
                <bibl>Paris, BnF, fr. 24209 (P3), 320cd; </bibl>
                <bibl>Torino, Biblioteca nazionale universitaria, L.I.5 (T),
                    491cd.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="previous_editions">

                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Histoire littéraire de la France</hi>, XXIII, 675;
                    </bibl>  

                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Continuation Rothelin</hi>, 548;</bibl>
                <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, 217; </bibl>
                    <bibl>Dufournet 1989, 188; </bibl>
                        <bibl>Guida 1992, 115; </bibl>
                            <bibl>Dijkstra 1995a, 209.</bibl>
                                <bibl>Versification and music. </bibl>
    
                </listBibl>
            <listBibl type="essential_bibliography">
                    <bibl><hi rend="underline">Bédier 1928</hi>: Joseph Bédier, «Les chansons du
                        comte de Bretagne», in <hi rend="italic">Mélanges de linguistique et de
                            littérature offerts à Alfred Jeanroy par ses élèves et ses amis</hi>,
                        Paris, Champion, 1928, pp. 477-495.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Cazel 1989</hi>: Fred A. Cazel, Jr.,
                    «Financing the Crusades», in <hi rend="italic">A History of the Crusades</hi>,
                    general editor Kenneth M. Setton, vol. VI, Madison, The University of Wisconsin
                    Press, 1989, pp. 116-149</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline"><pb type="soft"/>Edbury 2007</hi>: Peter
                    Edbury, «The French Translation of William of Tyre’s <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi>: the Manuscript Tradition», <hi rend="italic">Crusades</hi>,
                    6, 2007, pp. 69-105.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Grossel 2000</hi>: Marie-Geneviève
                    Grossel, «Les Champenois et l’appel de l’outremer au XIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle», in <hi rend="italic">Mémoire de Champagne</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Actes du troisième mois médiéval, Centre d’études médiévales
                        de la région Champagne-Ardenne</hi>, II, Langres, Guéniot, 2000, pp.
                    105-131.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Guida 2006</hi>: Saverio Guida,
                    «L’autore e il latore di <hi rend="italic">Vai, Hugonet, ses bistensa</hi> (BdT
                    461,247)», <hi rend="italic">Cultura neolatina</hi>, 66, 2006, pp. 45-82.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Jackson 1987</hi>: Peter Jackson, «The
                    crusades of 1239-41 and their aftermath», <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the
                        School of Oriental and african Studies</hi>, 50, 1987, pp. 32-60.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Köhler 2000</hi>: Erich Köhler,
                    L’avventura cavalleresca, ideale e realtà nei romanzi della Tavola Rotonda,
                    Bologna, Il Mulino, 2000</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Lower 2005</hi>: Michael Lower, <hi rend="italic">The Baron’s Crusade: a call to arms and its consequences</hi>,
                    Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Press, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Marshall 1980</hi>: John H. Marshall,
                    «Pour l’étude des <hi rend="italic">contrafacta</hi> dans la poésie des
                    troubadours», <hi rend="italic">Romania</hi>, 101, 1980, pp. 289-335.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Morgan 1982</hi>: Margaret R. Morgan,
                    «The Rothelin Continuation of William of Tyre», in <hi rend="italic">Outremer.
                        Studies in the history of the Crusading Kingdom of Jerusalem presented to
                        Joshua Prawer</hi>, edited by Benjamin Z. Kedar, Hans E. Mayer, Raymond C.
                    Smail, Jerusalem, Yad Izhak Ben-Zvi Institute, 1982, pp. 244-257.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Painter 1989</hi>: Sidney Painter, «The
                    Crusade of Theobald of Champagne and Richard of Cornwall, 1239-1241», in <hi rend="italic">A History of the Crusades</hi> (Editor in Chief, Kenneth Meyer
                    Setton), II, <hi rend="italic">The Later Crusades, 1189-1311</hi>, Edited by R.
                    L. Wolff and Harry W. Hazard, Madison, University of Wisconsin Press, 1989, pp.
                    463-487.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Petersen Dyggve 1938</hi>: Holger
                    Petersen Dyggve, <hi rend="italic">Moniot d’Arras et Moniot de Paris, trouvères
                        du XIIIe siècle, édition des chansons et étude historique</hi>, Helsinki,
                    Imprimérie de la Société de littérature finnoise, 1938.</bibl>
                <bibl rend="Bibliography"><hi rend="underline">Röhricht 1886</hi>: Reinhold Röhrich,
                    «Die Kreuzzüge des Grafen Theobald von Navarra und Richard von Cornwallis, nach
                    dem heiligen Lande», <hi rend="italic">Forschungen zur deutschen
                    Geschichte</hi>, 26, 1886, pp. 67-102.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
                <editorialDecl xml:lang="en">
                    <p>See the corresponding paragraph in the introduction to RS 164.</p></editorialDecl>
            <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p><hi rend="bold">Si veda il paragrafo corrispondente nell’introduzione della canzone RS 164.</hi></p></editorialDecl>
                <metDecl pattern="7a&#x2019;bba&#x2019;a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;" xml:lang="en">
                    <p>7a’bba’a’ba’a’ba’ (MW 1302,1 = Frank 472); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas
                        unissonans</hi>; rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-ou(r)s</hi>. The same metrical shape appears in seven other
                    texts, all in 7-syllable lines and with the same alternation of m. and f.
                    rhymes; among these is RS 1141 (the Count of Brittany), with 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> and identical rhymes, while the first 3 stanzas of
                    RS 1135 (Moniot d’Arras) also has the same rhymes <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>/
                        <hi rend="italic">-ous</hi>. The same scheme but with different rhymes is
                    used in the anonymous crusade song RS 1738a, datable to 1244-1245. Among
                    troubadour texts the metrical shape is used by Raimon de Miraval in the <hi rend="italic">canso</hi> BdT 406.7 (m. rhymes only) and the anonymous <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi> BdT 461.247 which has the same alternance of m.
                    and f. rhymes (e rhyme <hi rend="italic">-ia</hi> / <hi rend="italic">-os</hi>
                    in st. III and IV). Two lines are missing at the end of st. I, and the sentence
                    may be incomplete, hence the indication of a lacuna.</p>
                </metDecl>
            <metDecl pattern="7a&#x2019;bba&#x2019;a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;" xml:lang="it">
                <p>(MW 1302,1 = Frank 472); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-ou(r)s</hi>; lo stesso schema metrico è adottato da altri sei
                    testi, tutti in settenari e con la stessa alternanza di rime maschili e
                    femminili; tra questi vi è la canzone RS 1141 del Conte di Bretagna che ha la
                    stessa struttura a cinque <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi> e le stesse
                    rime, mentre le prime tre strofi della canzone RS 1135 di Moniot d’Arras hanno
                    anch’esse le stesse rime <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>/ <hi rend="italic">-ous</hi>; va aggiunto inoltre che lo stesso schema, con rime diverse, è
                    usato dalla canzone di crociata anonima RS 1738a, databile al 1244-1245; tra i
                    testi trobadorici lo schema è usato da Raimon de Miraval nella canzone BdT 406.7
                    (solo rime maschili) e nel sirventese anonimo BdT 461.247 che ha la stessa
                    alternanza di rime maschili e femminili (e rime <hi rend="italic">-ia</hi> / <hi rend="italic">-os</hi> nelle strofi iii e iv); mancano due versi alla fine
                    della prima strofe, e la frase precedente potrebbe essere incompleta; per questo
                    motivo la lacuna viene segnalata graficamente.</p>
            </metDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2014-03-17T15:13:02Z</date><name>Tomaz Erjavec</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader><text><front>
        <p rend="Title">RS 1133 Anonimo</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic bold">Ne chant pas, que que nuls die</hi></p>
    </front><body/><back>
                <div type="historical" xml:lang="en">
                <p>See the corresponding paragraph in the introduction to RS 164. The references
                    allow us to situate the present text, as RS 164, after the Gaza ambush and
                    before the liberation of the Christian prisoners, so between 13 November 1239
                    and 23 April 1241, and it seems likely that in this case too the song was
                    composed before the departure of Thibaut de Champagne and the greater part of
                    the French contingent, around the middle of September 1240.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="historical" xml:lang="it">
                <p>Si veda il paragrafo corrispondente nell’introduzione della canzone RS 164. Anche
                    i riferimenti contenuti in questo testo permettono di situarne la composizione
                    dopo l’imboscata di Gaza e prima della liberazione dei prigionieri cristiani,
                    quindi tra il 13 novembre 1239 e il 23 aprile 1241, e anche in questo caso
                    sembra probabile che la stesura del testo preceda la partenza di Thibaut de
                    Champagne e della maggior parte del contingente francese, verso la metà di
                    settembre del 1240.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="notes" xml:lang="en">
                <p>Unlike RS 164 this text does not criticise the crusade leaders’ caution after the
                    Gaza episode, and does not appear to agree with the barons’ position. Instead it
                    adopts the point of view of the lesser, poor knights (<hi rend="italic">bachelers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vavasours</hi>, vv. 31-32), who
                    denounce the barons’ rivalries and their imprudent personal initiatives which
                    produced disastrous consequences (vv. 7, 11-14, 43-46), while at the same time
                    complaining about the prolonged period of inactivity (vv. 5-6, 21-24, 31-40).
                    Despite expressing disapproval over the Gaza sortie, the song ends with a prayer
                    for the liberation of the prisoners. Particularly notable is the realism
                    expressed in these lines which form a sort of caption to the events narrated in
                    the chronicle in which they are set, giving us access to the state of mind and
                    opinions of the participants in the later crusades. Idealistic motives do not
                    seem as clear as they once were, and in any case they are not highlighted;
                    instead, more worldly preoccupations predominate: ambition for personal glory on
                    the part of individual barons, the problems of the high cost of the expeditions
                    and the economic difficulties of the minor knights. </p>
                <p>The anonymous author cannot have been an entirely uncultured man, given that his
                    versification forms part of a network of literary references that cannot be put
                    down to chance. He must have at least known the song RS 1135 of Moniot d’Arras,
                    from which he takes the rhymes of the first three stanzas (and also the
                    expression <hi rend="italic">que q’en die</hi> of the incipit). Some influence
                    of the Occitan <hi rend="italic">sirventes</hi> BdT 461.247 is also possible,
                    given the application of the metrical schema to a crusade song which expresses
                    polemical positions. Still to be resolved is the identification of the count of
                    Brittany, author of a few lyrics which are often sprinkled with formal
                    irregularities. One of these songs imitates the metrical shape and rhymes of RS
                    1133. Some scholars suggest the count may be Pierre Mauclerc, who took part in
                    the barons’ crusade, while Bédier prefers to identify him with Pierre’s son Jean
                    (married <pb type="soft"/>to Bianca, daughter of Thibaut de Champagne), though
                    his arguments do not appear definitive (Bédier 1928, pp. 477-482; note for
                    example that the <hi rend="italic">Continuation Rothelin</hi> continues to call
                    Pierre Mauclerc count of Brittany, even though his son succeeded him in 1237).
                    If the count of Brittany the lyric author were identifiable with the crusader
                    Pierre Mauclerc, he might conceivably be the actual author of RS 164, in which
                    we find similar metrical irregularities to those found in the small corpus
                    attributed to the count of Brittany, and which in any case expresses positions
                    that chime well with the character concerned, with the advantage that, unlike
                    Philippe de Nanteuil, he was not taken prisoner at Gaza.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=7,@n=8)]">These lines appear to confirm the death of Count Henry II of Bar-le-Duc at
                    Gaza, which the same chronicle has called into doubt on the preceding pages (<hi rend="italic">Cont. Roth.</hi> p. 546), but which the other sources certify.
                    See the note to v. 20 of RS 164.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=13,@n=15)]">The problem of the rivalries and internal divisions in the crusading army,
                    which was already emerging clearly during the first crusade, seems to have
                    diminished somewhat during the 12th-c. crusades or to have applied only at the
                    level of the rulers; but it explodes again in the 13th c. and becomes
                    particularly glaring during the barons’ crusade, as is shown by all the sources,
                    especially the <hi rend="italic">Continuation Rothelin</hi> (see the excellent
                    syntheses of Balard 1989 and Lower 2005, pp. 167-175).</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=21,@n=24)]">Rather than blaming the incompetence of the expedition’s leaders – a
                    criticism from which many historians have not spared Thibaut de Champagne – the
                    author seems to attribute the cause of inactivity mainly to the divisions and
                    rivalries in the Christian army and to the barons’ personal initiatives.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro:(n=28)">This text, as RS164, shows the emergence of emphasis on French nationalism
                    (see also v. 41) which charcterises the later crusades.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=31,@n=40)]">The ‘bachelors’ are young knights or those aspiring to be such, generally
                    having no fief and destined to perform military service under a lord. The
                    vavassors constitute one of the lowest grades in the feudal hierarchy holding a
                    small fief over which they are unable to exercise direct rights, since some of
                    the latter remain the apanage of higher-ranking lords, so they are obliged to
                    lend military service to the real lord. The hereditary system of fiefs often
                    brought about the impoverishment of these two classes, and the equation of
                    vavassors and poverty is often present in courtly literature, which in some
                    cases tends to exalt the dignity and nobility of soul of those belonging to
                    these classes (Köhler 2000). See for example the romances of Chrétien de Troyes
                    and Bertran de Born’s song BdT 80.37, 12-22. Furthermore those belonging to the
                    lower nobility were often constrained to pawn and mortgage their lands to
                    procure the funds necessary to finance the expedition (Cazel 1989), a phenomenon
                    alluded to in vv. 33-34. This stanza seems to express its solidarity with the
                    lower levels of feudal society, to which the author may well belong.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=41,@n=47)]">These lines synthesise well on the one hand the mood of disillusionment in
                    the face of the ever more negative results produced by expeditions to the Holy
                    Land, and on the other, the residual hope in divine intervention which alone can
                    guarantee their success.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="notes" xml:lang="it"> <p>Contrariamente alla canzone RS 164, questo testo non
                    critica la prudenza dei capi della spedizione dopo l’episodio di Gaza e non
                    sembra accordarsi con la posizione dei baroni. Si tratta piuttosto del punto di
                    vista dei piccoli cavalieri poveri (<hi rend="italic">bachelers</hi> e <hi rend="italic">vavasours</hi>, vv. 31-32), che stigmatizzano le invidie tra i
                    baroni e le improvvide iniziative personali dall’esito disastroso (vv. 7, 11-14,
                    43-46), ma al contempo non apprezzano l’inerzia e l’inattività prolungata (vv.
                    5-6, 21-24, 31-40). Malgrado la disapprovazione espressa per la sortita di Gaza,
                    la canzone si chiude con una preghiera per la liberazione dei prigionieri. Va
                    rilevato in particolare il realismo espresso nei versi, quasi una didascalia
                    degli eventi narrati dalla cronaca che li contiene, che permette di conoscere lo
                    stato d’animo e le opinioni dei partecipanti alle ultime crociate. Le
                    motivazioni ideali non sembrano più così chiare, e in ogni caso non vengono
                    messe in primo piano; prevalgono invece preoccupazioni più mondane e pratiche:
                    le ambizioni di gloria personale dei singoli baroni, i problemi dei costi
                    elevati delle spedizioni e le difficoltà economiche dei piccoli cavalieri.</p>
                <p>L’anonimo autore dei versi non doveva essere del tutto sprovvisto di cultura, se
                    si tiene conto che grazie al suo schema metrico questo testo s’inserisce in una
                    rete di riferimenti letterari che non possono essere casuali. Egli doveva
                    conoscere almeno la canzone RS 1135 di Moniot d’Arras, della quale riprende le
                    rime delle prime tre strofi (e anche l’espressione <hi rend="italic">que q’en
                        die</hi> dell’incipit), ma non è da escludere, vista l’applicazione dello
                    schema metrico a una canzone di crociata che esprime posizioni polemiche,
                    un’influenza del sirventese occitanico BdT 461.247. Resterebbe da sciogliere il
                        <pb type="soft"/>nodo dell’identificazione del conte di Bretagna autore di
                    alcune canzoni liriche, spesso condite di varie irregolarità formali, una delle
                    quali imita lo schema metrico e le rime della RS 1133; alcuni studiosi
                    propendono per Pierre Mauclerc, protagonista della crociata dei baroni, mentre
                    Bédier sostiene la candidatura del figlio Jean (sposo di Bianca, figlia di
                    Thibaut de Champagne), con argomenti che tuttavia non appaiono definitivi
                    (Bédier 1928, pp. 477-482; si noti per esempio che la <hi rend="italic">Continuation Rothelin</hi> continua a chiamare Pierre Mauclerc conte di
                    Bretagna, benché il figlio gli fosse succeduto nel 1237). Se il conte di
                    Bretagna autore delle liriche fosse identificabile con il crociato Pierre
                    Mauclerc, non sarebbe inverosimile ipotizzare che possa trattarsi del vero
                    autore della canzone RS 164, nella quale si trovano le stesse irregolarità
                    metriche e rimiche che caratterizzano il piccolo corpus attribuito al conte di
                    Bretagna, e che esprime in ogni caso posizioni che ben si accordano con il
                    personaggio, con il vantaggio che, al contrario di Philippe de Nanteuil, egli
                    non fu fatto prigioniero a Gaza.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=7,@n=8)]">Questi versi sembrano confermare la morte del conte Enrico II di Bar-le-Duc
                    a Gaza, che la stessa cronaca mette in dubbio nelle pagine precedenti (<hi rend="italic">Cont. Roth.</hi> p. 546), ma che le altre fonti certificano.
                    Si veda la nota al v. 20 della canzone RS 164.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=13,@n=15)]">Il problema delle invidie e delle divisioni interne al fronte dei
                    crociati, già emerso in modo evidente durante la prima crociata, sembra
                    attenuato o comunque applicabile al solo livello dei sovrani nelle crociate del
                    XII secolo, ma riesplode nel secolo successivo diventando particolarmente
                    evidente durante la crociata dei baroni, come testimoniano tutte le fonti e
                    soprattutto la <hi rend="italic">Continuation Rothelin</hi> (si veda l’ottima
                    sintesi di Balard 1989 e Lower 2005, pp. 167-175).</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=21,@n=24)]">Più che all’inettitudine dei capi della spedizione – critica che molti
                    storici non hanno risparmiato a Thibaut de Champagne – l’autore della canzone
                    sembra attribuire la causa dell’inattività principalmente alle divisioni e alle
                    invidie interne al fronte cristiano e alle iniziative personali dei baroni.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro:(n=28)">Emerge anche in questo testo, come in RS 164, la sottolineatura dell’elemento
                    nazionale francese (si veda anche il v. 41), che caratterizza l’esperienza delle
                    ultime crociate.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=31,@n=40)]">I baccellieri sono giovani cavalieri o aspiranti tali, generalmente privi
                    di feudo e destinati all’attività militare al servizio di un signore; i
                    valvassori costituiscono uno dei gradi più bassi della gerarchia feudale,
                    titolari di un piccolo feudo sul quale non possono esercitare pieni diritti,
                    poiché alcuni di essi restano appannaggio dei signori di grado superiore, e
                    tenuti comunque a prestare un servizio militare al proprio signore. Il
                    particolare sistema ereditario dei feudi comportava frequentemente
                    l’impoverimento di queste due classi, e l’equazione tra valvassori e povertà è
                    spesso presente nella letteratura cortese, che in alcuni casi tende ad esaltare
                    la dignità e la nobiltà d’animo degli appartenenti a queste classi (Köhler
                    2000). Si vedano per esempio i romanzi di Chrétien de Troyes e la canzone di
                    Bertran de Born BdT 80.37, 12-22. Gli appartenenti alla piccola nobiltà erano
                    inoltre spesso costretti a impegnare e ipotecare le loro terre per procurarsi il
                    denaro necessario al finanziamento della spedizione (Cazel 1989), fenomeno al
                    quale fanno riferimento i vv. 33-34. Questa strofe sembra solidarizzare proprio
                    con le classi inferiori della società feudale, alle quali appartiene
                    verosimilmente lo stesso autore.</p>
                <p corresp="#RS.1133.fro[range(@n=41,@n=47)]">Questi versi sintetizzano bene da un lato l’atmosfera di disillusione per
                    l’esito sempre più negativo che vanno assumendo le spedizioni in Terra Santa, e
                    dall’altro la residua speranza in un intervento divino, che solo può garantire
                    il successo delle operazioni.</p>
            </div>
        </back></text></TEI>
