<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2015-02-03</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Tarbé 1850, 49 (version II, text of P); Tarbé 1862, 33 (version I, stanzas I-IV); Brakelmann 1868, 347 (version I, diplomatic edition of C); Bartsch 1870, 164 (stanzas I-II, text of u); Servois 1893, 117 (stanzas I-II, text of u); Bertoni 1917, 362 (version II, diplomatic edition of H); Spanke 1925, 2 (versions I and II); Lejeune 1936, 90 (stanzas I-II, text of u); Petersen Dyggve 1944, 61 (versions I and II); Lecoy 1970, 119 (stanzas I-II, text of u); Dufournet 1989, 92 (version I); Lepage 1994, 424 (versions I and II).</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Tarbé 1850, 49 (versione II, testo di P); Tarbé 1862, 33 (versione I, strofe i-v); Brakelmann 1868, 347 (versione I, edizione diplomatica di C); Bartsch 1870, 164 (strofe i-ii, testo di u); Servois 1893, 117 (strofe i-ii, testo di u); Bertoni 1917, 362 (versione II, edizione diplomatica di H); Spanke 1925, 2 (versioni I e II); Lejeune 1936, 90 (strofe i-ii, testo di u); Petersen Dyggve 1944, 61 (versioni I e II); Lecoy 1970, 119 (strofe i-ii, testo di u); Dufournet 1989, 92 (versione I); Lepage 1994, 424 (versioni I e II).</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl><hi rend="bold">(4+5+1)</hi>: version I = C 107r (112r; anonymous, but in the Gace Brulé group), M 38d (<hi rend="italic">me sire Gasse</hi>), O 59c (anon., but in the Gace Brulé group; modern attribution <hi rend="italic">Renaud de Sabueil</hi>), a 88a (<hi rend="italic">Blondiaus de Neele</hi> in the Index); version II = H 220b (anon.), K 303b (anon.), N 144b (287b, anon.), P 158b (anon.), X 193b (anon.); u 89a (stanzas I and II, <hi rend="italic">Renaut de sabloeil</hi>).</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl><hi rend="bold">(4+5+1)</hi>: versione I = C 107r (112r; anonima, ma gruppo Gace Brulé), M 38d (<hi rend="italic">me sire Gasse</hi>), O 59c (anon., ma gruppo Gace Brulé; attribuzione moderna <hi rend="italic">Renaud de Sabueil</hi>), a 88a (<hi rend="italic">Blondiaus de Neele</hi> nella tavola); versione II = H 220b (anon.), K 303b (anon.), N 144b (287b, anon.), P 158b (anon.), X 193b (anon.); u 89a (strofe i e ii, <hi rend="italic">Renaut de sabloeil</hi>).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>7a’b’a’b’ca’ca’ (MW 1113,1 = Frank 349), <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> in trouvère lyric; version I: 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi> with 2 <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> of 4 (ca’ca’) and 3 (a’ca’) lines; rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-i(p)te(s)</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; rhyme c = <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-é(z)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>; version II: 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi> with one <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> of 4 lines with different rhymes from those of the full stanzas (ca’ca’); rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ue</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">-oie</hi>); rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ure</hi>; rhyme c = <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">-i</hi>) (the rhyme c is fixed in the four full stanzas, but changes in the <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>); in version I, rich rhymes vv. 1, 6, 11, 16 (<hi rend="italic">vie-servie-envie-desservie</hi>), 13 and 15 (<hi rend="italic">repent-pent</hi>), 19 and 32 (<hi rend="italic">faire-refaire</hi>, also derivative), 33, 38 and 48 (<hi rend="italic">escondite-maudite-dite</hi>, also derivative), 47 and 54 (<hi rend="italic">pardoner-doner</hi>); identical rhymes in the <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> vv. 52 and 55 (<hi rend="italic">Egypte</hi>). Melody of version I in MO; melody of version II in KNPX (T 697); the melodic lines of the different witnesses do not present significant variants.</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">7a’b’a’b’ca’ca’ (MW 1113,1 = Frank 349), <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> nella lirica dei trovieri; versione I: 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi> con 2 <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 4 (ca’ca’) e 3 (a’ca’) versi; rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-i(p)te(s)</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-é(z)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>; versione II: 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas capcaudadas</hi> con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 4 versi con rime diverse dalle strofe (ca’ca’); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ue</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">-oie</hi>); rima b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ure</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-ent</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">-i</hi>) (la rima c è fissa nelle quattro strofe, ma cambia nell’<hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>); per quanto riguarda la versione I, vi è rima paronima tra i vv. 1, 6, 11, 16 (<hi rend="italic">vie-servie-envie-desservie</hi>), 13 e 15 (<hi rend="italic">repent-pent</hi>), 19 e 32 (<hi rend="italic">faire-refaire</hi>, anche derivativa), 33, 38 e 48 (<hi rend="italic">escondite-maudite-dite</hi>, anche derivativa), 47 e 54 (<hi rend="italic">pardoner-doner</hi>); rima identica negli <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> ai vv. 52 e 55 (<hi rend="italic">Egypte</hi>). Melodia della versione I in MO; melodia della versione II in KNPX (T 697); le linee melodiche dei vari testimoni non presentano varianti significative.type="music" </metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The manuscript tradition presents two distinct versions of this song, which have only the first two stanzas in common: the first version, composed of six stanzas and two <hi rend="italic">envois</hi>, is found in mss. CMOa; the second, composed of four stanzas and one <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>, is in mss. HKNPX. Ms. u, the sole witness of Jean Renart’s <hi rend="italic">Guillaume de Dole</hi>, into which the song is inserted as a lyric quotation, records only the first two stanzas, and contains some individual readings of both versions. The reference to departure for the East is found only in the <hi rend="italic">envois</hi> of CMOa. My edition is based on these mss. and disregards HKNPX and u, since it is impossible to demonstrate the existence of a single archtype of the different versions. Neither is it possible to establish a hierarchy among the mss. of the first version, even if in the second part of the song in particular some binary alternatives appear to divide mss. CO and Ma, in conformity with the stemmi outlined by Schwan 1886. O has been chosen as base ms., despite the scribe’s tendency to rewrite, because it is the only ms. along with C to record the complete text and has the advantage of a high number of conservative and <hi rend="italic">difficilior</hi> readings.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>La tradizione manoscritta presenta due versioni distinte di questa canzone, che hanno in comune solo le prime due strofe: la prima versione, composta da sei strofe e due congedi, è attestata dai mss. CMOa; la seconda versione, composta da quattro strofe e un congedo, è invece attestata dai mss. HKNPX. Il ms. u, testimone unico del <hi rend="italic">Guillaume de Dole</hi> di Jean Renart, nel quale la canzone è inserita come citazione lirica, riporta unicamente le prime due strofe, condividendo alcune lezioni particolari di entrambe le versioni. L’accenno alla partenza per l’Oriente si trova solo nei congedi della versione di CMOa, di cui si fornisce l’edizione senza tener conto della testimonianza di HKNPX e di u, essendo impossibile dimostrare l’esistenza di un unico archetipo comune alle diverse versioni. Non è neppure possibile stabilire una gerarchia tra i testimoni della prima versione, anche se soprattutto nella seconda parte della canzone si delineano alcune alternative binarie che oppongono i mss. CO a Ma, conformemente agli stemmi delineati da Schwan 1886. Si è scelto O come manoscritto base, malgrado la tendenza alla riscrittura del suo copista, perché si tratta dell’unico testimone, insieme a C, che riporta il testo completo e ha al suo attivo un alto numero di lezioni conservative e <hi rend="italic">difficiliores</hi>.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2015-02-03T18:45:14Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Anonymous</titlePart><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1229.en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>For the rest of my life I no more wish to have a heart disposed to sing, but prefer Love to slay me, to her own grave harm, because she will never again be so perfectly loved or served; so I declare to all: she has killed me and betrayed herself.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Alas, I realise full well that I have spoken foolishly and presumptuously, but my heart was moved to be frivolous and inconstant. Ah, lady, I repent of this so much, but it is too late to cry mercy once one is hanged [by the neck]; for this I have deserved to die.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>I am constrained to renounce Love on account of <hi rend="italic">her</hi> hypocritical conduct; I am sorry for it, [but] I can do no other, because <hi rend="italic">she</hi> ruins me against <hi rend="italic">her</hi> own interests; but <hi rend="italic">her</hi> nature is such that the one who should please <hi rend="italic">her</hi> most is always the most tormented by <hi rend="italic">her</hi>; this is why <hi rend="italic">she</hi> is a fickle traitress.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Mercy ought to be greater than justice and law; lady, I have been unable to remain silent and I know not whence comes my impatience; I have spoken most foolishly, and for this God should punish me as the despairing fool that I am, for in <hi rend="italic">her</hi> there has never been any imperfection.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>I have always defended <hi rend="italic">her</hi>, but now I see in <hi rend="italic">her</hi> what dismays me, when <hi rend="italic">she</hi> deprives of all <hi rend="italic">her</hi> favours the one who is most faithful to <hi rend="italic">her</hi> and leaves him in suspense, hence is untrustworthy; as far as I am concerned, may <hi rend="italic">she</hi> be accursed: of the joy that comes from love, which I once had in abundance, I now have very little.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Most wrongly have I slandered the truest in the world; so I hold myself to be a traitor and place myself in <hi rend="italic">her</hi> hands; <hi rend="italic">she</hi> can always condemn me for this, but may God reward <hi rend="italic">her</hi>, if <hi rend="italic">she</hi> were willing to forgive me for the lie I have spoken.</p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>Count, I wish to send Narcissus to bear my song overseas, written in his heart, right into the land of Egypt.</p></div><div n="8" type="stanza"><p>Renaut, God bring great misfortune onto the one who dishonours Love! On <hi rend="italic">her</hi> account I leave for Egypt.</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1229.it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Non voglio avere mai più in vita mia il cuore disposto a cantare, anzi preferisco che Amore mi uccida, a <hi rend="italic">suo</hi> grave danno, perché non sarà mai più servita così bene; per questo dichiaro a tutti: ha ucciso me e tradito <hi rend="italic">lei</hi>.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Ahimè, ho detto davvero una cosa folle e presuntuosa, ma al mio cuore è venuta voglia di essere frivolo e scostante. Ah, signora, ne sono profondamente pentito, ma troppo tardi invoca la grazia chi aspetta fino a quando l’hanno (ormai) appeso (per il collo); per questo ho meritato di morire.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Sono costretto a rinnegare Amore a causa della <hi rend="italic">sua</hi> condotta ipocrita; mi dispiace, ma non posso fare diversamente, perché mi respinge andando contro <hi rend="italic">se stessa</hi> (contro il <hi rend="italic">suo</hi> interesse); ma la <hi rend="italic">sua</hi> natura è tale che colui che più <hi rend="italic">la</hi> compiace, più ne è tormentato; è proprio una traditrice infida.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>La pietà dev’essere più grande della giustizia e del diritto; signora, non ho potuto tacere e non so da dove mi è venuta questa insofferenza; ho parlato in modo molto sciocco, e Dio dovrebbe punirmi, come il folle senza speranza che sono, perché in <hi rend="italic">lei</hi> non c’è mai stato niente di sbagliato.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>L’ho sempre giustificata, ma ora vedo in <hi rend="italic">lei</hi> chi mi sgomenta, quando a chi più <hi rend="italic">le</hi> è fedele toglie ogni bene e lo lascia in sospeso, quindi non (ci) si deve fidare; per quanto mi riguarda <hi rend="italic">la</hi> maledico: la gioia che viene dall’amore, che fu già grande, ora è minima.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Ho calunniato a torto la più leale di tutte, per questo mi considero un traditore e mi rimetto in <hi rend="italic">sua</hi> balia; può sempre condannarmi per questo, ma Dio <hi rend="italic">le</hi> renda merito, se volesse perdonarmi la menzogna che ho detto.</p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>Conte, voglio mandare Narciso perché porti la mia canzone scritta nel suo cuore oltremare, nella terra d’Egitto.</p></div><div n="8" type="stanza"><p>Renaut, che Dio possa maledire chi disprezza Amore! A causa <hi rend="italic">sua</hi> me ne vado in Egitto.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
