<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2014-05-07</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>La Ravallière 1742, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 139; Auguis 1824, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 9; Tarbé 1850, 40; Bartsch 1908, 187; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 199; Wallensköld 1925, 61; Brahney 1989, 76.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(9) K 21b-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 64d-65a (anonima), O 70ac (anon.), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 29v-30v (<hi rend="italic">Monios</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 79rv (anon.), T 8v-9r (anon., but <hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>), V 10c-11a (anon.), X 21d-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), a 5rv (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>). All mss. insert this song into a corpus of texts attributed to Thibaut de Champagne, with the sole exception of R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, whose attribution cannot be considered reliable.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(9) K 21b-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 64d-65a (anonima), O 70ac (anon.), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 29v-30v (<hi rend="italic">Monios</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 79rv (anon.), T 8v-9r (anon., ma <hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>), V 10c-11a (anon.), X 21d-22b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), a 5rv (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navare</hi>). Tutti i testimoni inseriscono questa canzone in un corpus di testi attribuiti a Thibaut de Champagne, con l’eccezione del solo R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, la cui attribuzione non può essere considerata affidabile.</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10abbac’c’aa (MW 1410, 2 = Frank 549); the original model is the crusade song <hi rend="italic">S’onques nuns hons por dure departie</hi> of Hugues de Berzé (RS 1126), of which however only the ‘a’ rhyme is feminine; 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) with a 4-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di (c’c’aa); a = <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; b = <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-u</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>; c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; the identical rhyme-word <hi rend="italic">maintenir</hi> in vv. 4 and 9 (but the two occurrences may have different nuances), <hi rend="italic">avenir</hi> in vv. 12 and 15, <hi rend="italic">vertu</hi> in vv. 19 and 27 <hi rend="italic">aidier</hi> in vv. 23 and 31; lyric caesura in v. 26 and perhaps v. 17; melody in M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVXR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, with M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVX attesting the same melodic line and R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> offering a variant of this; the melody of R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> on the other hand is entirely independent (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 204; Tischler 1997, IX n° 835).</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10abbac’c’aa (MW 1410, 2 = Frank 549); il modello originario è costituito dalla canzone di crociata <hi rend="italic">S’onques nuns hons por dure departie</hi> di Hugues de Berzé (RS 1126), dove però la sola rima femminile è la a; 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 4 versi (c’c’aa); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ier</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-u</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-aie</hi>; <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima identica <hi rend="italic">maintenir</hi> ai vv. 4 e 9 (ma le due occorrenze possono avere sfumature diverse), <hi rend="italic">avenir</hi> ai vv. 12 e 15, <hi rend="italic">vertu</hi> ai vv. 19 e 27 <hi rend="italic">aidier</hi> ai vv. 23 e 31; cesura lirica al v. 26 e forse al v. 17; melodia in M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVXR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, con M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>KVX che concordano nell’attestare la medesima linea melodica e R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> che ne propone una variante; la melodia di R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> è invece totalmente autonoma (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 204; Tischler 1997, IX n° 835).</p></metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The omission of v. 40 shows the usual grouping of mss. KOVX; the version of ms. R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, which lacks stanza V and the envoi, is fairly independent, but is basically linked to KOVX; mss. M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T as usual constitute the second branch of the tradition of Thibaut’s <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>; R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>a, while sharing some readings with M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T (vv. 12 and 22), seem to draw on a different tradition predating the compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>, and it will be appropriate to accept their readings where the variants are indifferent, especially when they are also supported by T. Graphies have been taken from ms. O. The fact that the majority of the mss. present some irregular rhymes (especially in vv. 1 and 20) and some doubtful readings (vv. 25 and 33) convinced Bédier of the existence of a corrupt archetype, but in reality none of these cases seems conclusive.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>La mancanza del v. 40 permette di raggruppare come di consueto i mss. KOVX; il ms. R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, privo della quinta strofa e del congedo, ha una lezione piuttosto autonoma, pur collocandosi sostanzialmente nel gruppo di KOVX; i mss. M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T costituiscono come di consueto il secondo ramo della tradizione del <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi> di Thibaut; R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>a, pur condividendo qualche lezione di M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>T (vv. 12 e 22), sembrano attingere ad una tradizione diversa e anteriore alla compilazione del <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi>, per cui converrà accettarne le lezioni in caso di alternative adiafore, soprattutto quando sono appoggiate anche da T. Come base grafica si è scelto il ms. O. Il fatto che la maggioranza della tradizione presenti qualche infrazione alla rima (soprattutto ai vv. 1 e 20) e qualche lezione dubbia (vv. 25 e 33) ha convinto Bédier dell’esistenza di una copia archetipica corrotta, ma in realtà nessuno di questi casi sembra determinante.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2014-10-03T14:42:10Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"/><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1469.en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Sweet thoughts and sweet memories inflame my heart with the desire to sing, and [also] True Love, which leaves me no peace, which maintains its followers in joy and instils sweet remembrance in hearts; so Love is of most high power, as it makes a man rejoice in suffering and does not let him abandon it despite his pain. </p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>No-one can preserve wisdom and honour without having felt within him the pains of love, nor can he in any way rise to great worth, nor has anyone yet seen this happen. So I beg you, sweet image of love, that downheartedness should not separate us; and that you will not see this come from me, since I wish to die entirely perfect in love.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Lady, if I had dared to beseech you I think I might have been most fortunate, but there is in me not sufficient courage that I dare to look at you directly. This reduces me to nothing, kills and terrorises me; your beauty inflicts such a wound in my heart that my eyes are not enough to assist me in looking at you as I desire.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>When I had to part from you, my lady, there was certainly not a more sorrowful man than I, and God would, I think, perform a miracle for me if I were ever able to approach you, for all the good and bad things I have, I have from you, sweet true lady, and no-one but you can assist me: they would not do so, since it would be useless. </p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>Her great beauty, a fiftieth of which no-one has the power to describe, her delightful words, her loving glances make me often rejoice and suffer: I expect joy from her, for my heart aspires to this, but fear takes hold of me once more, so I am perforce compelled to die in great distress (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> from privation), in joy and in longing. </p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Lady, for whom is my great desire, I send you greetings from over the salt sea, as to the one of whom I think day and night, and no other thought gives me joy.</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1469.it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Il dolce pensiero e i dolci ricordi accendono nel mio cuore il desiderio di cantare e (anche) il Vero Amore, che non mi dà pace, mantiene i suoi nella gioia e instilla nei cuori la dolce rimembranza; perciò Amore ha un grandissimo potere, visto che fa gioire anche chi è nello sconforto e non fa separare da lui neanche chi soffre.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Nessuno può acquistare saggezza e onore né può in nessun caso assurgere a un grande valore se non ha provato su di sé le pene d’amore e finora nessuno l’ha visto accadere. Per questo vi prego, dolce immagine d’amore, che lo scoramento non ce ne faccia separare; e non vedrete accadere così di me, perché voglio morire irreprensibile in amore.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Signora, se avessi osato supplicarvi avrei forse ottenuto un risultato migliore, ma non ho tanto coraggio da ardire in vostra presenza di rivolgervi la parola. Questa situazione mi annienta, mi uccide e mi terrorizza; la vostra bellezza infligge al mio cuore una tale ferita che i miei poveri occhi non sono sufficienti a guardarvi, come desidererei.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Nessuno ha mai sofferto più di me, quando ho dovuto allontanarmi da voi, e Dio farebbe davvero un prodigio per me se io potessi avvicinarvi, perché tutto il bene e il male che ho lo ricevo da voi, dolce signora leale, e nessuno potrebbe aiutarmi se non voi, né lo farebbe, perché sarebbe inutile.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>La sua grande bellezza, di cui nessuno riuscirebbe a descrivere neppure la cinquantesima parte, le parole gradevoli e gli sguardi amorosi mi fanno spesso gioire e soffrire: mi aspetto la gioia da lei, perché il mio cuore aspira a questo, ed ecco che lo sconforto mi prende di nuovo, e così sono destinato per forza a morire (<hi rend="italic">oppure</hi> a morire di privazione), in grande sconforto, nella gioia e nel desiderio.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Signora, alla quale anela il mio grande desiderio, vi mando i saluti da oltre il mare salato, come a colei cui penso giorno e notte, e nessun altro pensiero mi dà gioia.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
