<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Se j’ai lonc tans esté en Romenie (RS 1204)</title><author>Raoul de Soissons (?)</author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><name>Mike Paterson</name><resp xml:lang="en">Conversion to TEI-conformant markup by</resp><resp xml:lang="it">Conversione al markup conforme a TEI di</resp></respStmt>        <respStmt>
      <name>Luca Barbieri</name>
      <resp xml:lang="en">Italian Translation by</resp>
      <resp xml:lang="it">Traduzione italiana di</resp>
    </respStmt>
      
      <respStmt>
        <name>Anna Radaelli</name>
        <resp xml:lang="en">Italian translation checked by</resp>
        <resp xml:lang="it">Traduzione italiana controllata da</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>      <editionStmt>
      <edition><date>2014</date></edition>
    </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>French Department, University of Warwick</publisher>
        <date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence xml:lang="en" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode"> Distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International Public License</licence><licence xml:lang="it" target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode.it">Distribuito sotto la Licenza Pubblica Creative Commons Attribuzione-CondividiAlloStessoModo 4.0 Internazionale</licence></availability></publicationStmt>
      
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>La Ravallière 1742, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 144; Tarbé 1850, 63; Winkler 1914,
            46; Baumgartner 1983, 122; Rosenberg-Tischler 1995, 646; Hardy 2009
            (www.lfa.uottawa.ca/activites/textes/ineke/Chansons/ R1204ed.htm).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>(4): B 8v (anonymous), N 63d (<hi rend="italic">Mes sires T. de soissons</hi>), Me
            64r? (<hi rend="italic">Messire Thierri de Soissons</hi>), V 59c (anon., modern
            attribution <hi rend="italic">Raoul de Soissons</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>(4): B 8v (anonima), N 63d (<hi rend="italic">Mes sires T. de soissons</hi>), Me
            64r? (<hi rend="italic">Messire Thierri de Soissons</hi>), V 59c (anon., attribuzione
            moderna <hi rend="italic">Raoul de Soissons</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">
        <p>10a’b’b’a’a’b’b’a’a’ (MW 1310,2 = Frank 477); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi>,
          plus three initial lines of what is probably a sixth stanza (rhymes a’b’b’ repeated from
          the fifth stanza); rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ele</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; numerous rich and leonine rhymes, including
          some involving the repetition of whole words, vv. 11 and 16 (<hi rend="italic">sage</hi>
          and <hi rend="italic">visage</hi>), 12 and 15 (<hi rend="italic">rage </hi>and<hi rend="italic"> coraige</hi>), 24-25 (<hi rend="italic">semblance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lance</hi>); there is a lyric caesura in v. 28 and a feminine caesura with elision in
          vv. 9 and 10. Melody in N and a second independent melody in V (T 682).</p>
      </metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">
        <p>10a’b’b’a’a’b’b’a’a’ (MW 1310,2 = Frank 477); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi>, più
          tre versi iniziali di una probabile sesta strofa (rime a’b’b’ riprese dalla quinta
          strofa); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-aine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ele</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-age</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; numerose rime ricche e leonine; rima paronima
          ai vv. 11 e 16 (<hi rend="italic">sage</hi> e <hi rend="italic">visage</hi>), 12 e 15 (<hi rend="italic">rage </hi>e<hi rend="italic"> coraige</hi>), 24-25 (<hi rend="italic">semblance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lance</hi>); vi è cesura lirica al v. 28 e cesura
          femminile con elisione ai vv. 9 e 10. Melodia in N e seconda melodia indipendente in V (T
          682).</p>
      </metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en">
        <p>Analysis of the ms. readings show the division NV and B, confirming the stemma of Schwan
          1886, p. 171 which also appears in other editions and studies. V shows its typical
          independence, thought this is noticeably more pronounced than usual. The evidence from Me
          is negligible since it is reduced to the first two lines of the song. The edition is based
          on B, the only ms. to record the last incomplete stanza, and the transmitter of some
          conservative readings.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it">
        <p>L’analisi delle lezioni permette di separare i mss. NV e B, confermando così lo stemma di
          Schwan 1886, p. 171 nonché quanto è emerso in altre edizioni e in altri studi. Il
          canzoniere V mostra l’autonomia di lezione tipica di questo testimone, ma notevolmente più
          accentuata del consueto. L’apporto di Me è trascurabile in quanto ridotto ai primi due
          versi della canzone. L’edizione si basa sulla lezione di B, unico testimone che riporta
          l’ultima strofa incompleta e latore di alcune lezioni conservative.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2014-10-08T13:32:59Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Raoul de Soissons (?)</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1204.en" xml:lang="en">
        <head> Translation </head>
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
          <p>Even if I have stayed in the East for a long time and made my pilgrimage overseas,
            suffering many painful reverses and enduring many grave illnesses, now I am in a worse
            state than I ever was in the Holy Land, because good love has inflicted on me an
            affliction whose pain is never assuaged, but instead continues to increase and double
            and multiply, making my face pale and bloodless.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
          <p>A delightful young lady, merry, sweet and pleasing, beautiful and courtly and virtuous
            has put such a sweet madness in my heart that it makes me lose my sight and hearing, as
            one who sleeps lethargically, so that no-one can rouse him to consciousness; for when I
            think of her most sweet face, I prefer the company of my thoughts more than Tristan ever
            did of his beloved Yseut.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
          <p>Love has struck me in in the most telling spot through a look full of sweet promise,
            from which the most virtuous lady of France, and the supreme rose of beauty, has injured
            me; and I marvel that the injury does not heal, because it has wounded me with such a
            sweet appearance that I have never seen such a sharp lance-head; it is like the siren’s
            song, whose sweetness brings pain and suffering.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
          <p>If only I could feel her sweet breath and take pleasure in her lovely ways, for I long
            for love and intimacy with her more than Paris longed for Helen; and if Love is not too
            cruel to me, there will be no pain without recompense, for her beauty and her most great
            worth and the way she looked so lovely when I saw her for the first time bestowed on me
            the gift of a hundred sighs a day.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="stanza">
          <p>For her face, which is so sweet and beautiful, has left me with but a single thought,
            and this has so inflamed my heart that I feel it more burning and glowing than an ember
            or a spark; therefore I cannot live long if I fail to strike my lady with compassion,
            when my song tells her of the pain which lashes me on her account.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="stanza">
          <p>Song, go to Archer who plays the viel and to Raoul de Soissons, whom I like: tell them
            that love is too sharp a sword... </p>
        </div>
      </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.1204.it" xml:lang="it">
        <head> Translation </head>
        <div n="1" type="stanza">
          <p>Anche se ho soggiornato a lungo in Oriente e ho fatto il mio pellegrinaggio oltremare
            patendovi molti rovesci dolorosi e sopportando molte gravi malattie, ora sto peggio di
            come stavo in Terra Santa, perché il buon amore mi ha inflitto una tale sofferenza il
            cui dolore non si attenua mai, ma anzi cresce di continuo e raddoppia e si moltiplica,
            al punto che il mio volto ne è reso pallido ed esangue.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="stanza">
          <p>Una giovane signora gentile e gaia, dolce e piacente, bella e cortese e virtuosa mi ha
            messo nel cuore una così dolce smania che mi fa perdere la vista e l’udito, come colui
            che dorme di un sonno letargico, dal quale nessuno può ridestare la sua coscienza;
            infatti, quando penso al suo dolcissimo volto, amo più la compagnia del mio pensiero di
            quanto Tristano fece con la sua amante Isotta.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="stanza">
          <p>Amore mi ha davvero colpito nel punto giusto attraverso uno sguardo colmo di dolce
            promessa, col quale mi ha ferito la più virtuosa di Francia, e di bellezza la rosa
            sovrana; e mi stupisco che la ferita non sanguini, perché mi ha ferito con un aspetto
            così dolce che non ho mai visto una punta di lancia tanto acuminata; è simile al canto
            della sirena, la cui dolcezza è causa di dolori e sofferenza.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="stanza">
          <p>Potessi sentire il suo dolce alito e godere delle sue belle maniere, perché desidero il
            suo amore e la sua intimità più di quanto Paride desiderò Elena; e se Amore non è troppo
            crudele con me, non vi sarà pena senza ricompensa, perché la sua bellezza e la sua
            grandissima virtù e il bell’aspetto quando la vidi per la prima volta mi hanno lasciato
            in dono cento sospiri al giorno.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="stanza">
          <p>Perché il suo viso, che è tanto dolce e bello, mi ha lasciato un unico pensiero, e
            questo mi ha a tal punto infiammato il cuore che lo sento più caldo e più guizzante di
            una brace e di una favilla; quindi non posso resistere a lungo se non riuscirò a ferire
            la mia signora con la compassione, quando la mia canzone le farà sapere del dolore che
            mi flagella a causa sua.</p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="stanza">
          <p>Canzone, vai da Arciere che suona la viella e da Raoul de Soissons, che mi è simpatico:
            di’ loro che l’amore è una spada troppo tagliente...</p>
        </div>
      </div></body></text></TEI>
