<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Linda Paterson</author>
                <funder>AHRC</funder>
                <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
                <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Steve Ranford</name>
                    <resp>conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>joe bloggs</name>
                    <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
                <date>2014</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <listBibl type="essential_bibliography">
                    <bibl>Buchon 1840: Jean Alexandre C. Buchon, Recherches et matériaux pour servir
                        à une histoire de la domination française aux XIIIe, XIVe et XVe siècles
                        dans les provinces démembrées de l’Empire grec à la suite de la quatrième
                        croisade, Paris, Desrez, 1840.</bibl>
                    <bibl>De Bartholomaeis 1906: Vincenzo De Bartholomaeis, «Il troviero Chardon de
                        Croisilles», Studj romanzi, 4, 1906, pp. 261-297.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guesnon 1909: Adolphe-Henri Guesnon, «Publications nouvelles sur les
                        trouvères artésiens», Le Moyen Âge, 13, 1909, pp. 65-93, on pp.
                        89-93.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paris (Louis) 1855: Louis Paris, «Champagne – XIV. – Cardons de Reims», Le
                        Cabinet historique, 1, 1855, pp. 56-58.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paris (Paulin) 1856: Paulin Paris, Histoire littéraire de la France, 23,
                        Paris, Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, 1856, pp.
                        536-537.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Radaelli 2007: Anna Radaelli, «Una donna per due uomini o due uomini per
                        una donna? La tenzo del Chardo e d’En Ugo (BdT 114.1 = 448.2)», Cultura
                        neolatina, 67, 2007, pp. 235-251.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schultz-Gora 1884: Oskar Schultz-Gora, «Das Verhältnis der provenzalischen
                        Pastourelle zur altfranzösischen», Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie, 8,
                        1884, pp. 106-112.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Suchier 1907: Hermann Suchier, «Der Minnesänger Chardon», Zeitschrift für
                        romanische Philologie, 31, 1907, pp. 129-156.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tarbé 1850: Prosper Tarbé, Les chansonniers de Champagne aux XIIe et XIIIe
                        siècles, Reims, Regnier, 1850.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <listBibl type="previous_editions">
                    <bibl>Buchon 1840, 425;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tarbé 1850, 29;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paris 1855, 57;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Suchier 1907, 144;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bédier-Aubry 1909, 209;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cremonesi 1955, 134;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toja 1974, 278;</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dijkstra 1995a, 208.</bibl>
                </listBibl>

                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno>K 253b</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">chardon</hi>)</p>
                </msDesc>

                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno>N 124b</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">chardon de rains</hi>)</p>
                </msDesc>

                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno>P 112b</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <p> (<hi rend="italic">Chardons</hi>)</p>
                </msDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno>T 42r</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">Robers de blois</hi>)</p>
                </msDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno>X 171ab</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">chardon</hi>)</p>
                </msDesc>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <metDecl pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;" xml:lang="en">
                <p>10a’ba’bba’ba’ (MW 902,9 = Frank 302); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas
                        doblas/ternas</hi> (2+3) with a four-line <hi rend="italic">envoi
                    </hi>(ba’ba’); rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>;
                    rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-or</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-i</hi>; a very common
                    metrical shape adopted by Conon de Béthune in his famous crusade song RS 1125
                    (whose first stanza uses the rhymes <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">-or</hi> also found in Chardon’s text) and imitated in other
                    texts linked to the crusade such as Richard de Fournival’s RS 1020a and Huon
                    d’Oisi’s RS 1030 (but only with m. rhymes).</p>
            </metDecl>
            <metDecl pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;" xml:lang="it">
                <p>10a’ba’bba’ba’ (MW 902,9 = Frank 302); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas
                        doblas/ternas</hi> (2+3) con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi>di 4 versi
                    (ba’ba’); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima
                    b = <hi rend="italic">-or</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-i</hi>; schema metrico
                    diffusissimo adottato da Conon de Béthune nella famosa canzone di crociata RS
                    1125 (che usa nelle prime due strofi le rime <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi> e <hi rend="italic">-or</hi> che si trovano anche nel testo di Chardon) e ripreso
                    da altri testi legati alla crociata come Richard de Fournival RS 1020a e Huon
                    d’Oisi RS 1030 (ma con sole rime maschili).</p>
            </metDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2014-03-17T16:40:55Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader><text><front>

            <p rend="Title">Chardon de Croisilles</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic bold">Li departirs de la douce contree</hi> (RS 499)</p>
        </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="RS.499.eng" xml:lang="en">

                <div type="stanza" n="1">
                    <p>Departure from the sweet land where lives my beauteous one has put me into
                        great sadness; I am constrained to leave the one I have loved the most in
                        order to serve the Lord God my creator, and yet I belong completely to Love,
                        since I leave it all my heart and my thoughts: if my body goes to serve Our
                        Lord, I have not forgotten true love on this account.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="2">
                    <p>Love, this is too hard a parting, when I am forced to leave the best lady who
                        ever existed or who was ever born; in her is all beauty and worth, and none
                        should marvel if I weep at this; when my body goes to fulfil its destiny,
                        see how my noble heart has already begun its return journey, musing and
                        longing after my lady.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="3">
                    <p>Lady, in whom is my death and my life, I depart from you more grief-stricken
                        than I say; henceforth you have my heart in your power: keep it, or you have
                        betrayed me. God, where shall I go? Shall I utter loud laments or cries when
                        I am constrained to divide myself from my noble heart and leave it with the
                        one who has never left me part of hers?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="4">
                    <p>Love justly thanks the false lover for the profit it receives from him, but I
                        obtain no pity; it trusts the flatterer and the fraud, but I trust entirely
                        to noble service; my loyalty, I know this well, deprives me of the joy which
                        I have rightly deserved; it greatly grieves me that I ever set eyes on her,
                        when on her account true love so defies me.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="5">
                    <p>Sweet lady, whom my heart does not forget, for God’s sake please do not
                        forget me! Never will I ever seek another love; for God’s sake, I beseech
                        you, do not seek another lover! But if I learn that you are mocking me, I
                        shall not die entirely, but only half; however you will not make an enemy of
                        me if loyalty is not my enemy.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="6">
                    <p>VI. At the moment of departure, sweet lady, I beg you, whatever a flatterer
                        may say to you, do not forget me, and towards you I in turn will never
                        behave basely.</p>
                </div>


            </div><div type="translation" xml:id="RS.499.it" xml:lang="it">

                <div type="stanza" n="1">
                    <p>La partenza dal dolce paese dov’è la bella mi ha messo in una grande
                        tristezza; sono costretto a lasciare ciò che più ho amato per servire il
                        Signore, mio creatore; tuttavia appartengo completamente ad Amore, poiché
                        gli lascio tutto il mio cuore e il mio pensiero; se il mio corpo va a
                        servire Nostro Signore, per questo non ho dimenticato il vero amore.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="2">
                    <p>Amore, questa è una separazione troppo dura, dal momento che mi tocca partire
                        dalla migliore che sia mai esistita e che sia mai nata; in lei vi è ogni
                        bellezza e valore, nessuno si deve meravigliare se per questo <pb type="soft"/>piango; mentre il mio corpo va a compiere il suo destino,
                        ecco che il mio cuore puro s’è già messo sulla via del ritorno, lui che
                        senza infedeltà pensa e aspira alla mia signora.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="3">
                    <p>Signora, in cui è la mia morte e la mia vita, mi separo da voi più dolente di
                        quanto possa dire; da tempo avete il mio cuore in vostro potere: tenetelo
                        (con voi) o mi avrete tradito. Dio, dove andrò? Mi dispererò o griderò, dal
                        momento che devo separarmi dal mio cuore fedele e lasciarlo a colei che non
                        mi ha mai concesso una parte del suo?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="4">
                    <p>Il falso amante giustamente ringrazia Amore per i beni che riceve, mentre io
                        non ottengo pietà; si affida all’adulazione e all’inganno, ma io mi affido
                        completamente al buon servizio; la mia lealtà mi priva, lo so bene, della
                        gioia che ho meritato a buon diritto. Mi pesa persino d’averla mai vista,
                        dato che il vero amore mi tormenta così a causa sua.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="5">
                    <p>Dolce signora, che il mio cuore non dimentica, per Dio, non vogliate
                        dimenticarvi di me! Non cercherò mai in nessun caso un’altra amica; per Dio,
                        non cercate un altro amico! Ma se saprò che vi prendete gioco di me, non
                        morirò del tutto, ma a metà; tuttavia non farete mai di me un nemico, se la
                        lealtà non mi è nemica.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="stanza" n="6">
                    <p>Al momento di lasciarvi, dolce signora, vi prego, qualunque cosa un adulatore
                        possa dirvi, di non dimenticarmi, e io allo stesso modo non mi comporterò
                        mai in modo vile nei vostri confronti.</p>
                </div>


            </div></body></text></TEI>
