<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2015-12-01</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Wackernagel 1846, 31; Lacour 1856, 33; San-Marte 1861-1862, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 123; Dinaux 1837-1863, <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi> 271; Scheler 1879, 12;
            Brakelmann 1896, 26; Baudler 1902, 78; Orr 1915, 5; Noonan 1933, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 205; Petersen Dyggve 1945, 30; Pauphilet 1952, 921; Picot 1975, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 34; Dufournet 1989, 88.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Wackernagel 1846, 31; Lacour 1856, 33; San-Marte 1861-1862, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 123; Dinaux 1837-1863, <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi> 271; Scheler 1879, 12;
            Brakelmann 1896, 26; Baudler 1902, 78; Orr 1915, 5; Noonan 1933, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 205; Petersen Dyggve 1945, 30; Pauphilet 1952, 921; Picot 1975, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 34; Dufournet 1989, 88.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(10+1).</hi> A 159a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), C 150v (<hi rend="italic">Guios de Provins</hi>), K 221a (<hi rend="italic">Gontier de
              Soigniers</hi>), M 7d (<hi rend="italic">li Vidames de Chartres</hi>), Me 109r?
            (incipit only, <hi rend="italic">Gautier de Soignies</hi>), N 107a (<hi rend="italic">Gontier de Soignies</hi>), P 75c (<hi rend="italic">Gontier de Soignies</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 9r (<hi rend="italic">li Vidames de Chartres</hi>), T 106r
              (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de Chartres</hi>), U 57r (anonymous), a 21v (<hi rend="italic">le Vidame de Cartres</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(10+1).</hi> A 159a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), C 150v (<hi rend="italic">Guios de Provins</hi>), K 221a (<hi rend="italic">Gontier de
              Soigniers</hi>), M 7d (<hi rend="italic">li Vidames de Chartres</hi>), Me 109r? (solo
            incipit, <hi rend="italic">Gautier de Soignies</hi>), N 107a (<hi rend="italic">Gontier
              de Soignies</hi>), P 75c (<hi rend="italic">Gontier de Soignies</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 9r (<hi rend="italic">li Vidames de Chartres</hi>), T 106r
              (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de Chartres</hi>), U 57r (anonima), a 21v (<hi rend="italic">le Vidame de Cartres</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>8a7b’8a7b’8a7b’8a7b’ (MW 689,26 =
        Frank 225); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi> (3+2), the first three also <hi rend="italic">capfinidas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">dolor</hi> vv. 8 and 9, <hi rend="italic">donee-dont</hi> vv. 16-17); rhyme a: <hi rend="italic">-é</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ez</hi>; rhyme b: <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-iere</hi>; identical
        rhyme vv. 7-17 (<hi rend="italic">santé</hi>) and 33-37 (<hi rend="italic">ocïez</hi>),
        equivocal rhyme vv. 9 and 11 (<hi rend="italic">esté</hi>); grammatical rhyme vv. 1-14 (<hi rend="italic">demoré-demoree</hi>), 4-25 (<hi rend="italic">maleüree-maleürez</hi>) and
        16-27 (<hi rend="italic">donee-donez</hi>); paronymous rhyme vv. 16-18 (<hi rend="italic">donee-nee</hi>) and 31-35 (<hi rend="italic">lassez-assez</hi>); derivative rhyme vv.
        28-32 (<hi rend="italic">ariere-deriere</hi>); melody in AKMNPR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>TUa, with various variants; melodic structure ABAB’ CDEB’ (T 244).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>8a7b’8a7b’8a7b’8a7b’ (MW 689,26 =
        Frank 225); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi> (3+2), le prime tre anche <hi rend="italic">capfinidas</hi> (<hi rend="italic">dolor</hi> vv. 8 e 9, <hi rend="italic">donee-dont</hi> vv. 16-17); rima a: <hi rend="italic">-é</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ez</hi>; rima b: <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-iere</hi>; rima identica
        ai vv. 7-17 (<hi rend="italic">santé</hi>) e 33-37 (<hi rend="italic">ocïez</hi>), equivoca
        ai vv. 9 e 11 (<hi rend="italic">esté</hi>); rima grammaticale ai vv. 1-14 (<hi rend="italic">demoré-demoree</hi>), 4-25 (<hi rend="italic">maleüree-maleürez</hi>) e
        16-27 (<hi rend="italic">donee-donez</hi>); rima paronima ai vv. 16-18 (<hi rend="italic">donee-nee</hi>) e 31-35 (<hi rend="italic">lassez-assez</hi>); rima derivativa ai vv.
        28-32 (<hi rend="italic">ariere-deriere</hi>); melodia in AKMNPR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>TUa, con diverse varianti; schema melodico ABAB’ CDEB’ (T 244).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>A good number of common errors and lacunae show
        the threefold division AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta, CU, KNP. Mss. CU generally agree
        with KNP, and support the reading of AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta only when KNP are
        erroneous. The song is attributed to three different authors by the three manuscript
        families: AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta to the Vidame de Chartres, KMePN to Gontier de
        Soignies and C to Guiot de Provins. C’s attributions are generally considered unreliable;
        the numerous analogies with the song RS 502, the difference of style from Gontier de
        Soignies’ usual one and the general reliability of the s<hi rend="superscript">I</hi> group
        of witnesses induce a preference for the attribution to the Vidame de Chartres (see
        Formisano 1980, p. xxxvi). In a situation where a choice has to be made between two
        equivalent alternatives, CU seem to contain an excessively independent version and in AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta a stanza is missing; it has therefore been decided in this
        case to follow KNP, even though in other cases this group is known to be unreliable. The
        choice is made easier by the fact that the variants are minimal and in general do not change
        the sense of the text. I deviate from KNP only to supplete vv. 27-29 which are partly
        missing in these mss. (CU being followed here), and the final syllable of v. 31, and to
        correct the hypermetric vv. 24 (<hi rend="italic">celui</hi> for <hi rend="italic">cil</hi>)
        and 34 (initial <hi rend="italic">ne ne</hi>); finally in vv. 38-39 KNP’s reading appears
        erroneous (in particular the possessive <hi rend="italic">s’amor</hi>) and is isolated
        against the unanimous testimony of the other mss. Graphy of P.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Una buona quantità di errori e lacune comuni
        permette di dividere i testimoni in tre famiglie AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta, CU,
        KNP. I mss. CU si accordano in generale con KNP, e confermano la lezione di AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta solo in caso di errore di KNP. La canzone è attribuita a tre
        autori diversi dalle tre famiglie di testimoni: AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta
        l’attribuiscono al Vidame de Chartres, KMePN a Gontier de Soignies e C a Guiot de Provins.
        Le attribuzioni di C sono ritenute generalmente inaffidabili; le numerose analogie con la
        canzone RS 502, lo stile piuttosto lontano da quello abituale di Gontier de Soignies e la
        generale affidabilità dei testimoni del gruppo s<hi rend="superscript">I</hi> fanno
        preferire l’attribuzione al Vidame de Chartres (si veda Formisano 1980, p. xxxvi). In una
        situazione in cui ci si trova spesso a scegliere tra due alternative equivalenti, i mss. CU
        sembrano avere una lezione eccessivamente autonoma e in AMR<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Ta
        manca una strofa; perciò si sceglie in questo caso di seguire la lezione di KNP, ben sapendo
        che in altri casi essa si dimostra poco affidabile. La scelta è facilitata dal fatto che le
        varianti sono minime e in generale non modificano il senso del testo. Ci si distacca da KNP
        solo per integrare i vv. 27-29 che mancano parzialmente a questi testimoni (si ricorre alla
        lezione di CU) e la sillaba finale del v. 31, per sanare l’ipermetria dei vv. 24 (<hi rend="italic">celui</hi> per <hi rend="italic">cil</hi>) e 34 (<hi rend="italic">ne
          ne</hi> iniziale); infine ai vv. 38-39 la lezione di KNP sembra erronea (in particolare il
        possessivo <hi rend="italic">s’amor</hi>) ed è isolata contro la testimonianza compatta
        degli altri manoscritti. La grafia è quella di P.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2015-12-09T18:44:43Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Vidame de Chartres</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.421.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>However long I have stayed outside my sweet country and endured many great
              tribulations in an unhappy (accursed?) land, I have not forgotten the sweet pain which
              pleases me so well, from which I do not wish to be cured, so much have I loved the
              pain. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>I have always been in pain and wept many a tear; the finest summer’s day or year
              seemed to me to be rain or ice, since I was forced to stay in the land I hate the
              most: I shall never have joy in my lifetime if it is not given to me in France. </p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>So God grant me joy and health, and may the fairest lady in the world comfort me with
              her beauty which has so entered my heart; and if I die in this thought, I truly
              believe my soul will be saved; God, if only the one who married her would lend me his
              place!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Alas, I am too unhappy if the one to whom I have dedicated myself, to the point where
              I cannot extricate myself, does not heed my prayer; I have concealed myself too long
              because of those slanderous people who will never have their hearts weary of speaking
              ill behind one’s back.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Ah, sweet creature, do not kill me, and do not be cruel or haughty towards me who
              love you more than ever with loyal and sincere love; and if you kill me nevertheless,
              alas, I shall pay too high a price for the love which will oppress me so; but now it
              is sweet and light to me.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.421.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Per quanto abbia soggiornato fuori dal mio dolce paese e sopportato molte grandi
              tribolazioni in una terra sventurata [maledetta?], per questo non ho dimenticato il
              dolce male che tanto mi piace, dal quale non voglio guarire tanto (ne) ho amato il
              dolore.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Sono sempre stato in pena e ho pianto molte lacrime; il più bel giorno d’estate mi
              sembrava pioggia o gelo, dal momento che mi toccava soggiornare nel paese che odio di
              più: non avrò mai gioia in vita mia se non mi viene data in Francia.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Perciò Dio mi dia gioia e sollievo, e la più bella creatura del mondo mi conforti con
              la sua bellezza che mi è a tal punto entrata nel cuore; e se muoio con questo
              pensiero, credo proprio che la mia anima sarà salva; Dio, se solo colui che l’ha
              sposata volesse cedermi il suo posto!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Ahimè, sono troppo infelice se colei alla quale mi sono votato, al punto che non
              posso più tirarmi indietro, non ascolta la mia preghiera; mi sono nascosto troppo a
              lungo a causa di quella gente maldicente che non avrà mai il cuore stanco di sparlare
              alle spalle.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Ah, dolce creatura, non uccidetemi, e non siate crudele né altera verso di me che vi
              amo più che mai d’amore leale e sincero; e se voi tuttavia mi uccidete, ahimè, pagherò
              troppo caro l’amore che a tal punto mi opprimerà; ma ora mi è dolce e leggero.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
