<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-02-24</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Paris 1833, 113; Lacour 1856, 37; Ulrich 1889-1895, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>
            147; Brakelmann 1896, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 34; Noonan 1933, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 196; Petersen Dyggve 1945, 34.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Paris 1833, 113; Lacour 1856, 37; Ulrich 1889-1895, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>
            147; Brakelmann 1896, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 34; Noonan 1933, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 196; Petersen Dyggve 1945, 34.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(9+1).</hi> A 159a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), K 181b (<hi rend="italic">li Visdame de Chartres</hi>), M 8a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de
              Ch[...]</hi>), Me 85v? (incipit only, <hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), N 86c
              (<hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), P 71a (<hi rend="italic">Robert de
              Blois</hi>), T 106v (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), U 22v (anonymous), X 129d (<hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), a 21v (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de
              Cartres</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">(9+1).</hi> A 159a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), K 181b (<hi rend="italic">li Visdame de Chartres</hi>), M 8a (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de
              Ch[...]</hi>), Me 85v? (solo incipit, <hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), N 86c
              (<hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), P 71a (<hi rend="italic">Robert de
              Blois</hi>), T 106v (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame</hi>), U 22v (anonima), X 129d (<hi rend="italic">Robert de Blois</hi>), a 21v (<hi rend="italic">li Vidame de
              Cartres</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;">
        <p>10a’ba’ba’ba’ (MW 674,5 = Frank 224); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rhyme
          a: <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rhyme b: <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>; the stanzas are <hi rend="italic">capcaudadas</hi>, as the rhyme <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi> is found at the
          end and the begining of each stanza; frequent identical rhymes, to the extent that one
          could speak of <hi rend="italic">coblas retronchadas</hi>, even if the repetitions do not
          fall systematically in the same position of each stanza (<hi rend="italic">venir</hi> vv.
          2 and 18; <hi rend="italic">demoree</hi> vv. 5 and 14; <hi rend="italic">desir</hi> vv. 6,
          13 and 23, but the second case is a noun whereas in the other cases it is a verb; <hi rend="italic">nee</hi> vv. 7, 10 and 22 (in this case also the last occurrence is a
          noun); <hi rend="italic">agree</hi> vv. 15 and 24; <hi rend="italic">pensee</hi> vv. 19
          and 29); paronymous and derivative rhyme vv. 2, 9, 18 (<hi rend="italic">venir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">revenir</hi>), 4 and 16 (<hi rend="italic">reveïr</hi>, <hi rend="italic">veïr</hi>) and vv. 11, 20, 32, 34 (<hi rend="italic">retenir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">atenir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tenir</hi>); paronymous only in vv. 3, 7, 8, 10, 22 (<hi rend="italic">senee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">nee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">retornee</hi>);
          rich and leonine rhymes are also very frequent; lyric caesura vv. 7, 20 and 30; feminine
          caesura with elision v. 6; Italian-style accentual caesura 4’+5’ or else decasyllable 6+4
          v. 1 (v. 13 is also, definitely, 6+4); melody in all mss., with A’s individual; melodic
          structure ABAB CDE (T 291).</p>
      </metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’ba’ba’ (MW 674,5 = Frank
        224); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rima a: <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima
        b: <hi rend="italic">-ir</hi>; le strofe sono <hi rend="italic">capcaudadas</hi>, poiché la
        rima <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi> si trova alla fine e all’inizio di ogni strofa; frequenti
        rime identiche, tanto che si potrebbe parlare di <hi rend="italic">coblas retronchadas</hi>,
        anche se le ripetizioni non avvengono sistematicamente nella stessa posizione delle strofe
          (<hi rend="italic">venir</hi> vv. 2 e 18; <hi rend="italic">demoree</hi> vv. 5 e 14; <hi rend="italic">desir</hi> vv. 6, 13 e 23, ma il secondo caso è un sostantivo mentre negli
        altri casi si tratta di un verbo; <hi rend="italic">nee</hi> vv. 7, 10 e 22 (anche in questo
        caso l’ultima occorrenza è un sostantivo); <hi rend="italic">agree</hi> vv. 15 e 24; <hi rend="italic">pensee</hi> vv. 19 e 29); rima paronima e derivativa ai vv. 2, 9, 18 (<hi rend="italic">venir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">revenir</hi>), 4 e 16 (<hi rend="italic">reveïr</hi>, <hi rend="italic">veïr</hi>) e ai vv. 11, 20, 32, 34 (<hi rend="italic">retenir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">atenir</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tenir</hi>); solo paronima
        tra i vv. 3, 7, 8, 10, 22 (<hi rend="italic">senee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">nee</hi>, <hi rend="italic">retornee</hi>); molto frequenti anche le rime ricche e leonine; cesura
        lirica ai vv. 7, 20 e 30; cesura femminile con elisione al v. 6; cesura accentuale
        all’italiana 4’+5’ oppure decasillabo 6+4 al v. 1 (certamente 6+4 è anche il v. 13); melodia
        in tutti i testimoni, indipendente quella di A; schema melodico ABAB CDE (T 291).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>As is often the case common errors are scarce,
        but the usual opposition between the families AMTa and KNPX is constant. In M the text is
        lacunary because of the removal of a vignette and only vv. 1-3 and 20-33 remain. U’s text is
        highly individual: the first four lines of the first three stanzas are in the same position
        as in the other mss., while the last lines of the stanza are displaced according to the
        following order: 1-4+26-28, 8-11+5-7, 15-18+12-14. Hence vv. 19-25 and 29-35 are missing and
        in their place the copyist has added a fourth stanza and a sort of <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> of five lines, both independent of the rest of the tradition. In the tradition
        of this text the variants are few and of little relevance. In the case of minor differences
        between AMTa and KNPX the reading confirmed by U is chosen (vv. 2, 11, 12, 16), even if in
        the trouvère tradition there are a few traces of a possible common model of U and KNPX.
        Where U is absent or has an individual reading (vv. 3, 13, 20, 23, 33, 35) decisions are
        made on a case by case basis, what appears to be the best reading being chosen. In all these
        cases the reading of A(M)Ta seems <hi rend="italic">difficilior</hi>, except in v. 23 where
        the variants of Aa and MT are probably erroneous. The graphy is that of P. The attribution
        to the Vidame de Chartres, unanimous in AMTa, is also confirmed by K, but see also the
        notable affinities with the song RS 421.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>Come spesso avviene scarseggiano gli errori
        congiuntivi, ma la consueta opposizione tra le famiglie AMTa e KNPX è costante. In M il
        testo è lacunoso a causa dell’ablazione di una vignetta e ne restano solo i vv. 1-3 e 20-33.
        Il testo di U è molto particolare: i primi quattro versi delle prime tre strofe restano
        nella stessa posizione degli altri testimoni, mentre gli ultimi versi delle strofe vengono
        spostati secondo la seguente successione: 1-4+26-28, 8-11+5-7, 15-18+12-14. Mancano di
        conseguenza i vv. 19-25 e 29-35 al posto dei quali il copista aggiunge una quarta strofa e
        una sorta di congedo di cinque versi entrambi indipendenti dal resto della tradizione. Nella
        tradizione di questo testo le varianti sono poche e di scarsa rilevanza. In caso di
        opposizione adiafora tra AMTa e KNPX si sceglie la lezione confermata da U (vv. 2, 11, 12,
        16), anche se nella tradizione dei trovieri si trova qualche traccia di un possibile modello
        comune a U e KNPX. Laddove U non è presente o ha una lezione autonoma (vv. 3, 13, 20, 23,
        33, 35) si decide di volta in volta accogliendo la lezione che sembra migliore. In tutti
        questi casi la lezione di A(M)Ta sembra <hi rend="italic">difficilior</hi>, tranne al v. 23
        dove le varianti di Aa e MT sono probabilmente erronee. La grafia è quella di P.
        L’attribuzione al Vidame de Chartres, compatta in AMTa, è confermata anche da K, ma si
        vedano anche le notevoli affinità con la canzone RS 421.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-03-13T09:36:03Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Vidame de Chartres</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.502.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>For as long as I remained away from my own country I was destined not to have joy, as
              when I thought of the lovely, wise lady it seemed to me I should not see her again. I
              made a long sojourn far from her in a land where I did not wish to be: I would have
              rather (been) in the land of her birth.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>I was happy when I saw that I should be returning from Blois and I was certain that I
              would return to the most beautiful creature ever born, to whom I belong, should she be
              willing to retain me; I pray her, for the sake of God who has so greatly honoured her
              that whoever sees her lives in desire, that she have mercy on me without delay.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Now I am in the land where lives the one that pleases me, but I cannot see her as I
              wish, because I am so afraid of the cruel snoopers that I dare not move. I would
              rather have painful thoughts about her than obtain the greatest favours from anothers
              much do I love her sweet reputation.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Nevertheless may God grant me joy and pleasure from the loveliest creature, just as I
              desire it, since nothing delights me but her love, so much has she drawn me to her
              most sweet pleasure. Oh God, will it ever happen that I hold her secretly in my arms,
              both of us naked, at our leisure? Yes, if Love wishes me to live.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Lady, on whose account I have such glad thoughts that no other joy can compare with
              them, no-one who has seen and gazed upon you can refrain from your praise, for in you
              kindness is joined to beauty; so I must consider myself most fortunate and privileged,
              since I have fallen in love with beauty and kindness.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.502.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Finché fossi rimasto fuori dal mio paese sarei stato destinato a non avere gioia,
              perché quando pensavo alla bella assennata ero convinto che non l’avrei rivista. Ho
              fatto un lungo soggiorno lontano da lei in una terra dove non desideravo essere: avrei
              preferito (essere) là dove lei è nata.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Sono stato felice quando ho visto che sarei ripartito da Blois e ho avuto la certezza
              che sarei tornato dalla più bella creatura che sia mai nata, alla quale appartengo, se
              lei mi vuole accogliere; la prego per Dio, che l’ha tanto onorata che chiunque la veda
              vive nel desiderio, che abbia pietà di me senza indugio.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Ora sono nel paese dov’è colei che mi piace, ma non posso vederla a mio agio, perché
              ho tanta paura della gente crudele e indiscreta che non oso andare e venire.
              Preferisco avere da lei gravi preoccupazioni che ottenere i più grandi favori da
              un’altra, tanto amo la sua dolce reputazione.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>Dio mi conceda gioia e piacere dalla bellissima creatura, così come desidero, perché
              niente mi appaga se non il suo amore, a tal punto mi ha conquistato al suo dolcissimo
              piacere. Dio, accadrà mai che la tenga di nascosto tra le mie braccia, entrambi nudi,
              a mio piacimento? Sì, se Amore vuole che io resista (resti in vita).</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Signora, verso la quale nutro pensieri così belli che nessun’altra gioia vi si può
              comparare, nessuno che vi abbia vista e contemplata potrebbe trattenersi dal lodarvi,
              perché in voi alla bellezza è sommata la bontà; per cui devo ritenermi fortunato e
              privilegiato, dal momento che mi sono innamorato della bellezza e della bontà.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
