<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2014-10-05</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>La Ravallière 1742, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 132; Leroux de Lincy 1841, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 125; Tarbé 1850, 124; Meyer 1877, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 370; Clédat 1892, 223; Bartsch-Horning 1895, 384; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 169; Riemann 1909-1910, 575; Wallensköld 1925, 183; Wagner 1949, 158; Pauphilet 1952, 898; Cremonesi 1955, 200; Gennrich 1955, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 9; Toja 1966, 421; Mary 1967, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 360; Picot 1975, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 64; Baumgartner 1983, 252; Brahney 1989, 226; Guida 1992, 106; Rosenberg-Tischler 1995, 360; Dijkstra 1995a, 204; Sánchez Palomino 2005, 172.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>La Ravallière 1742, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 132; Leroux de Lincy 1841, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 125; Tarbé 1850, 124; Meyer 1877, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 370; Clédat 1892, 223; Bartsch-Horning 1895, 384; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 169; Riemann 1909-1910, 575; Wallensköld 1925, 183; Wagner 1949, 158; Pauphilet 1952, 898; Cremonesi 1955, 200; Gennrich 1955, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 9; Toja 1966, 421; Mary 1967, <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi> 360; Picot 1975, <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi> 64; Baumgartner 1983, 252; Brahney 1989, 226; Guida 1992, 106; Rosenberg-Tischler 1995, 360; Dijkstra 1995a, 204; Sánchez Palomino 2005, 172.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(8). K 1b-2b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 13cd (anonima), N 1c-2a (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), O 127bc (anon.), S 316bc (anon.), T 2v (anon.), V 1cd (anon.), X 8cd (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>).</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(8). K 1b-2b (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 13cd (anonima), N 1c-2a (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>), O 127bc (anon.), S 316bc (anon.), T 2v (anon.), V 1cd (anon.), X 8cd (<hi rend="italic">li rois de Navarre</hi>).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababc’c’b (MW 1159,1 = Frank 361); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) with a 3-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> (c’c’b); rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ez</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ont</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; rhyme c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; identica; rhyme <hi rend="italic">mont</hi> in vv. 16 and 22; feminine caesura with elision in vv. 2 and 11; lyric caesura in vv. 29 and 36; melody in KM<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>NOVX, with very few variants (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 3; Tischler 1997, I n° 5).</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10ababc’c’b (MW 1159,1 = Frank 361); 5 <hi rend="italic">coblas doblas</hi> (2+2+1) con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 3 versi (c’c’b); rima a = <hi rend="italic">-a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ez</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-is</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ont</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-oir</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-ance</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima identica <hi rend="italic">mont</hi> ai vv. 16 e 22; cesura femminile con elisione ai vv. 2 e 11; cesura lirica ai vv. 29 e 36; melodia in KM<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>NOVX, con pochissime varianti (van der Werf 1979, II, p. 3; Tischler 1997, I n° 5).</p></metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The tradition of the text is very compact, with few variants and little stemmatic significance. All the songbooks transmitting the text are witnesses of Thibaut’s Liederbuch, with the sole exception of S which in this case distinguishes itself more by visibly sloppy readings than by difficiliores variants. In Mt, T and V the song forms part of Thibaut de Champagne’s corpus; in O, where the texts are ordered alphabetically, it is the first text under the letter <hi rend="italic">S</hi>, a position traditionally reserved for Thibaut, followed by two other texts; in S it is found in the centre of a series of some thirty songs attributable to the king of Navarre. The attribution can therefore be considered unanimous.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>La tradizione del testo è molto compatta, con poche varianti e di scarso rilievo stemmatico. Tutti i canzonieri che riportano il testo di questa canzone sono testimoni del <hi rend="italic">Liederbuch</hi> di Thibaut, ad eccezione del solo S che però in questo caso si distingue più per qualche lezione platealmente trasandata che per varianti <hi rend="italic">difficiliores</hi>. In M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, T e V la canzone fa parte del corpus di Thibaut de Champagne; in O, nel quale i testi sono ordinati alfabeticamente, si tratta del primo testo della lettera <hi rend="italic">S</hi>, posto tradizionalmente riservato a Thibaut, del quale seguono altri due testi; in S si trova al centro di una serie di una trentina di canzoni attribuibili al re di Navarra. L’attribuzione può quindi essere considerata unanime.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2014-10-05T18:14:12Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main"/><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.6.en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Lords, know this: whoever will not now go to that land where God died and rose again, and whoever will not take the cross to Outremer will find it hard ever to go to heaven. Whoever has pity and good remembrance in his heart must seek to avenge the Highest Lord and liberate His land and His country.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>All the base men who do not love God, goodness or honour or reputation, will remain here; and each says: “What will my wife do?”, “There is no way I would leave my friends”. These are embroiled in vain preoccupations, since there is certainly no true friend apart from the one who was placed upon the true cross for us. </p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Soon those valiant young men who love God and the honour of this world, who wisely wish to proceed towards God, will set out on their way; and the snotty-nosed faint-hearts and the lechers will stay behind: they are blind, I have no doubt about it. Whoever does not aid God at least once in his lifetime, and at so little cost, loses the glory of the world. </p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>God allowed himself to suffer pain upon the cross and will say to us on the day when all come together [come before Him?]: “You who helped me carry my cross, you will go to where my angels are; and you from whom I had no help will all descend into the depths of hell”.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>Each imagines he can live without a care in the world and that he will never have anything to worry about; the Enemy and sin have such a hold on them that they have no discernment, will [? see LB’s note, tho’ the text has <hi rend="italic">hardement</hi> not <hi rend="italic">volonté</hi>] or energy. Good Lord God, take this illusion away from them and place us in your realm in such a holy way that we may see Your face [ending in ‘You’ seems too abrupt I think].</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.6.it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Signori, sappiatelo, chi ora non andrà in quella terra dove Dio fu messo a morte e resuscitò e chi non prenderà la croce d’oltremare difficilmente potrà mai andare in paradiso. Chi ha in sé compassione e buona memoria, deve compiere la vendetta dell’Altissimo e liberare la sua terra e il suo paese.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Resteranno qui solo i vili che non amano Dio, né il bene, né l’onore, né la reputazione; essi dicono: “e mia moglie cosa farà?” “non lascerò per nessuna ragione i miei amici”. Sono invischiati in vane preoccupazioni, poiché non c’è vero amico al di fuori di Colui, certamente, che per noi fu posto sulla vera croce.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Presto partiranno i giovani valorosi che amano Dio e l’onore del mondo, che saggiamente vogliono andare verso Dio; e i pavidi e i debosciati resteranno: sono ciechi, non ho alcun dubbio. Chi non soccorre Dio neppure una volta nella vita, per così poco perde la gloria del mondo.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Dio si lasciò martoriare sulla croce per noi e ci dirà nel giorno in cui tutti saranno radunati: “voi che m’avete aiutato a portare la croce, voi andrete là dove sono i miei angeli: là vedrete me e mia madre Maria; e voi dai quali non ho mai ricevuto aiuto scenderete tutti nell’inferno profondo”.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>Ognuno si illude di poter vivere sempre spensierato e pensa che non avrà mai preoccupazioni; il Nemico e il peccato li possiedono a tal punto che non hanno discernimento, né audacia, né energia. Buon Signore Dio, togliete loro questa illusione e mettete noi nel vostro regno così santamente che vi possiamo vedere.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Dolce Signora, regina incoronata, pregate per noi, Vergine beata, e così non ci capiterà nulla di male.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
