<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2016-03-05</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Huet 1912, p. 29; Vaillant 1913,<hi rend="exldetailsdisplayval"> </hi>p. 28; Raugei
            1981, p. 175.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Huet 1912, p. 29; Vaillant 1913,<hi rend="exldetailsdisplayval"> </hi>p. 28; Raugei
            1981, p. 175.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss</hi>.: <hi rend="bold">(2).</hi> M 88r-88v (<hi rend="italic">~Me s(ire) Gautiers dargies</hi>), T 143r (<hi rend="italic">Me sire gautiers
              dargies</hi>).</bibl>
          <bibl> [@type=manuscripts,@xml:lang=it]</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss</hi>.: <hi rend="bold">(2).</hi> M 88r-88v (<hi rend="italic">~Me s(ire) Gautiers dargies</hi>), T 143r (<hi rend="italic">Me sire gautiers
              dargies</hi>).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>7a4b7a4b7a4b7a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a8b (MW 693,1); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas
          singulars</hi> and an 11-line <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> a4a4a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a8b; rhyme a
        = <hi rend="italic">-er, -ant, -ié, -é</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-ir, -ai, -ort,
          -ent</hi>; between stanzas III and IV the two mss. also transmit a probably interpolated
        stanza distinguished by the alternation of m. and f. rhymes (rhyme a’ = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">is</hi>). Unicum. For further details see Raugei,
        pp. 175-176. The melody is transmitted in both mss.with the structure ABCD ABCD EFGH IKG’L
        MNO (T 467).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>7a4b7a4b7a4b7a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a8b (MW 693,1); 4 <hi rend="italic">coblas
          singulars</hi>, con un <hi rend="italic">envoi</hi> di 11 versi (a4a4a4b4a4a4a4b4a4a8b);
        rima a = <hi rend="italic">-er, -ant, -ié, -é</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-ir, -ai,
          -ort, -ent</hi>; tra le strofe III e IV i due manoscritti riportano una strofa
        probabilmente interpolata, caratterizzata da una rima ‘a’ femminile (rima a’ = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">is</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Unicum</hi>. Per ulteriori dettagli si veda Raugei, pp. 175-176. La melodia è trasmessa da
          entrambi i manoscritti, secondo lo schema ABCD ABCD EFGH IKG’L MNO (T 467).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>Apart from a few minor variants the two mss.
        transmit the same text, including st. IIIb, though T has an inferior (erroneous?) reading in
        v. 42 and errors in 60 and 61, as well as a lacuna from v. 17 to v. 33; a modern hand has
        filled in the missing lines from the text of M. Graphy M.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>A parte qualche minima variante i manoscritti
        riportano lo stesso testo, che include la strofa IIIb, anche se T ha una lezione deteriore
        (erronea?) al v. 42 e lezioni erronee ai vv. 60 e 61, oltra a una lacuna dal v. 17 al v. 33;
        una mano moderna ha integrato i versi mancanti secondo la lezione di M. Grafia di
        M.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2016-03-13T10:18:23Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Gautier de Dargies</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.795.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>I certainly imagined I would refrain from singing forever, but I cannot think of a
              better way to express my heart and thoughts, which are making me very angry; I am
              forced to divide and separate myself from my heart. Sweet person, fair of face, I pay
              too dearly for you; most bitter do I find the memory of your bearing, your speech,
              your playfulness, your approach; now I can weep and give myself over to sorrow; it
              will be long before I ever repent of this!</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>To come to see her candid laughing countenance – her bright face, fresh and pleasing
              – was my doom; when I looked on her, I gazed on her most sweetly, and fell in love
              with her. Now she has plunged me into great affliction; God, what shall I do! Full of
              sorrow and sore laments, deeply troubled, henceforth I shall take my distance from
              her: the most worthy lady whom I love so much with a true heart. Hereafter I shall
              find myself sleeping little and waking much.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>I have taken leave of the one who has slain me so; I had great suffering for it, but
              this was wrong. She kept me firmly underfoot, with no pleasure, and she always kept me
              away from contact with her. She did wrong to deceive me, neglected as I was, and left
              me little comfort. Now I arraign her: she has burdened me too much, and I bear a heavy
              load. I have made my preparations and my decision for, sighing, I am on my way to the
              port (the end?). </p>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <p><hi rend="italic">Sorrowfully I leave my sweet love and in great sadness. Although I
                still have life in my body, after leaving her company things are now worse for me:
                my joy has ended. It seems to me that I have in no way deserved this, but rather the
                pity I foolishly yearned for has perished; I have left it in her land, in Brie (?),
                and I go off to Syria most downcast because of her.</hi></p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>My lady, whom I have loyally loved, and for a long time, has certainly strung me
              along as she wished; she gave me many a fair look, but falsely, and I have most dearly
              paid for it. I still feel its effects: she has severely wounded and damaged me – I
              have endured this most patiently – and caused me great pain and much (love-)sickness;
              I have little help for my health; I have gone so far astray that now, be truly aware
              of this, my torments are all doubled.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>I have long remained loyal, but have gained so little; I found humiliation. I tell
              the truth: unless I lie, she has rewarded me to her liking. So a man who expects his
              just deserts is a fool.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.795.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Ho pensato seriamente di smettere di cantare per sempre, ma non riesco a immaginare
              un modo migliore per esprimere il mio stato d’animo e il mio pensiero, che mi esaspera
              oltremodo; sono costretto a separarmi dal mio cuore e abbandonarlo. Bella persona,
              viso grazioso, pago un prezzo troppo alto per voi; trovo particolarmente amaro il
              ricordo del vostro portamento, delle vostre parole, della vostra allegria, del vostro
              appressarvi; ora posso (solo) piangere e lasciarmi sopraffare dal dolore; sarà troppo
              tardi quando me ne pentirò.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Vedere il suo volto candido e sorridente, il suo viso luminoso, fresco e piacevole, è
              stata la mia rovina; quando la guardai, l’osservai con tenerezza, e mi innamorai di
              lei. Ora mi ha gettato in un grande sconforto; Dio, che farò? Pieno di tristezza e di
              grande dolore, profondamente turbato, d’ora in poi l’eviterò: la donna più nobile, che
              amo così tanto di vero cuore. Oramai mi toccherà dormire poco e vegliare molto.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="stanza">
            <p>Ho detto addio a colei che mi ha ucciso in questo modo; ne ho sofferto molto, e ho
              fatto male. Mi ha tenuto saldamente sotto i piedi, privo di piacere, e mi ha sempre
              escluso dalla sua considerazione. Si è comportata male quando, dopo avermi trascurato,
              mi ha ingannato e mi ha concesso ben poco conforto. Ora io l’accuso: mi ha troppo
              oppresso, e ne porto un grande peso. Ho procurato e deciso di incamminarmi sospirando
              verso il porto (la fine?).</p>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="stanza">
            <p><hi rend="italic">Dolente e molto triste lascio il mio dolce amore. Anche se ho
                (ancora) vita in corpo, dopo aver lasciato la sua compagnia tutto va male: la mia
                gioia è finita. Mi sembra di non avere in alcun modo meritato questo, ma è morta per
                me la pietà che ho vanamente agognato; l’ho lasciata nella sua terra, a Brie (?), e
                me ne vado molto afflitto a causa sua.</hi></p>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="stanza">
            <p>La mia signora, che ho amato fedelmente e a lungo, si è davvero presa gioco di me; mi
              ha illuso mostrandosi falsamente ben disposta, e l’ho pagato a caro prezzo. Ne sento
              ancora gli effetti: mi ha molto tormentato e prostrato – e l’ho sopportato
              pazientemente – e mi ha molto angustiato e fatto soffrire; ma per la mia salute ho
              poco giovamento; ho tanto vagato a vuoto, sappiatelo bene, che ora tutti i miei
              tormenti sono raddoppiati.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="stanza">
            <p>Sono rimasto fedele a lungo, e ne ho guadagnato così poco; vi ho trovato (solo)
              commiserazione. Dico la verità: se non mi sbaglio, mi ha ripagato a suo capriccio. È
              folle chi si aspetta la loro riconoscenza.</p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
