<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2015-08-25</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>de la Borde 1780, II, 270; Crapelet 1829, 132; Michel 1830, 33; Brakelmann
            1870-1891, 114; Fath 1883, 54; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 87; Bartsch 1920, 164; Ullsperger
            1935, 61; Delbouille 1936, 227; Brittain 1937, 140; Pauphilet 1952, 875; Spaziani 1954,
            33; Cremonesi 1955, 107; Lerond 1964, 76; Toja 1966, 229; Cluzel 1969, 113; van der Werf
            1977-1979, 243; Alvar 1982, 256; Baumgartner 1983, 240; Bergner 1983, 458; Dufournet
            1989, 114; Rosenberg-Tischler 1995, 388; Gaullier-Bougassas 2009, 516 (for the romances
            containing quotations, references are given only to the editions of the <hi rend="italic">Roman du Châtelain de Coucy</hi>, and not to <hi rend="italic">Guillaume
              de Dole</hi>, for which the single ms. has been consulted directly).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>de la Borde 1780, II, 270; Crapelet 1829, 132; Michel 1830, 33; Brakelmann
            1870-1891, 114; Fath 1883, 54; Bédier-Aubry 1909, 87; Bartsch 1920, 164; Ullsperger
            1935, 61; Delbouille 1936, 227; Brittain 1937, 140; Pauphilet 1952, 875; Spaziani 1954,
            33; Cremonesi 1955, 107; Lerond 1964, 76; Toja 1966, 229; Cluzel 1969, 113; van der Werf
            1977-1979, 243; Alvar 1982, 256; Baumgartner 1983, 240; Bergner 1983, 458; Dufournet
            1989, 114; Rosenberg-Tischler 1995, 388; Gaullier-Bougassas 2009, 516 (per quanto
            riguarda i romanzi a citazioni, si danno solo i riferimenti alle edizioni del <hi rend="italic">Roman du Châtelain de Coucy</hi>, ma non a quelle del <hi rend="italic">Guillaume de Dole</hi>, di cui si è consultato direttamente il manoscritto
            unico).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss</hi>. <hi rend="bold">(13+3)</hi>: A 155a (<hi rend="italic">li
              Kastelains de Chouci</hi>), C 125v (<hi rend="italic">Muse an Borse</hi>), K 95b (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains de Couci</hi>), L 62v (anonymous), M 53c (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains de Couci</hi>), O 73c (anon.), P 30c (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains de Conci</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 129v (anon.), T 155v
              (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains</hi>), U 38r (anon.), V 75b (anon.), X 69a (<hi rend="italic">Li Chastelains de Couci</hi>), a 13v (<hi rend="italic">li
              Castelains</hi>), u 73b (vv. 1-8 = <hi rend="italic">Guillaume de Dole</hi> vv.
            922-929); <hi rend="italic">Roman du Châtelain de Coucy et de la Dame de Fayel</hi> vv.
            7005-7011 (vv. 1-8, 2 mss.).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Mss. (13+3)</hi>: A 155a (<hi rend="italic">li Kastelains de
              Chouci</hi>), C 125v (<hi rend="italic">Muse an Borse</hi>), K 95b (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains de Couci</hi>), L 62v (anonima), M 53c (<hi rend="italic">li
              Chastelains de Couci</hi>), O 73c (anon.), P 30c (<hi rend="italic">li Chastelains de
              Conci</hi>), R<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 129v (anon.), T 155v (<hi rend="italic">li
              Chastelains</hi>), U 38r (anon.), V 75b (anon.), X 69a (<hi rend="italic">Li
              Chastelains de Couci</hi>), a 13v (<hi rend="italic">li Castelains</hi>), u 73b (vv.
            1-8 = <hi rend="italic">Guillaume de Dole</hi> vv. 922-929); <hi rend="italic">Roman du
              Châtelain de Coucy et de la Dame de Fayel</hi> vv. 7005-7011 (vv. 1-8, 2 mss.).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bbba’6b (MW 966,4 = Frank
        312); 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi> “incatenate”; rima a: <hi rend="italic">-ete</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima b: <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; la <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> RS 757 di Thibaut de
        Champagne si serve di uno schema molto simile e quasi speculare; rima derivativa ai vv. 15 e
        27 (<hi rend="italic">pramete-entremete</hi>); ‘annominatio per immutationem’ ai vv. 9 e 11
          (<hi rend="italic">doucete-boucete</hi>); rima grammaticale ai vv. 17-29 (<hi rend="italic">regardee-garder</hi>) e 19-30 (<hi rend="italic">plouree-plourer</hi>); rima
        equivoca tra i vv. 18 e 21-40 (<hi rend="italic">non</hi>, ma identica tra i vv. 21-40 dove
        tutta la locuzione finale è molto simile), 44-48 (<hi rend="italic">pardon</hi>); rima
        equivoca all’orecchio tra i vv. 20-42 (<hi rend="italic">hom-on</hi>), 34-38-46 (<hi rend="italic">dont-don</hi>, ma identica tra i vv. 38-46); numerose rime paronime in <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; vi è cesura lirica al v. 43 e cesura femminile con elisione al v.
        33; il testo presenta tre linee melodiche diverse: una nel ms. R, una in V e la terza in
        AKLMOPTUXa, con numerose varianti; schema melodico ABAB CDEF (T 577,1).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’ba’bbba’6b (MW 966,4 = Frank
        312); 6 <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi> “incatenate”; rima a: <hi rend="italic">-ete</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-ee</hi>; rima b: <hi rend="italic">-er</hi>, <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; la <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> RS 757 di Thibaut de
        Champagne si serve di uno schema molto simile e quasi speculare; rima derivativa ai vv. 15 e
        27 (<hi rend="italic">pramete-entremete</hi>); ‘annominatio per immutationem’ ai vv. 9 e 11
          (<hi rend="italic">doucete-boucete</hi>); rima grammaticale ai vv. 17-29 (<hi rend="italic">regardee-garder</hi>) e 19-30 (<hi rend="italic">plouree-plourer</hi>); rima
        equivoca tra i vv. 18 e 21-40 (<hi rend="italic">non</hi>, ma identica tra i vv. 21-40 dove
        tutta la locuzione finale è molto simile), 44-48 (<hi rend="italic">pardon</hi>); rima
        equivoca all’orecchio tra i vv. 20-42 (<hi rend="italic">hom-on</hi>), 34-38-46 (<hi rend="italic">dont-don</hi>, ma identica tra i vv. 38-46); numerose rime paronime in <hi rend="italic">-on</hi>; vi è cesura lirica al v. 43 e cesura femminile con elisione al v.
        33; il testo presenta tre linee melodiche diverse: una nel ms. R, una in V e la terza in
        AKLMOPTUXa, con numerose varianti; schema melodico ABAB CDEF (T 577,1).</p></metDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The number and order of stanzas fairly clearly
        show the division AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta–KLPVX–CU, but the usual paucity of
        errors and the particularly high incidence of contamination make it impossible to clarify
        further the relations between the mss. and to use the stemma systematically to reconstruct
        the text. A few common errors occur only in KLPVX, in vv. 25-27 (the rhyme is modified and
        hence the metrical shape of the stanza is distorted), 34 (the reading <hi rend="italic">vit</hi> seems a corrupt form of Aa’s <hi rend="italic">vient</hi>) and 37). Collation
        therefore gives rise to the identification of three different “editions” rather than a
        collection of explicable variants of the same text. Tripartite readings which seem to
        confirm the existence of the three families are found in vv. 11 and 27-28. Mss. OR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> e CU appear particularly contaminated, and in some cases divide
        to follow the readings of different families (vv. 3, 5 and 10); but even M sometimes acts
        autonomously and includes readings from other families, in vv. 26, 30 and 36 for example.
        The particular situation of the manuscript tradition makes it impossible to produce a truly
        critical edition and requires an edition based on the reading of a version of one of the
        manuscript groups. That of AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta has been chosen, not only
        because it is the only complete one, but also because it presents several better readings.
        This choice also necessarily implies the acceptance of the particular stanzaic structure
        defined here as “interlaced” <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi>, though some doubt about
        its authenticity remains: the rhymes of stanzas I and II are picked up in stanza IV, while
        the rhymes of stanzas V and VI are anticipated in stanza III. This case is unique in Old
        French lyric which inevitably gives rise to some uncertainty. In cases of a threefold
        division the reading of AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta is always adopted, as in a
        twofold division if the group is in essential agreement (vv. 3 and 5), even when all the
        other mss. agree on the same reading (vv. 14, 26, 30). If mss. AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta are virtually uniform, decisions are made one by one on the basis of the value
        of the different readings, taking account of the other witnesses. T, which shows some
        northern characteristics, has been chosen as base. As far as the attribution is concerned,
        only ms. C, notoriously unreliable, offers a different one; in L, O and V the text is
        integrated into the section devoted to the Châtelain de Coucy.</p></editorialDecl>
      <editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>La tradizione manoscritta di questa canzone
        delinea abbastanza nettamente tre famiglie AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta, KLPVX, CU,
        già a partire dal numero e dall’ordine delle strofe; ma l’abituale scarsità di errori e
        l’incidenza particolarmente importante della contaminazione rendono impossibile approfondire
        ulteriormente i rapporti tra i testimoni e servirsi in modo sistematico dello stemma per la
        ricostruzione del testo. Alcuni errori comuni sono reperibili solo per la famiglia KLPVX ai
        vv. 25-27 (viene modificata la rima e perciò alterato lo schema metrico della strofa), 34
        (la lezione <hi rend="italic">vit</hi> sembra una forma corrotta di <hi rend="italic">vient</hi> di Aa) e 37. La collazione dà quindi luogo all’identificazione di tre
        “redazioni” diverse più che di un insieme di varianti razionalizzabili dello stesso testo.
        Lezioni tripartite che sembrano confermare l’esistenza delle tre famiglie si trovano ai vv.
        11 e 27-28. Risultano particolarmente contaminati i mss. OR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> e
        CU, che in alcuni casi si separano per seguire lezioni di famiglie diverse (vv. 3, 5 e 10);
        ma anche M si comporta a volte in modo autonomo e accoglie le lezioni di altre famiglie per
        esempio ai vv. 26, 30 e 36. La situazione particolare della tradizione manoscritta non
        permette di procedere a una vera e propria edizione critica, obbligandoci a proporre la
        lezione di una delle “redazioni” del testo. Si è scelta quella di AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta non solo perché è l’unica completa, ma anche perché presenta in diverse
        occasioni la lezione migliore. La scelta di riprodurre l’edizione di AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta implica necessariamente anche l’accettazione della particolare
        struttura strofica che abbiamo definito a <hi rend="italic">coblas ternas</hi> “incatenate”,
        pur permanendo qualche dubbio circa la sua autenticità: le rime delle strofe i e ii vengono
        infatti riprese nella strofa iv, mentre le rime delle strofe v e vi sono anticipate nella
        strofa iii. Si tratta di un caso unico nella lirica francese che suscita inevitabilmente
        qualche perplessità. In caso di lezione tripartita si sceglie sempre la lezione di AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta, così come nelle opposizioni bipartite se il gruppo resta
        compatto (vv. 3 e 5), anche quando tutti gli altri testimoni si accordano sulla medesima
        lezione (vv. 14, 26, 30). Se i mss. AMOR<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Ta non sono compatti,
        si decide di volta in volta sulla base del valore delle lezioni alternative, anche tenendo
        conto della testimonianza degli altri canzonieri. Si è scelta come base la lezione del ms.
        T, la cui grafia mostra qualche caratteristica settentrionale. Per quanto riguarda
        l’attribuzione, solo il ms. C, notoriamente poco affidabile, ne propone una diversa; in L, O
        e V il testo è integrato nella sezione dedicata al Castellano di Coucy.</p></editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2015-08-30T15:22:02Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Châtelain de Coucy</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="text" xml:id="rs.985.fro" xml:lang="fro">
          <lg n="1" type="stanza">
            <l n="1">Li noveaus tans et mais et vïolete</l>
            <l n="2">et roussignols me semont de chanter,</l>
            <l n="3">et mes fins cuers me fait d’une amourete</l>
            <l n="4"> si douç present ke ne l’os refuser;</l>
            <l n="5">or me laist Diex en tel honor monter</l>
            <l n="6">ke cele ou j’ai mon cuer et mon penser</l>
            <l n="7">tiegne une fois entre mes bras nuete</l>
            <l n="8">ains keˇaille outremer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2" type="stanza">
            <l n="9">Au comenchier la trovai si doucete</l>
            <l n="10">ne ne quidai pour li mal endurer,</l>
            <l n="11">mais ses dols vis et sa belle boucete</l>
            <l n="12">et si bel oel vair et riant et cler</l>
            <l n="13">m’orent ains pris ke m’osaisse doner;</l>
            <l n="14">mais s’or me vieut retenir et cuiter,</l>
            <l n="15">miex aim a li faillir, si me pramete,</l>
            <l n="16">k’a une autre achiever.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="3" type="stanza">
            <l n="17">Las! pour quoi l’ai de mes iex regardee,</l>
            <l n="18">la douce riens ki Fausse Amie a non?</l>
            <l n="19">Ele me rit et je l’ai tant plouree:</l>
            <l n="20">si docement ne fu traïs nus hom.</l>
            <l n="21">Tant com fui miex, ne me fist se bien non,</l>
            <l n="22">mais or sui siens si m’ochist sans raison;</l>
            <l n="23">et pour itant ke de cuer l’ai amee,</l>
            <l n="24">n’i set autre ocoison.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="4" type="stanza">
            <l n="25">De mil sospirs ke je li doi par dete</l>
            <l n="26">ne me velt pas d’un tot seul aquiter,</l>
            <l n="27">ne Fause Amor ne laist ke s’entremete</l>
            <l n="28">ne ne mi laist dormir ne reposer.</l>
            <l n="29">S’ele m’ochist, mains avra a garder,</l>
            <l n="30">si ne m’en sai vengier fors au plourer;</l>
            <l n="31">car ki Amors destruit et desirete</l>
            <l n="32">ne s’en set ou clamer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="5" type="stanza">
            <l n="33">Sour toute joie est cele coronee</l>
            <l n="34">ke j’ai d’Amors; Diex, i faurai je dont?</l>
            <l n="35">Oïl, par Dieu, tex est ma destinee,</l>
            <l n="36">car tel destin mi doinent li felon;</l>
            <l n="37">si sevent bien k’il font grant mesprison,</l>
            <l n="38">car ki ce taut dont ne puet faire don</l>
            <l n="39">il en conquiert anemis et mellee:</l>
            <l n="40">n’i fait se perdre non.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="6" type="stanza">
            <l n="41">Si coiement est ma dolors celee</l>
            <l n="42">k’a mon samblant ne la reconoist on;</l>
            <l n="43">se ne fuissent la gens maleüree</l>
            <l n="44">n’eüsse pas sospiré em pardon:</l>
            <l n="45">Amors m’eüst doné son guerredon;</l>
            <l n="46">mais en cel point ke dui avoir mon don,</l>
            <l n="47">lor fu m’amors ensegnïe et mostree:</l>
            <l n="48">ja n’aient il pardon!</l>
          </lg>
        </div><div type="text" xml:lang="en ">
          <p>Luca Barbieri 2015</p>
        </div><div type="text" xml:lang="it ">
          <p>Luca Barbieri 2015</p>
        </div></body><back>
      <div type="historical" xml:lang="en">
        <head> Historical context and dating </head>
        <p>It is fruitless to speculate about the possibility of deducing the relative chronology of
          the Châtelain de Coucy’s two “crusade songs”, as Bédier 1909, p. 100 does, even if it is
          true that RS 985 seems to describe an initial phase of love, which ought logically to
          precede that described in RS 679; but there is no need even to mention how risky it is to
          apply overly autobiographical and chronological criteria to the medieval French lyric. It
          can simply be said that if RS 679, as a <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi>, was
          composed just before departure, RS 985, given the generic indication of future departure
          on crusade contained in v. 8, could have been composed at any time between the Châtelain
          taking the cross and the beginning of the Third or Fourth Crusade. Nothing is known about
          the date when he first took the cross, while in the case of the Fourth Crusade
          Villehardouin, § 7 tells us that the Châtelain did so between the beginning of Advent (28
          November) 1199 and the start of Lent (23 February) 1200.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="historical" xml:lang="it">
        <head> Contesto storico e datazione </head>
        <p>Non si può speculare sulla possibilità di dedurre dal testo delle due “canzoni di
          crociata” del Castellano di Coucy l’eventuale anteriorità dell’una rispetto all’altra,
          come fa Bédier 1909, p. 100, anche se è vero che la canzone RS 985 sembra descrivere una
          fase iniziale dell’amore, che dovrebbe precedere quella descritta nella RS 679; ma non
          occorre ricordare quanto sia rischioso applicare criteri eccessivamente autobiografici e
          cronologici alla lirica francese medievale. Si può solo dire che se la RS 679, in quanto
            <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi>, dovrebbe essere stata composta
          nell’imminenza della partenza, la RS 985, visto l’accenno generico alla futura partenza
          per la crociata contenuto nel v. 8, potrebbe essere stata scritta in qualsiasi momento tra
          la presa di croce e l’inizio della terza o della quarta crociata. Nulla si sa sulla data
          della prima presa di croce, mentre nel caso della quarta crociata la testimonianza di
          Villehardouin, § 7 ci permette di sapere che il Castellano di Coucy prese la croce a una
          data compresa tra l’inizio dell’Avvento (28 novembre) del 1199 e l’inizio della Quaresima
          (23 febbraio) del 1200.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="notes" xml:lang="en">
        <head> Notes </head>
        <p>This text is neither a <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> nor a crusade song as
          it is traditionally understood, but a classic song of courtly love which begins in the
          light style of a pastourelle to end tragically because of the lady’s indifference and the
          pernicious action of the slanderers. The only sign of departure on crusade occurs in v. 8,
          at the end of the first stanza, but this simple indication referring to a figure such as
          the Châtelain de Coucy, whose actual participation in two crusades is well known, and the
          legend of love and death celebrated in the romance of which he is the protagonist, invite
          us to consider it as integral to the corpus (for other arguments see Dijkstra 1995a,
          55-56). It contains some points of contact with RS 679, where the lady seems indifferent
          to the lover’s suffering (vv. 13-14) and the poet blames the action of the slanderers (vv.
          33-34), but the style of the two texts is very different.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=7)">The beginning of this song is reminiscent of a pastourelle
          both for its frequent diminutives and for the reference to nakedness; see for example the
          “canso-pastourelle” of Jocelin de Dijon RS 95, 11-20. The explicit references to nakedness
          are not very common in the OF lyric and nearly all are in genres other than the courtly
          love song. </p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=8)">The various strategies adopted by the manuscript tradition
          (ançoiz qu’aille, ains que voise, ains que j’aille, ains k’en aille), which even lead to
          the production of hypermetric readings such as those of L (ains que je m’en voise) and UV
          (ainz que je voise), suggest the existence of an original hiatus ains ke aille.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=10)">C’s hypometric reading and the initial diffraction of the
          tradition (ja ne, je ne, que ne, qu’onc ne, qu’ains ne) suggest the existence of an
          original initial ne ne, wih syllabic repetition having led to the suppression of an
          element (as attestated by C). Such a solution is made difficilior from the fact that in
          this case the sentence is linked to a previous positive statement (but the possibility of
          this usage is documentated by Ménard § 214, pp. 198-199; for the series ne ne see Ménard §
          419 point 1°, p. 332), and compare AMa in v. 28.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro[range(@n=14,@n=15)]">The main problem with v. 14 concerns the
          presence or absence of an initial negation, which leads to two different interpretations.
          The variant with a negation is attestated by mss. CU+KLPVX and accepted by all editors,
          but it has every appearance of a facilior and trivial interpretation. It is possible
          however to remain faithful to AMOR3Ta if we understand the two verbs as feudal metaphors
          (retenir means “take into service”, while quiter means “free from service”; compare the
          similar interpretation of Bédier 1909 and Lerond 1964), or even in the literal sense
          (“keep with her” and “leave, abandon”) meaning “if she wants to take me and (then) leave
          me”, or else “if she wants to take me (into her service) and free me”; in this case the
          negation does not seem necessary. Concerning v. 15, it should be recalled that prometre
          can also mean “concede, grant some hope” or “ordain” (cfr. God X, 430c and VI, 432a) and
          the first sense seems particularly interesting, given the use of the subjunctive which
          could be interpreted as indicating a wish along the lines of si m’aït Diex.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=19)">The idea of mockery inherent in the reading quant de moi rit
          di MOR3T is never otherwise attestated in this form in OF lyric and fits ill with the idea
          of the “sweet death” expressed in the following line. It must refer to a smile, perhaps
          cruel, but nonetheless a real smile, so the reading ele se rit is preferable, unanimously
          attested by the mss. of the other two families and also supported by Aa. See for example
          Tristan en prose (ed. Curtis) III, iii, 688, 55 (p. 14): Amors me rit, et puis me point
          jusques au sanc.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=23)">ACUa’s reading is the only one that does not syntactically
          link this line to the previous one, thus avoiding an awkward contradiction (it does not
          make much sense to say the lady is killing the poet because he has loved her faithfully
          after having just said she has no reason to do so); it seems much better to isolate vv.
          23-24 syntactically and interpret them as meaning that precisely because the poet has
          loved the lady faithfully, she has no excuse.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=35)">I do not share the opinion of Lerond 1964, p. 81 who see in
          MR3T’s nenil/naie a lectio difficilior, justifying it with a strained interpretation. It
          seems rather that the negation is a lectio facilior arising from the idea that the poet
          cannot passively resign himself to an unrewarding fate. But such a fate is made inevitable
          by the interference of the slanderers and in any case the expression teux est mon destin /
          ma destinee in the OF lyric nearly always expresses the idea of resignation to a negative
          situation. Compare RS 679, 9-11: Beaus sire Diex, k’iert il dont et coment? / convenra il
          k’ens la fin congié praigne? / Oïl, par Dieu, ne puet estre autrement.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro[range(@n=38,@n=39)]">This phrase with its proverbial overtones is
          not entirely clear, even if the general sense is intelligible: the slanderers who take
          away the joy of love will not be able to restore it. Certain exceptions to the formula
          faire don could suggest a passive sense (“receive as a gift, freely”), in which case it
          would have the much clearer sense of “who takes away what he cannot receive as a gift”;
          but it could also be interpreted more simply as “who takes away (from others) what he
          himself cannot give”, in other words love. See Colin Muset RS 989, 8-12: Amors ont malvais
          renon, / car li riche al cuer felon / sont amé por faire don, / et li cortois povres hom /
          aime seus.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="notes" xml:lang="it">
        <head> Note </head>
        <p>Non si tratta in questo caso né di una <hi rend="italic">chanson de départie</hi> né
          tantomeno di una canzone di crociata tradizionalmente intesa, ma di una classica canzone
          d’amore cortese che inizia con lo stile leggero di una pastorella per finire tragicamente
          a causa dell’indifferenza della dama e dell’azione perniciosa dei calunniatori. L’unico
          accenno alla partenza per la crociata si trova al v. 8, alla fine della prima strofa, ma
          questo semplice accenno riferito a un personaggio come il Castellano di Coucy di cui si
          conosce l’effettiva partecipazione a due crociate e la leggenda d’amore e morte celebrata
          nel romanzo che lo vede protagonista invita a considerarla parte integrante del corpus
          (per altri argomenti si veda Dijkstra 1995a, 55-56). Si può trovare inoltre qualche punto
          di contatto con la canzone RS 679, dove la dama sembra indifferente alle sofferenze
          dell’amante (vv. 13-14) e il poeta biasima l’azione dei calunniatori (vv. 33-34), ma lo
          stile dei due testi è comunque molto diverso.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=7)">L’inizio di questa canzone ricorda una pastorella anche per i
          frequenti diminutivi e il riferimento alla nudità; si veda per esempio la
          “canzone-pastorella” di Jocelin de Dijon RS 95, 11-20. I riferimenti espliciti alla nudità
          non sono molto numerosi nella lirica francese e quasi tutti al di fuori della canzone
          cortese.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=8)">Le molteplici strategie dilatatorie adottate dalla tradizione
          manoscritta (ançoiz qu’aille, ains que voise, ains que j’aille, ains k’en aille), che
          arrivano fino alla produzione di lezioni ipermetriche come quella di L (ains que je m’en
          voise) e di UV (ainz que je voise) suggeriscono l’esistenza di uno iato originario ains ke
          aille.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=10)">La lezione ipometrica di C e la diffrazione iniziale della
          tradizione (ja ne, je ne, que ne, qu’onc ne, qu’ains ne) fa sospettare l’esistenza di un
          originale ne ne iniziale, con ripetizione sillabica che ha facilitato la soppressione di
          un elemento (come attestato da C). Tale soluzione è resa difficilior dal fatto che in
          questo caso la frase è coordinata a una prima sentenza positiva (ma la possibilità di
          questo uso è documentata da Ménard § 214, pp. 198-199; per la successione ne ne si veda
          Ménard § 419 punto 1°, p. 332), ed è in ogni caso attestata dai mss. AMa al v. 28.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro[range(@n=14,@n=15)]">Il problema principale del v. 14 riguarda la
          presenza o l’assenza di una negazione iniziale, che porta a due interpretazioni diverse.
          La variante con negazione è attestata dai mss. CU+KLPVX ed è accolta da tutti i principali
          editori, ma ha tutta l’aria di un’interpretazione facilior e scontata. Si potrebbe invece
          restare fedeli a AMOR3Ta intendendo i due verbi come metafore feudali (retenir significa
          “prendere al servizio”, mentre quiter significa “liberare dal servizio”; si veda del resto
          l’interpretazione in questa direzione di Bédier 1909 e Lerond 1964) o anche in senso
          proprio (in questo caso “tenere con sé” e “lasciare, abbandonare”) col significato di “se
          mi vuole prendere e (poi) lasciare”, oppure “se mi vuole prendere (al suo servizio) e
          liberare”; in questo caso la negazione non mi pare affatto necessaria. Per quanto riguarda
          il v. 15, va ricordato che prometre può significare anche “concedere, dare una speranza” o
          “ordinare” (cfr. God X, 430c e VI, 432a) e soprattutto il primo significato sembra
          interessante, visto l’uso del congiuntivo che potrebbe essere interpretato con valore
          ottativo analogo al tipo si m’aït Diex.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=19)">Il valore di scherno insito nella lezione quant de moi rit
          di MOR3T non è mai attestato in questa forma nella lirica francese e si adatta male
          all’idea della “dolce morte” espressa nel verso successivo. Deve trattarsi di un sorriso,
          forse crudele, ma pur sempre di un vero sorriso, e per questo si preferisce in questo caso
          la lezione ele se rit attestata in modo compatto dai testimoni delle altre due famiglie e
          confermata anche da Aa. Si veda per esempio Tristan en prose (ed. Curtis) III, iii, 688,
          55 (p. 14): Amors me rit, et puis me point jusques au sanc.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=23)">La lezione di ACUa è l’unica che non lega sintatticamente
          questo verso al precedente, evitando così una fastidiosa contraddizione (non ha molto
          senso dire che la dama uccide l’autore per il fatto che egli l’ha amata lealmente dopo
          aver appena detto che non ha nessun motivo per farlo); mi sembra molto più efficace
          isolare sintatticamente i vv. 23-24 e interpretarli nel senso che proprio perché l’autore
          ha amato lealmente la dama, questa non ha alcuna scusa.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro:(n=35)">Non condivido l’opinione di Lerond 1964, p. 81 che vede in
          nenil/naie di MR3T una lectio difficilior giustificandola con un’interpretazione troppo
          forzata per essere plausibile. Mi sembra al contrario che la negazione sia una lectio
          facilior suscitata dall’idea che l’autore non possa rassegnarsi passivamente a un destino
          ingrato. Ma tale destino è reso inevitabile dall’intervento dei calunniatori e in ogni
          caso l’espressione teux est mon destin / ma destinee nella lirica francese esprime quasi
          sempre l’idea di rassegnazione a un’opzione negativa. Si veda peraltro la corrispondenza
          con RS 679, 9-11: Beaus sire Diex, k’iert il dont et coment? / convenra il k’ens la fin
          congié praigne? / Oïl, par Dieu, ne puet estre autrement.</p>
        <p corresp="#rs.985.fro[range(@n=38,@n=39)]">Questa frase dal sapore proverbiale non è
          chiarissima, anche se il senso generale è comprensibile: i calunniatori che sottraggono la
          gioia d’amore alla fine non potranno che rimetterci. Alcune accezioni della formula faire
          don potrebbero far pensare a un uso in senso passivo (“ricevere in regalo,
          gratuitamente”), nel qual caso si avrebbe il senso molto più chiaro di “chi sottrae ciò
          che non può avere in dono”; ma si potrebbe anche interpretare più semplicemente “chi
          sottrae (ad altri) ciò che lui stesso non può offrire”, cioè amore. Si veda Colin Muset RS
          989, 8-12: Amors ont malvais renon, / car li riche al cuer felon / sont amé por faire don,
          / et li cortois povres hom / aime seus.</p>
      </div>
    </back></text></TEI>
