<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title/>
        <author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author>
        <funder>AHRC</funder>
        <principal>Linda Paterson</principal>
        <editor>The person who did the editing</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Steve Ranford</name>
          <resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name>joe bloggs</name>
          <resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2014-05-06</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
          authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher>
        <date>2014</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl type="previous_editions">
          <head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head>
          <bibl>Raynaud 1887; Paris – Mas Latrie 1906; Kohler 1913; Melani 1994, 126.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="essential_bibliography">
          <bibl>Bromiley 1977: Geoffrey N. Bromiley, «Philip of Novara’s account of the war between
            Frederick II of Hohenstaufen and the Ibelins», Journal of Medieval History, 3, 1977, pp.
            325-337.</bibl>
          <bibl>Edbury 1991: Peter W. Edbury, The Kingdom of Cyprus and the Crusades (1191-1374),
            Cambridge University Press,1991.</bibl>
          <bibl>Edbury 1997: Peter W. Edbury, John of Ibelin and the Kingdom of Jerusalem,
            Woodbridge, The Boydell Press, 2007.</bibl>
          <bibl>Hill 1948: George Hill, A History of Cyprus, II, The Frankish Period (1192-1432),
            Cambridge University Press, 1948.</bibl>
          <bibl>Jacoby 1984: David Jacoby, «La littérature française dans les états latins de la
            Méditerranée orientale à l’époque des croisades: diffusion et création», in Essor et
            fortune de la Chanson de geste dans l’Europe et l’Orient latin, actes du IXe congrès
            international de la Société Rencesvals pour l’étude des épopées romanes, Padoue-Venise,
            29 août - 4 septembre 1982, II, Modena, Mucchi, 1984, pp. 617-646.</bibl>
          <bibl>Kohler 1913: Philippe de Novare, Mémoires, édités par Charles Kohler, Paris,
            Champion, 1913.</bibl>
          <bibl>La Monte – Hubert 1936: John L. La Monte, Merton J. Hubert, The Wars of Frederick II
            against the Ibelins in Syria and Cyprus, New York, Columbia University Press,
            1936.</bibl>
          <bibl>La Monte 1937: John L. La Monte, «John d’Ibelin, the Old Lord of Beirut, 1177-1236»,
            Byzantion, 12, 1937, pp. 417-448.</bibl>
          <bibl>Lefèvre 1998: Sylvie Lefèvre, «Philippe de Novare, Mémoires. Notice», in Le Roman de
            Renart, édition publiée sous la direction d’Armand Strubel, Paris, Gallimard, 1998, pp.
            1386-1393.</bibl>
          <bibl>Mas Latrie 1852-1861: Louis de Mas Latrie, Histoire de l’île de Chypre sous le règne
            des princes de la maison de Lusignan, 3 voll., Paris, Imprimerie impériale,
            1852-1861.</bibl>
          <bibl>Melani 1994: Guerra di Federico II in Oriente (1223-1242), introduzione, testo
            critico, traduzione e note a cura di Silvio Melani, Napoli, Liguori, 1994.</bibl>
          <bibl>Paris 1890: Gaston Paris, «Philippe de Novare», Romania, 19, 1890, pp.
            99-102.</bibl>
          <bibl>Paris 1902: Gaston Paris, «Les Mémoires de Philippe de Novare», Revue de l’Orient
            latin, 9, 1902, pp. 164-205, poi in Gaston Paris, Mélanges de littérature française du
            Moyen Âge, publiés par Mario Roques, Paris, Champion, 1912, pp. 427-470.</bibl>
          <bibl>Paris – Mas Latrie 1906: Les Gestes des Chiprois, éd. Gaston Paris et Louis de Mas
            Latrie, in Recueil des Historiens des Croisades, Documents Armeniens, II, Paris,
            Imprimerie nationale, 1906, pp. 653-872.</bibl>
          <bibl>Raynaud 1887: Les Gestes des Chiprois, recueil de chroniques françaises écrites en
            Orient aux XIIIe et XIVe siècles (Philippe de Navarre et Gérard de Monréal), publié pour
            la première fois pour la Société de l’Orient latin par Gaston Raynaud, Genève, Fick,
            1887.</bibl>
          <bibl>Tanniou 2013: Florence Tanniou, «L’Histoire entre chronique et travestissement dans
            les Mémpores de Philippe de Novare: le sens des métamorphoses», comunicazione orale al
            colloquio Parodie courtoises / Parodies de la courtoisie, XIVth Congress of the
            International Courtly Litterature Society, Lisbon, 22-27 July 2013.</bibl>
          <bibl>Cronache.</bibl>
          <bibl>Amadi: Chroniques d’Amadi et de Strambaldi, publiées par M. René de Mas Latrie, I,
            Chronique d’Amadi, Paris, Imprimerie nationale, 1891.</bibl>
          <bibl>Bustrone: Chronique de l’île de Chypre par Florio Bustron, publiée par M. René de
            Mas Latrie, Paris, Imprimerie nationale, 1884.</bibl>
          <bibl>Continuation Rothelin: Continuation de Guillaume de Tyr, de 1229 à 1261, dite du
            manuscrit de Rothelin, in Recueil des historiens des croisades, publié par les soins de
            l’Académie des Inscriptions et des Belles-Lettres, Historiens occidentaux, II, Paris,
            Imprimerie impériale, 1859, pp. 485-639 (traduz. inglese: Crusader Syria in the
            Thirteenth Century. The Rothelin Continuation of the History of William of Tyre with
            part of the Eracles or Acre text. Edited by Janet Shirley, Aldershot, Ashgate,
            1999).</bibl>
          <bibl>Eracles: L’estoire de Eracles empereur et la conqueste de la terre d’Outremer, in
            Recueil des historiens des croisades, publié par les soins de l’Académie des
            Inscriptions et des Belles-Lettres, Historiens occidentaux, II, Paris, Imprimerie
            impériale, 1859, pp. 1-481 (traduz. inglese: Crusader Syria in the Thirteenth Century.
            The Rothelin Continuation of the History of William of Tyre with part of the Eracles or
            Acre text. Edited by Janet Shirley, Aldershot, Ashgate, 1999).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>Turin, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 39r (47r); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (modern
            copy of the Turin ms. made by Carlo Perrin and checked by Gaston Raynaud against the
            original), f. 47r. As usual it has been possible to follow the graphy and readings of
            the Turin ms., only correcting the hypometric vv. 1 and 9 and the hypermetric v. 2; the
            translation is that of Melani 1994 with a few modifications.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Mss. </head>
          <bibl>Torino, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 39r (47r); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (copia
            moderna del ms. di Torino eseguita da Carlo Perrin e ricontrollata da Gaston Raynaud
            sull’originale), f. 47r. Come di consueto si rispetta il più possibile la grafia e la
            lezione del manoscritto di Torino, correggendo solo le ipometrie (vv. 1 e 9) e
            ipermetrie (v. 2); la traduzione è quella di Melani 1994 con qualche modifica.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <metDecl pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;" xml:lang="en"><p>10a’b’b’a’ccd’d’ (MW 1431,6 =
        Frank 577); 2 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rhyme a = <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>; rhyme b = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rhyme c = <hi rend="italic">-o(u)r</hi>; rhyme d = <hi rend="italic">-endre</hi>; identical versification and rhymes in
        the “sirventes” RS 184a; one approximate rhyme in v. 12 (<hi rend="italic">terre</hi> rhymes
        in <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>).</p></metDecl>
      <metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>10a’b’b’a’ccd’d’ (MW 1431,6 =
        Frank 577); 2 <hi rend="italic">coblas unissonans</hi>; rima a = <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>; rima b = <hi rend="italic">-ie</hi>; rima c = <hi rend="italic">-o(u)r</hi>;
        rima d = <hi rend="italic">-endre</hi>; stesso schema e rime del “sirventese” RS 184a; una
        rima imperfetta per l’orecchio al v. 12 (<hi rend="italic">terre</hi> in rima con <hi rend="italic">-aire</hi>).</p></metDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange>
        <change><date>2014-05-06T16:17:16Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader><text><front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Philippe de Novare</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub"/>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor/>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract"/>
    </front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.190a.en" xml:lang="en">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div type="stanza">
            <p><hi rend="italic">This is the rhyme which Sir Philippe de Novare composed when he was
                wounded outside the castle of Dieudamour, during the siege:</hi></p>
          </div>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>I am wounded, but still I cannot be silent concerning Sir Renart and the rest of his
              company, which because of him is starving and dishonoured inside Maupertuis, where he
              is taking refuge. But if Renart is in fear for his life, what harm have the other
              vavassors and the sergeants done? Why are they allowing themselves to be sold? Someone
              is keeping them waiting [for reinforcements] like fools.</p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Renart knows more about treachery than Ganelon, who betrayed France. He has stuffed
              his den full of food: he has instated himself there to rule the land and dupes them
              every day concerning peace. Anyone who serves such a traitor is much dishonoured: so
              he can be served he has him hanged here outside, but he makes the ones inside take
              flight.</p>
          </div>
        </div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.190a.it" xml:lang="it">
          <head> Translation </head>
          <div type="stanza">
            <p><hi rend="italic">Questo è il componimento che messer Filippo da Novara fece, quando
                fu ferito davanti al castello di Diodamore, nel corso dell’assedio:</hi></p>
          </div>
          <div n="1" type="stanza">
            <p>Ferito son, ma ancora non posso stare zitto<lb/>su don Rainardo e il resto della sua
              compagnia,<lb/>che per sua colpa ha fame ed è disonorata<lb/>là dentro a Malpertugio,
              dove egli si rifugia.<lb/>Ma se Rainardo teme per la sua propria vita<lb/>che male
              hanno mai fatto quegli altri valvassori<lb/>e i sergenti? Perché si lascian cosi
              vendere?<lb/>Come stolti li fa attendere i rinforzi.<lb/></p>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="stanza">
            <p>Rainardo meglio sa tradire assai di quanto<lb/>non seppe fare Gano, che la Francia
              tradi.<lb/>Per sé Rainardo ha empito la sua tana di cibo:<lb/>là dentro egli è
              insediato per governar la terra<lb/>e riguardo alla pace li beffa egli ogni
              giorno.<lb/>Certo è disonorato chi serve il traditore:<lb/>per farsi ben servire lo fa
              impiccar qua fuori,<lb/>e dentro li fa invece fuggir senza ritegno.<lb/></p>
          </div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>
