<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author><name>Linda</name><surname>Paterson</surname></author><funder>AHRC</funder><principal>Linda Paterson</principal><editor>The person who did the editing</editor><respStmt><name>Steve Ranford</name><resp>Conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp></respStmt><respStmt><name>joe bloggs</name><resp>Translation to Italian of xyz</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2014-10-17</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Warwick? (The publisher is the person or institution by whose
            authority a given edition of the file is made public.)</publisher><date>2014</date><availability status="free"><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/"> Distributed under a
              Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License </licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listBibl type="previous_editions"><head> Previous Editions/Edizioni precedenti </head><bibl>Raynaud 1887, 55; Paris – Mas Latrie 1906, 686; Kohler 1913, 30; Melani 1994, 112.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="en"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(2). Turin, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 34r (42r) (T); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (modern copy of the Turin ms. made by Carlo Perrin and checked against the original by Gaston Raynaud), f. 42r.</bibl></listBibl><listBibl type="manuscripts" xml:lang="it"><head> Mss. </head><bibl>(2). Turin, Biblioteca Reale, Varia 433, f. 34r (42r) (T); Paris, BnF, n.a. fr. 6680 (copia moderna del ms. di Torino eseguita da Carlo Perrin e ricontrollata da Gaston Raynaud sull’originale), f. 42r.</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><metDecl xml:lang="en" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>14 laisses in rhymed alexandrines; the meter is typical of the 13th-c. <hi rend="italic">chansons de geste</hi>, also used in the Crusade Cycle (<hi rend="italic">Chanson d’Antioche</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Conquête de Jérusalem</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Chétifs</hi>); numerous lines are hypometric or hypermetric, some of which may be authorial; a single irregular rhyme in v. 44 (simple assonance <hi rend="italic">doute</hi> in a laisse rhyming in <hi rend="italic">-onte</hi>), then two cases of rhymes in mute final <hi rend="italic">s</hi> (<hi rend="italic">estendars</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dars</hi> in vv. 63-64 in a laisse rhyming in <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>). For the metrical and linguistic of Philippe de Novare’s verse texts see Melani 1994, pp. 51 and 61-63.</p></metDecl><metDecl xml:lang="it" pattern="10a&#x2019;ba&#x2019;bba&#x2019;ba&#x2019;"><p>14 lasse rimate di alessandrini; il metro è quello tipico della <hi rend="italic">chanson de geste</hi> del XIII secolo, utilizzato anche nei testi del ciclo delle crociate (<hi rend="italic">Chanson d’Antioche</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Conquête de Jérusalem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chétifs</hi>); numerosi versi presentano ipometrie o ipermetrie, alcune delle quali potrebbero risalire all’autore stesso; una sola rima irregolare al v. 44 (semplice assonanza <hi rend="italic">doute</hi> in una lassa con rima <hi rend="italic">-onte</hi>), più due casi di rima con <hi rend="italic">s</hi> finale muta (<hi rend="italic">estendars</hi> e <hi rend="italic">dars</hi> ai vv. 63-64 in una lassa con rima <hi rend="italic">-art</hi>). Per le particolarità metriche e linguistiche dei testi in versi di Philippe de Novare si veda Melani 1994, pp. 51 e 61-63.</p></metDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="en"><p>The edition entirely follows the graphy of the Turin ms. and substantially follows its readings. The majority of the interventions are made to correct for scansion (hypometric vv. 4, 11, 20, 27, 33, 35, 61, 83 and hypermetric vv. 6, 7, 12, 21, 23, 25, 32, 33, 47, 51, 56, 69); since, as indicated above, the possibility of authorial irregularities cannot be excluded, all corrections are signalled in square brackets and simple suppressions in round brackets.</p></editorialDecl><editorialDecl xml:lang="it"><p>L’edizione rispetta integralmente la grafia e sostanzialmente la lezione del manoscritto di Torino. La maggior parte degli interventi sono volti a sanare le numerose ipometrie (vv. 4, 11, 20, 27, 33, 35, 61, 83) e ipermetrie (vv. 6, 7, 12, 21, 23, 25, 32, 33, 47, 51, 56, 69) del manoscritto; poiché, come si è detto, non è possibile escludere che tali infrazioni risalgano all’originale, tutte le integrazioni sono segnalate tra parentesi quadre e le soppressioni semplici tra parentesi tonde.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2014-10-17T11:19:03Z</date><name>Linda Paterson</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart type="main">Philippe de Novare</titlePart><titlePart type="sub"/></docTitle><docAuthor/></titlePage><div type="abstract"/></front><body><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.- (Verse letter).en" xml:lang="en"><head> Translation </head><p><lb/><hi rend="italic">This is the letter in verse which Sir Philippe de Novare, who was
            cloistered in the Hospital of St John in Nicosia, sent to Sir Balian of Ibelin, who was
            in Acre.</hi></p><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Dear lord and dear friend, the hermit who is now a novice brother sends you more than a hundred thousand greetings. Were it not for the white cross, there would be every reason for him to sing the hours and an entire Mass [for his funeral]. </p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>My friend, your land now resembles Spain, for in it there are five bailiffs in a single band. They showed me great love so that I would swear allegiance to them; but I opposed this, and they were so underhand that without me having been judged by a court and without further ado they ordered me to be taken and thrown in the privy. That night they really behaved like Germans: they had the doors guarded and were all deadly serious; the grim-faced man who placed them there was the one who measured his own length on the field.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>That night I never saw such a wild beast as the one who banged his head in the middle of the field. Please God, he will have such a beating throughout his life, since every year there is a feast for all the great saints.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>This is how I was arrested in court that night; fine words and request for a trial were fruitless; and this is how the cunning traitors guarded me. Then they wanted to kill me treacherously during the night, but I was warned by someone who, I think, gave me good and loyal counsel – whoever may be annoyed at this.</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>I therefore put on the mantle of St John as fast as possible, but trust in God that I shall leave the order very soon; had I known that Balian and Ansel the Snub-nosed would arrive, I would have changed my tune.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>The one who fell off his horse in the lists forced me to flee to the Hospital. My God! If they had had that traitor killed so many evils would never have befallen Cyprus.</p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>If Ansel the Snub-nosed had been allowed to do what he wanted when he performed the great «flatimus» (fall), the «benedicamus» of the Mass would have been said (all would have been over and done with). Everyone would have said «Deo gratias dicamus» (thank God for that),</p></div><div n="8" type="stanza"><p>if the blessing had been pronounced on his song (if that had been the end of his exploits)! Balian, do not forget the irons or the grim prison! I would willingly keep silent about it, but it is known everywhere.</p></div><div n="9" type="stanza"><p>If you were arrested you are not shamed by it, since the one who seized you has seized both king and count; but what makes me furious is that everyone says repeatedly that the one who ordered this is reviled by everyone; but this shows clearly he is very afraid of you.</p></div><div n="10" type="stanza"><p>Balian, do not allow it to happen during your lifetime that a man ransomed from the field should get the better of you. Do remember my lord Philip of Nablus and your good uncle, for this is most fitting for you.</p></div><div n="11" type="stanza"><p>For God’s sake! The two Philips, of Nablus and of Ibelin, and your father’s uncle, my lord Baldwin, never bowed or bent their heads for anything; and if you give up because of five miserable scoundrels, may the God who destroyed and ruined Cain destroy and ruin you too if you do not bring things to a conclusion.</p></div><div n="12" type="stanza"><p>For God’s sake! Set aside your loves of Acre, and you and Sir Badger (?), who thinks he is a leopard, [. . . ] For a miserable fox, who fell from his grey horse, and who was advancing from there, even the Longobards [. . .]. If you love the women, who have had had their part [in the suffering], please save them from the siege! Both Grimbert and Renart, who have fixed their banners before the Hospital, make those who hold the village stand guard every night with lances and arrows, and deny us justice. The ladies are in there with just one single Lombard. How can you bear it, you cowardly recreant? When I see them (the bailiffs) I remember the day after Easter, God help me: my whole heart burns in fury, because each of them acts like a king as long as he has his share. This is a game for overgrown children, God help me: they are kings for a day, then the next they are back to what they were.</p></div><div n="13" type="stanza"><p>I cannot help laughing when I see them as regents: Hugh with his twisted mouth, who abjures nobility; William of Rivet, who thinks he is so wise, and lulls them with his evil speech; and Renart, who is an expert at breaking pledges; Amaury and Gauvain, who are not of the same lineage; you know them all well. No-one is more barbaric: if I make songs or rhymes about them this is no great outrage: I am the nightingale, since they have put me in a cage.</p></div><div n="14" type="stanza"><p>No-one should blame me if there are some bad rhymes in it, or irregular lines, for this is the first draft; if I am in the cage much longer I will finish my rhyme: the next one will be equivocal at least, or leonine.</p></div></div><div type="translation" xml:id="rs.- (Verse letter).it" xml:lang="it"><head> Translation </head><p><lb/><hi rend="italic">Questa è la lettera in versi che messer Filippo da Novara, che era chiuso nell’Ospedale di San Giovanni a Nicosia mandò a messer Baliano d’Ibelin, il quale si trovava ad Acri.</hi></p><div n="1" type="stanza"><p>Più di centomila salve, bel signore e bel compare,<lb/>a voi manda l’eremita che è fratello, ora, novizio.<lb/>Se non fosse per la croce bianca, ci sarebbe tanto<lb/> perché adesso egli cantasse le ore con la messa intera.</p></div><div n="2" type="stanza"><p>Compare, la vostra terra assomiglia ora alla Spagna<lb/>ché ci son cinque reggenti in un’unica brigata.<lb/>Han mostrato gran bontà per avere il giuramento.<lb/> Però a questo io mi opposi. Tale n’ebbero dispetto<lb/>che senza esser giudicato da una corte e senza indugio<lb/>ordinarono di prendermi e ficcarmi in gattabuia.<lb/>Essi proprio hanno imitato, quella notte, la Germania:<lb/>guardar fecero le porte: non c’è chi sia neghittoso;<lb/>diede le disposizioni quello dal volto rapace<lb/>che col proprio corpo prese le misure alla campagna.</p></div><div n="3" type="stanza"><p>Io non vidi quella notte animal cosi selvaggio<lb/>quanto quello che distese la sua testa in mezzo al campo.<lb/>Se Dio vuole, per la vita avrà quello tal tempesta,<lb/>perché a tutti i grandi santi ciascun anno si fa festa.</p></div><div n="4" type="stanza"><p>Venni dunque imprigionato laggiù in corte quella notte:<lb/>bel parlare e domandare un processo, ciò fu invano,<lb/>così fui guardato a vista dai felloni traditori.<lb/>Poi volevano ammazzarmi nella notte, a tradimento,<lb/>ma di ciò qualcun mi disse (si dispiaccia pur chi vuole,<lb/>ché costui mi diede – credo – un fidato e buon consiglio).</p></div><div n="5" type="stanza"><p>Allacciai dunque al più presto il mantel di San Giovanni,<lb/>ma confido in Dio che presto ne sarò già uscito fuori;<lb/>e se avessi allor saputo che Baliano giungerebbe<lb/>e con lui il camuso Ancello avrei detto altro banno.</p></div><div n="6" type="stanza"><p>Quello che si era nascosto tra la lizza ed il cavallo<lb/>m’ha cacciato e messo a forza quaggiù dentro all’Ospedale.<lb/>Dio! Se avessero lasciato ammazzar quel traditore<lb/>tanto male di sicuro non avremmo avuto in Cipro. </p></div><div n="7" type="stanza"><p>Se risolver si lasciava ad Ancello il Camuso<lb/>quando quello dal cavallo fece il grande ruzzolone<lb/>della messa era già detto il suo «benedicamus»:<lb/>tutti avrebbero poi detto: «Deo gratias dicamus»</p></div><div n="8" type="stanza"><p>se a quel tempo fosse stata posta fine alla sua gesta.<lb/>Baliano, non scordate ferri né dura prigione:<lb/>volentier ne avrei taciuto, ma dovunque lo si sa. </p></div><div n="9" type="stanza"><p>Della vostra prigionia non portate voi vergogna,<lb/>perché quello che vi prese ha già preso e re e conti.<lb/>Però questo mi fa rabbia, che chiunque parla dice<lb/>che l’ha fatto far colui ch’è del mondo il vituperio.<lb/>Ma da ciò si vede bene ch’egli gran tema ha di voi. </p></div><div n="10" type="stanza"><p>Baliano, non lasciate che, voi vivo, vi succeda<lb/>che uno che fu riscattato l’abbia vinta su di voi;<lb/>in voi torni la memoria di Filippo di Nablus<lb/>e del vostro grande zio, poiché ben vi si conviene. </p></div><div n="11" type="stanza"><p>Sì, per Dio, quei due Filippi, di Nablus e d’Ibelin<lb/>e lo zio di vostro padre, che era sire Baldovino,<lb/>mai non tennero per nulla fronte bassa e capo chino;<lb/>e se voi la date vinta a quei cinque mascalzoni<lb/>quell’Iddio che già distrusse, confondendolo, Caino<lb/>vi distrugga e vi confonda, se non ne venite a capo. </p></div><div n="12" type="stanza"><p>Per Dio, i vostri amori d’Acri, su, metteteli da parte<lb/>e voi con messere tasso (?), che si crede esser leopardo<lb/>[. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ]<lb/>Per un misero volpone, che dal grigio giù cascò,<lb/>e che già di qua s’avanza, che perfino i Longobardi<lb/>[. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .]<lb/>Se le dame avete a cuore, che han passato i loro guai,<lb/>su, toglietele d’assedio! Sia Grimberto, sia Rainardo,<lb/>che davanti all’Ospedale han piantato gli stendardi,<lb/>ogni notte fanno stare di guardia con lance e frecce<lb/>quelli che occupano il borgo, e ci negano giustizia!<lb/>Assediate son le dame, con un unico Lombardo:<lb/>come fate a sopportarlo, miserabile codardo?<lb/>Dio mi guardi, ché mi sembra l’indomani dopo Pasqua,<lb/>allorquando qua li vedo. Tutto il cuore mi si infiamma,<lb/>perché ognuno si fa re, basta che si trovi quarto:<lb/>questo è un gioco da bambini, se Dio vuole, un po’ cresciuti:<lb/>solo un giorno fanno i re, poi ritornan quel che sono. </p></div><div n="13" type="stanza"><p>Le risate non trattengo se li vedo alla reggenza:<lb/>Ugo con la bocca storta, che smentisce nobiltà;<lb/>poi Guglielmo di Rivet, che si dà le arie d’un saggio,<lb/>che col suo dire maligno tutti li manda in sollucchero;<lb/>e Rainardo che sa bene come infrangere gli impegni;<lb/>Amalrico con Galvano, che non sono d’un lignaggio:<lb/>tutti ben li conoscete: nessuno è cosi selvaggio.<lb/>Se canzoni o rime faccio su di loro non è oltraggio:<lb/>sono come l’usignolo, posto che m’han messo in gabbia. </p></div><div n="14" type="stanza"><p>Non ne devo portar pena, se c’è qualche rima falsa,<lb/>se le strofe son confuse, questa è sol la prima veste:<lb/>se più a lungo resto in gabbia limerò la mia poesia,<lb/>così che avrà rime equivoche o leonine perlomeno. </p></div></div></body></text></TEI>
